<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 >
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Charles Eyre Pascoe: selected journalism</title>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Compiled by </resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>Page scans of The Standard for November 5, 8, and 11 1877 from the British Newspaper Archive. </p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2026-06-25">Tagged in TEI and exposed on Digital Lacy website</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
<text><front>
  <p>According to the report of Pascoe's death published by the <title>Sutton and Cheam Advertiser</title> on 17 November 1912, <q>he joined the staff of “The Standard,” and wrote for that paper some striking articles on canal life. </q>. A search through the British Newspaper Archive throws up some unsigned articles which read very much like Pascoe's work, though other confirmatory evidence is hard to find. </p><p>For a more up to date perspective on the legislation these articles cautiously welcome, see
 <bibl>`Social Policy and the "Floating Population". The Administration of the Canal Boats Acts 1877-1899' by 
 Roy M. MacLeod
 <title>Past &amp; Present</title>, No. 35 (Dec., 1966), pp. 101-132 </bibl>
</p></front>

<body>
 <div xml:id="Std_1877-08-96">
  <head> LIFE ON A CANAL BOAT </head>
  <head> (FROM OUR SPECIAL COMMISSIONER.) </head>
  <dateline>BRAUNSTON, Tuesday.</dateline>
  <p> Braunston is a straggling village, with a church and parsonage, on the borders of
   Northamptonshire. I am particular in mentioning this, for with the exception of the church, which
   has some pretensions to architectural merit, and the parsonage, which is as pretty in its
   surroundings as can well be imagined, there is nothing to commend itself to the notice of the
   visitor to the village of Braunston, The Oxford Canal lies in the valley at the foot of the hill
   leading from Dunchurch and Rugby (from which latter town it is distant eight miles), and crossing
   a bridge, and walking a hundred or so yards up the main road, you reach the terminal station on
   the Grand Junction Canal. A few red brick buildings, a blacksmith's forge, the curate’s cosy
   dwelling among the trees, a half-dozen or so dilapidated cottages, and a basin or dock for the
   repair of broken-down barges, constitute the principal features of the station. I was anxious to
   reach Braunston, because I had been given to understand that it was a rallying ground for the
   boatmen, and besides was the place where dwelt a gentleman who knew about as much of barges,
   bargemen, barge women, and, their children as any man in England, When, therefore, Braunston
   Basin hove in sight from the ricketty plank thrown across the barge’s tarpaulin, doing duty as
   the boat's bridge, I was glad. I may say, indeed, that rejoiced for more reasons than one. I had
   had enough of barge life for the present, and would fain have changed my resting place. among the
   sugar bags for the more comfortable repose of the village inn.</p>
  <p> This morning Captain Jonah took the opportunity of having a few words of friendly conversation
   with me on the canal bank. He wished me clearly to understand the position of affairs as far as
   himself and family were concerned. ‘Look you,” said the, skipper," things could not be wuss with
   me and mine than they is at present, We're bound to be done some good by if they carries out this
   education of the children. Trade’s awfu’ bad, Prices is down to nothin’ on account of the
   comp'tition with the railroad. It’s as much as us can do to make both ends meet now. If they
   takes the chidr'n they takes in course the mothers, and if they takes the mothers that means
   rising the wages. D'yer see?” I gave Captain Jonah to understand I quite saw that; but I said
   that I should like to have a few figures from him, if he would not mind giving them, in reference
   to this same subject of wages. I ascertained from him that at present the boatmen calculate to
   make from five to seven pounds for the round “voyage” from London to Birmingham and back, which,
   including stoppages, occupies about fourteen days. Out of this sum they have to find the cost of
   a horse, provender, stabling, and so forth, and money for ropes, lines, and straps used in
   drawing the boat, Pressing the skipper closely, I found that he considered 2l. 5s. a week was but
   a fair wage for the labour of himself, the wife, and Joe. At the very least 2l. clear ought to.
   be earned, and if they took the children away, this sum would have to be raised to meet the
   additional expense of rent for a cottage for the wife, and schooling for the children. Such in
   brief were Captain Jonah’s views with regard to the Canal Boats Act. A “mate” of his being in
   charge of a barge in our wake, I took occasion to have a few words of conversation with him also.
   He had ‘heard considerable talk of the “larnin'” question,. He thought it was a good job, Many,
   however, didn’t—many of the boatmen were so ignorant that nothing you could do for them, however
   good, would make them satisfied. </p>
  <p> Many, however, didn’t—many of the boatmen were so ignorant that nothing you could do for them,
   however good, would make them satisfied, The women, this boatman thought, ought to be taken out
   of the boat. It was no place for a woman. Parenthetically I may here remark that I have an
   impression that the cap'en had a personal and purely selfish reason for advancing this opinion.
   His wife and he were constantly at high words, and doubtless if the authorities were by any
   chance to take his wife out of the boat he would be only too glad, And I, moreover, surmise that,
   the wife once on shore, the husband would do everything in his power to remove from. his. own
   shoulders the responsibility of supporting her. The wife's keep would fall upon the parish, I am
   satisfied that the local authorities interested in carrying out the provisions of the Act will
   have to exercise extreme caution in dealing with any clause affecting he women, When I say
   “women" I am alluding more particularly to the mothers of the children who next year will come
   under the cognisance of various local school boards, I was talking yesterday to the clergyman. of
   a parish abutting on a certain section of the Grand Junction canal. He gave me instances of the
   great difficulty that had been experienced by the guardians of the poor in his district in
   reaching cases of wife desertion by the canal boatmen, He mentioned the case of a boatman’s wife
   with six children, and all she received from her husband’s wages was ten shillings a week. “He
   stays away up in London,” said the clergyman, “and we can't get hold of him.” The reverend
   gentleman, whose words I am quoting, had had some experience of the canal boatmen, their habits,
   and mode of life. "I think you may say as a rule” he remarked, in the course of conversation,
   "that their whole idea of life is eating, drinking, and smoking. They are utterly selfish,. They
   spend all they earn upon themselves. We got up a special Sunday afternoon service for them in the
   parish church here for a time; but they wouldn't attend it, They had no coats, they pleaded, and
   didn’t like coming to the church in their sleeves— the boatman generally wear a sort of fustian
   jacket, with brown cotton stuff sleeves-—and the service was perforce dropped.” The clergyman
   considered the average wages they earned ample to keep the men, their wives, and children in fair
   comfort, if the boatmen would only keep out of the beer shop. </p>
  <p> But to return to my companion of this canal voyage. Tho cap'en of the barge that had kept us
   company from Paddington Basin was distinctly of the opinion that the women should be kept out of
   the boats. “ Why shouldn't they be kep out. We could do without ‘em, ‘The Bridgewater trustees
   had ‘em out,” said the man, “ but they sneaked in again. Not that it was the women’s fault, Some
   of the cap'ens asked leave to take their wife from sich a place to sich a place, and then they
   was aboard ag'in. And once aboard they stuck there.” I have already said that I am disposed to
   take this man's statement for what it is worth. I mention it because it happens to lead up to one
   of the main difficulties to be contended with in carrying the Act Into operation, This
   difficulty, however, is not one affecting the political bearings of the measure, but is purely of
   a social character. "If,” continued the boatman, “they takes away the chidr'n, why the mother
   must live ashore to look after 'em. And don't yer see" — here Captain Jonah’s friend followed the
   reasoning of Captain Jonah himself—"when the mothers goes off with the chidr’n they’s got to rise
   our wages.” I said to the man, "Now, what do you consider is the actual amount in hard money you
   put into your pocket weekly—I mean for the labour of yourself, your wife and the two lads?” I was
   particularly desirous that my question should not be misunderstood, and l repeated it, because I
   had become more and more convinced during my journey down the canal that there was no difficulty
   whatever in carrying the Act into operation as far as the authorities were concerned; the matter
   resolved itself purely into a question of labour and wages. The boatman replied, and I was
   careful to take down his words. "We reckon to get two pound ten." "Those are excellent wages,“ I
   replied; "hundreds. of clerks. up in London make less, and few artisans more. You ought to be
   able to educate the children yourselves, even now, on those wages. Captain Jonah's mate opined
   that they might be considered good wages "by any one as didn't know all the expenses the boatmen
   were at." Continued the skipper, "I've lost two 'orses only lately, and I give eleven pounds for
   that there ‘orse. Where's I to get another eleven pound from if I looses that 'un?" I felt
   compelled to agree with bargee that eleven pounds sterling were not to be scraped together now
   a-days without some forethought and thrift. As this wages question will by and bye, when the Act
   comes into operation, become— unless I am greatly mistaken — a point of debate between the barge
   owners and the men, l have been especially particular in collecting Information on this point ;
   and, I may add, from. a. variety of sources, from the canal superintendents, owners, bargemen and
   their wives, and the lads tending the horses </p>
  <p> A gentleman who is partner in a large firm of lime and cement merchants was good enough to
   give me the following particulars. His firm owned about twelve or thirteen boats working as
   "lime’ boats, and six or seven as "coal” boats, on one of our principal canals. There was not a
   boat of these, so far as he could call to mind, that was not worked by a ,am, his wife, and a
   lad. "I believe,” said this gentleman, “that the boatmen in our employ have made, and are making,
   on the average 2l. 5s.a week, ‘and this with no rent and taxes to pay." I understood him to mean
   that this sum was earned by the joint labour of the three. I have yet to ascertain however,
   whether this rate of earnings is common throughout the trade and steady throughout the year. If
   it be so, it seems to me that the boatmen have little to complain of now, and will have little to
   complain of by and bye when out of this forty-five shillings per week they have to set aside a
   few shillings for rent of a cottage and for school pence for the children. With one single
   exception all the bargemen I have talked with on my journey down the Grand junction Canal look at
   the Act as simply a masters’ question. One man and his wife, who had reared thirteen children,
   and only one out of the boat, were against the Act; but this formed the solitary exception. I am
   inclined to agree with the clergyman whose opinion of the bargemen I have already quoted, that
   the men as a rule eat well, drink well, and smoke well. The first-night 1 was on board the barge
   I threw an eye across the captain's supper table. I noticed a tempting boiled knuckle of ham, a
   shapely piece of corned beef, fat and lean admirably blended, a crusty loaf of fresh baked bread,
   a dish. of pickled onions and cucumber, and a goodly can of ale. In the morning there was an
   unlimited supply of milk, fresh from the cow, for the children, tea and bread for the skipper,
   his wife, and guest. I may say that my own supper, from lack of forethought, was considerably in
   rear of the skipper’s, and I was trusting that I might. receive an invitation to the cabin. I may
   be permitted, perhaps, to express the hope that I shall never partake of a worse meal than that
   which graced the little cabin table of my friend the bargee, who thinks that things could not be
   worse than they are with him at present, Probably’ many who read this may consider their own lot
   at times a degree less desirable than that of Captain Jonah, of the good barge Mary Jane. I
   reserve the consideration of barge accommodation and. the question of how the Act is to be
   carried out for another letter, which I will write after visiting the Potteries, where I am told
   the condition of the barge people is less favourable than that which I have been describing. </p>

 </div>
 <div  xml:id="Std_1877-09-08">
  <head>THE CANAL BOATS ACT AND THE BARGEMEN.</head>
  <head>[From Our Special Commissioner.]</head>
  <dateline>RUNOORN, Tuesday.</dateline>
  <p> Yesterday I took leave of Captain Jonah and the crew of his barge, Mary Jane. Joe was fast
   asleep on the gangway of one of the lock-gates. The sick relative had taken possession of my nest
   among the sugar-bags, and was likewise asleep. Ellen, with baby tucked under her left arm like a
   bag of old linen, was leading the horse, on whose back Sam was astride, Jack, the lurcher, was
   scampering about in the fields, a picker-up of unconsidered trifles, The skipper was alone with
   me, clearing up matters,“ You talks about that 'ere ‘orse, I tell yer ’er won't lay down. Once
   let un git used to a stable and ‘er ‘ll lay down fast enough. But not all us can do w’ll get un
   to lay down, leastwise ‘cept in Birmingham.” This was in reply to an observation from me that
   Captain Jonah’s horse seemed a trifle tired, and needed rest. “When us gits to Birmingham 'er
   makes up for it. You see, ‘er's used to the stable there, and the other ‘orses, and ‘er lays down
   like a lamb. But you might jist as well try to ’oist that boat across your showlders as try to
   git that ere ‘orse to lay down ‘cept in Birmingham. Keep her belly full, says I to Joe, keep her
   belly al’ays full, Joe, and then ‘er goes along like a steam ingin.” I may say that I am able to
   speak with some authority myself concerning this same animal's idiosyncrasies, 1 was walking on
   the towing-path with Joe in the early morning of Saturday, about the hour that the working men of
   Rickmansworth were astir, and going their various ways to their labour until tho evening, when
   Joe turned upon me unawares. “Jist walk arter the oss a bit while I runs on to the lock,” I took
   Joe's whip and walked after the horse. For two long hours I walked after the horse (Joe, taking
   every available opportunity to rest, was found dead asleep on his ordinary bed, the gangway of a
   lock- gate far on ahead), until fairly exhausted by curses loud and deep from boatmen passing in
   the opposite direction to ourselves, whose drawing-ropes I fell foul of. The skipper, his wife,
   and the sick relative enjoyed my discomfiture. ‘'He’s a darned sight too cunnin’ for yer,
   guvnor,” said Captain Jonah, alluding to the horse, and coming to my rescue when a bridge stood
   straight in the way and I had brought half a dozen barges to a standstill, “’Er’s drea'ful
   cunnin’ if ‘er once catches sight that taint Joe as is walkin’ arter ’er. Yer see it was ‘cause
   ‘er caught sight of yer. Yer should never let that ‘ere ‘orse see yer. Keep behind ‘er, I al’ays
   says to Ellen, and then there’s no stoppin’ the boat,” Captain Jonah and I took a friendly
   farewell of each other at a village ale-house, in the company of a few brother bargees invited
   for the occasion, the skipper's parting words to me being, “It's all a’ owners’ question Don't
   forget that, guvnor,” </p>
  <p> Whilst at Braunston I had the advantage of having an hour's conversation with the gentleman to
   whom I alluded in my last letter. He is an owner of barges and a builder of barges ; moreover, he
   has had many years' experience of the people working the boats on the different canals, his
   pocket, in common with the pockets of most owners, will in all probability be touched by the
   "accommodation” Clause of the Act. ‘I think there has been a great deal of fuss made about this
   matter of cabin accommodation,” said he to me, ‘when really there is no necessity for it. Though
   the space is small, how long are they (meaning the boatman and his family) in the cabin? I could
   take you to places in London that are fifty thousand times worse in regard to space and
   cleanliness than the boat cabins are. Look down Lime house, and about there. Go about the timber
   places in Limehouse. I quite agree that we want something done for the barge people. The children
   are terribly ignorant; we want something done, and something must be done for them. The education
   of the younger children is what is peremptorily needed. The boatmen and women must, as far as
   their condition is concerned, go as they are—let us look after-the rising generation and that as
   soon as can be!” With this we went to a covered dock where a recently built barge was being
   painted and stepped into the cabin. I took the dimensions down as follows :— 8ft. 6in. long, 6ft.
   6in, in the widest part, and 5ft. high. I am bound to say, and without hesitation, that here the
   sleeping accommodation for two was as ample in point of space as that which was reserved for
   married couples in the after cabin of a 1630 ton ship in which I once sailed to New York. There
   were no obstacles to efficient ventilation, and there was also a good side bed for children.
   Altogether I should have felt no difficulty whatever in passing this boat cabin as sufficient
   accommodation for a man, his wife, and two children. Absence of furniture, mess traps, curtains,
   bedding, and the like, no doubt made a slight difference in the appearance of available space ;
   but even with these additions I should still have been quite content to occupy the cabin myself
   with the number mentioned, Fresh air is after all what is most needed for children, and with all
   proper precautions such as is made on board ship to prevent people falling overboard, I should
   consider a child’s life on board a barge infinitely preferable to a child’s life in a London
   alley. A sort of painted rope netting rigged around the cabin deck and stern of the boat would no
   doubt answer all the purposes of a proper protection for the children. It must be borne in mind
   that I am referring more particularly now to barge life on tho Grand Junction Canal. I shall
   presently have something to say of barge life elsewhere. </p>
  <p> Returning to the subject of the Act, the gentleman whose conversation I have been reporting
   considered that there was such prejudice against the canals now (I take it that he meant in point
   of competition with the railroads), and the depression in trade was at present so great that,
   really, unless matters mended, it would become a very serious question with the owners what was
   to be done when the Act came into operation. “It all resolves itself into a question of wages,”
   said he. “There will be no difficulty at all in getting hold of the children if the men are paid
   sufficiently to keep a home for the mothers. That is, I think, that will have to be done. The
   women will, of course, belong to some parish, and the parish authorities Will have to see that
   the children are properly educated.” I asked him how. he would guard against the possible evil of
   boatmen shirking the responsibility of contributing to their wives’ support. “They are constantly
   travelling from place to place,” said I; “what is to proven a man residing at Braunston, for
   instance, spending all his wages in London, and vice versa?" "You will, I am afraid, have that
   difficulty occasionally to contend against,” was the reply ; "but with a rise in the rate of
   wages we shall get a better class of boatman and the thing will right itself. It is impossible to
   take the wife’s labour out of the boat without offering compensation to the husband in some kind.
   We are all agreed upon this; the men see it, and the owners see it. We look forward to having a
   better class of boatmen and a better state of things on the canals generally. Understand this
   clearly,” said the gentleman, in bringing our conversation to a close, “we owners are distinctly
   in favour of the Act, and consider it an excellent measure, though it must affect our pockets
   considerably.” </p>
  <p> T altered my plans, and instead of writing this from Burslem, as I promised, took the rail to
   Runcorn, in order to make note of the condition of things on the Bridgewater Canal, which at this
   point joins with the river Mersey. I walked on to the canal bank, and jumped on to the first
   barge alongside the wharf. It’s cabin accommodation was very bad indeed. There was a woman on
   board, and I asked her how many children she had. “One of her own, and one giv to her.” "Given to
   you! ” said I; "What do you mean?” "Well, this ere lad,” said the woman, pointing to a boy of
   about twelve years of age, “he was giv to me.” Later in the day I happened to mention this
   incident to a gentleman, whose knowledge of the barge people is as extensive as that of any
   person whom I have as yet met with on my journey – he had laboured as a missionary among them,
   preached every Sunday at a mission chapel near the canal bank to the boatmen and was in every way
   qualified to give me trustworthy information— "It’s a very common thing for them to be lending
   their children from one boat to another,” said he to me—“boys and girls both. both. For instance,
   we had a little girl who used to attend our Sunday school here. She was about seven years of age.
   She had been attending school for eight consecutive Sundays, and had gained eight good conduct
   tickets. The child was looking forward with great hope and pleasure to gaining a ninth ticket,
   which she would have secured by her attendance at the school on the ninth Sunday. During the week
   she was lent by her parents to another boat. The poor child fell off into the cut and was
   drowned, We never saw anything of her after she left the school,” "Good Heaven !” said I, “do you
   mean to say such things have been permitted amongst these people ?” “How was it to be prevented?”
   he replied, "up to the present no one has taken the slightest interest in the condition of the
   boatmen but here and there. George Smith, of Coalville, has been the man who has been mainly
   instrumental in drawing public attention to the matter, and, thank God, we have got the Act. Now
   we shall see what's to be done." The state of the barges on the Grand Junction Canal struck me as
   being Paradise compared with the state of many of the barges that came under my observation on
   tho canal side in the neighbourhood of Runcorn. They were filthy to a degree, and in many cases
   utterly unfit for human habitation, I ascertained casually that of all the boats plying on the
   Bridgewater Canal. the Wigan "flats” are out and out the very worst, and the Wigan boat people
   the most depraved. As was said to me "They are more immoral, more dirty—and that would be quite
   mild to say of some of their boats—and the most difficult to labour amongst. Other barge- people
   are bad, and very bad many of them; but the Wiganers are more depraved in every way, shape, and
   form.” I am merely repeating word for word what was told me by a gentleman of great experience
   among the boat-people on the Bridgewater Canal,. and I have had this statement confirmed by
   several.</p>
  <p> I made some inquiries during my stay at Runcorn concerning the rate of wages paid to the
   boatmen, and ascertained that two men working on one of tho “broad” boats earned between them
   50s. a week. No women are allowed to live on board this description of barge, which is worked by
   skipper and mate, The skipper earns on an average 27s., the mate 23s. a week. The accommodation
   provided seems to be ample, and the ventilation, with a little improvement, might be made all
   that is to he desired. I took occasion to ask a man who had served first as a boatman on the
   canal, then as an able seaman in the merchant service, and afterwards in the same capacity in the
   Royal navy—a man, therefore, of wide practical acquaintance with shipboard. accommodation— I
   asked him what hands, in his opinion, the barges might reasonably be allowed to carry. He thought
   on board the “broad” boats two, and on the “flats’ three ; the “narrow” boats might likewise be
   permitted to carry three persons, The space in the cabin of the “broad” boats I found to be as
   follows :— About 5ft. 6in. high, 6ft. long, and from side to side 9 ft. wide. The sleeping berth
   was about 9ft. by 3ft. </p>
  <p> While walking on the canal bank at Runcorn a man came up to me, and said that he should like
   me to come over to his barge. Accordingly, over I went. Presently I stood on the barge deck the
   centre of a circle of brawny-armed women, shaggy- headed children, and very frouzy-clothed men.
   An Amazon with tanned face and goodly beard put her arms a-kimbo, and stood forth the champion of
   the party, and what she had to say was received with bargee cheers, thus:— "Ers right,” "Sal
   knows on 't,” “Leave 'er alone for knowin about us,” “it's right what she’s a-saying, master,”
   "Listen to her, master,” and so on. The Amazon was very clear and decided in her manner. She
   looked around now and-again upon the circle about her much as a great speaker looks upon an
   audience around and before him, and gave an appropriate shrug of the shoulders here and a nudge
   of the head there, and a lusty bang with her fist at that portion of her speech which was very
   telling in point of oratorical action. "Master," she began, "they’s got to recompense us. They’s
   got to gi’ us more money. They'll ‘eve to do som'at for us when they taks the childr’n out of the
   boats, or us con never live. The masters w'll have to find the 'orses to pull the boats, and
   they'll have to pay tho boatmen reg'lar weekly wages. That's what they’s got to do. We w’d like
   to be ashore and ‘ave the childr'n to school ; but us can't live ashore without more wages." I
   asked the woman what she considered fair wages for the husband to earn, and she replied
   “Thirty-two shillin’ a week, and to find nothin’.” Then she went off on another tack. "Look you,
   master, I wants to know what's to ‘come o' the poor women as works the boats?” The Amazon gave a
   nod of the head sideways, and an inquiring look round, as much as to say, “Now, friends, I have
   him,” and continued, “You go to'ards Wigan, and what do ye see? You'll see lots of poor women,
   captains, and they works tho boats to maintain their children. What's to ‘come o’ them?” "Why
   workus to be sure,” exclaimed a sinewy sister of the barge, ‘What else?” "Four out o° six boats
   as comes from Wigan is worked by the women who've lost their ’usbands. What'll come to them poor
   craters?” asked the spokesman of the assembly. “Who's to support the childr'n as the mothers 's
   took away out of their boats?” “It is not intended,” I said, “to prevent the working in the boats
   if the accommodation is sufficient ; and things would be better for them all, they would find
   this time next year.” “We ‘opes so, I'm sure, master,” was the chorus in reply, and with that I
   took my departure, distributing largess by way of compensation for the time during which I had
   occupied their attention. </p>
 </div>

 <div xml:id="Std_1877-09-11"><head>THE CANAL BOATS ACT AND THE BARGEMEN. (FROM OUR SPECIAL COMMISSIONER.) </head> <dateline>BURSLEM,
  Monday.</dateline>
  <p> I have arrived at the following general_conclusions in the way of a summary of the experiences
   of my canal-boat journey :— First, that a difference exists in the_social condition of the people
   on different canals; secondly, that the Canal Boats Act is received with favour by bargeowners,
   boat-people, and canal companies alike ; and, thirdly, that there will not be such difficulty in
   carrying the Act into operation as might at first appear. My own observation leads me to consider
   that the condition of the boatwomen and children, the accommodation on. board the barges, their
   cleanliness, and the habits of the boatmen themselves are altogether worse in this district than
   nearer London. I saw nothing nearly so offensive to the eye in the course of my journey down the
   Grand Junction Canal as I met with in my walk on the canal side at Runcorn, and more recently on
   the banks of the Trent and Mersey Canal, in the vicinity of Burslem. This may be accounted for,
   however, by the fact that the boats congregated about these places are as a rule coal boats, and
   therefore more difficult to be kept clean and neat in the cabins than boats carrying general
   merchandise, timber, and hay. These latter are. mostly to be met with on the canals running
   through Worcestershire and Herefordshire, and the Grand Junction Canal, on many sections of which
   the country passed through is open and attractive, and altogether void of that smoky atmosphere
   common to the manufacturing districts. For ail this, however, there is much that needs looking
   into on the canals of North and South Staffordshire. It is in these districts and at Wigan, in
   Lancashire, that the authorities will find the most work to do in connection with the Canal Boats
   Act, and it is to be hoped that they will show themselves most energetic in carrying its principal
   and, I may add, excellent provisions into effect. They will have to cope with the most fearful
   ignorance, the result, unfortunately, of too long neglect of the condition of our canal population
   ; and, it may be, they will at first encounter resistance and obstacles to their work on the part
   of the canal boat-people. I have pointed out where, in my opinion, and in the opinion of others
   with whom I have conversed, the main difficulty will be found. If the labour, or rather wages,
   question did not crop up in the matter it would be, comparatively speaking, plain sailing in
   carrying the various clauses of the Act into operation ; but, as it is, the wages question is in
   fact the one great hinge on which everything seems to turn. Once let this be adjusted
   satisfactorily, and 1 venture to say that the boatmen and women both will welcome with more than
   gladness the efforts at present being made by the Government to improve their condition. I may
   say—and I do so with the utmost pleasure — that from first to last during my journey. I have met
   with nothing but an anxious desire on the part of owners of boats and agents of canal companies to
   furnish me every facility towards making my inquiry as searching and complete as possible. And
   although I have ventured to bespeak attention for this "wages-question ” element as being one
   which has met me at every turn I have taken, it is not to be understood that I foreshadow the
   slightest opposition from either owners of barges or canal proprietors to the just settlement of:
   the fair demands of the men when the proper time arrives. </p>
  <p> I have been curious to ascertain some statistical particulars of the population on the
   Bridgewater Canal. Mr. Beddows, the company’s agent at Runcorn, has been good enough to give me
   the following information :—At present his company (the Bridgewater Navigation Company) owns 335
   boats. Employed in these are 662 men, of whom 422 are married and the remainder unmarried. Only
   six, women are employed in any capacity on board the boats of the company, and among the total
   number of boat-people in their service but ten children are living on board any of their craft.
   More than three-fourths of the men can read and write, 105 are total abstainers, and 576 are
   proved to be sober boatmen. Of the whole number of men and women 646 have a home on shore, and but
   35 not. This seems to be a very satisfactory state of things, and if the "accommodation” on board
   the company's craft will bear as close inspection as the above stated figures, the Bridgewater
   Canal proprietors have reason to congratulate themselves on the help they will be able to afford
   the Government. I am told, however, that the boatmen in the service of this company, as well as of
   other companies, are dreadfully deficient in sanitary knowledge. Recently a boat came into Runcorn
   with a boy ill from small-pox on board. The boy was landed among the barge-people on shore, and no
   steps whatever were taken to cleanse the boat's cabin, the result being that the disease was
   communicated to a second, and, if I remember rightly, to a third person, one of whom died. There
   is little doubt that infectious disease may be propagated to an alarming extent by means the canal
   boats. The fourth clause of the Act, it is satisfactory to know, will deal efficiently with this
   evil. </p>
  <p> I should like, whilst the matter is fresh in my mind, to draw attention to a subject in
   connection with my recent inquiries, which, it seems to me, might well be looked into by the
   Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, though I confess my inability to point out a way
   for the society's officers to lay hold of the offenders. I refer to the overworking of the animals
   drawing canal boats. I have already mentioned that these unfortunate brutes— for the most part
   broken-down cab-horses—are provided by the boatmen themselves. A man will pay on the average from
   eleven to twelve pounds for his horse; A boatowner informed me that it was not am uncommon thing
   for some boatmen to drive their horses for thirty consecutive hours without resting them ; but I
   think the following admission will even cap this flagrant act of cruelty. I was talking to a
   genial bargee at Tunstall yesterday on things connected with his calling in general, and happened
   to ask him how he worked his boat, of which, by the way, he was owner. His two lads worked her,
   said he, "and last night the_lads come home from bottom of Wolverhampton Locks to Tunstall, about
   forty-five miles, without stopping.” Said I, “Was a horse drawing the boat?” ‘No, it waren’t a
   ‘orse ; it were a mule, and when ‘er come into the stable ‘er eat its meat and rolled about in the
   straw: for all the ‘orld like the donkeys does.” I ascertained that the lads started between three
   and four o'clock in the morning and arrived home about eleven o'clock at night. These bargemen
   have not the slightest notion that they are ill-using their beasts by over-driving them in this
   fashion. To "keep their bellys al'ays full” is the one great thing, and, to do the boatmen
   justice, the tin provender cans tied to the noses of their horses, mules, or donkeys are seldom
   empty. This man informed me that he was paid for his work by the ton. His boat would carry twenty-
   four tons, and with this load from Tunstall to Wolverhampton he earned, according to the present
   rate of freights, 3l. 1s. Out of this sum. he invariably deducted 9s. for boat hire, which went
   into his own pocket as a reserve fund for contingencies, for repairs, casualties, and so on, and
   it cost him, he said, 1l. a week for horse’s keep and stabling. This left about 15s. per week
   a-piece for the two lads, who were his own sons. There seems to be no absolute standard of wages
   for the boat-people. What they earn depends wholly upon their own energy and labour. It will
   readily be seen how this works generally prejudicially for the beasts drawing the boats. A boatman
   is naturally anxious to get through his “voyage” as quickly as possible. He, with his mate, will
   work day and night to lessen the time in going from place to place, and I have little doubt that
   the horse is worked as long as the poor brute can stagger along. On long journeys the periods of
   rest or “tying-up” are made as brief as possible, and may be reckoned at about seven out of the
   twenty-four hours—from eight in the evening till three the next morning. In my judgment the best
   possible thing that could be done for the boatmen, if it could be done without detriment to the
   owners’ interests, would be to pay them weekly wages. Much of the grumbling now constant with them
   would disappear, and the manifest injustice of not paying the boat hands for the time they are
   kept hanging about place waiting for a load would also be-done away with. Under the present state
   of things the men seem to me to have a direct inducement to shirk every responsibility of treating
   fairly the poor brutes drawing the boats. </p>
  <p>When I was at Runcorn I took the opportunity of visiting some of the cottages of the
   boat-people. The accommodation provided was decent and fairly good, and generally consisted of two
   rooms and a washhouse. For this a rent of 3s. 6d. a week was paid. The tenants, who were generally
   well supplied with children, lived without exception. in the boats on the “voyages,” and whilst
   away locked up the cottages. I mention this because it shows that even at present some of the
   boat-people find no difficulty in maintaining a place on shore. On the other hand it must not be
   lost sight of that the wife counts as one hand in working the boats—I am referring more
   particularly now to what are known as the “narrow” boats. When the wife has to live wholly on
   shore, as will probably be the case when the Canal Boats Act comes into operation, there will be
   so much taken away from joint earnings of husband and wife, with an added expense for an
   additional hand hired to take the woman's place. This point will have to he carefully considered.
   Personally I should prefer to see the women with their husbands in the boats—narrow, broad, or
   flat. I believe that the wives in most cases exercise an influence for good over their husbands
   —keep them from spending all their earnings at the beershop, endeavour to make the cabins,
   according to their lights, tidy and comfortable, and generally are useful in many ways. The
   exception proves the rule ; and though I have pointed out many things which need remedying, I
   should be sorry, very sorry indeed, to see the women compelled by force of circumstances to live
   out of the "narrow” boats, which are the boats likely to be most affected by the working of the
   Act. The uninitiated may care to know that the “narrow” boats are those ordinarily to be seen on
   the Grand Junction Canal with the brilliantly-painted little cabins aft; the “broad” boats are the
   dumpy- looking red and black barges, pretty much the same as those plying on the Thames; and the
   “flats” carry a mainsail and are built after the fashion of the bluff-bowed Dutch craft of the
   Scheldt. It seems to me that the cabins of the narrow boats might with comfort furnish
   accommodation for a man and his wife with their children under four years of age. As far as the
   “flats” and “broad” boats are concerned, if fore-cabins are provided, these might be reasonably
   allowed to carry four persons on each boat.</p>
  <p> The principal centres that in my opinion will require most attention in carrying out the
   provisions of the Act will be, first and foremost, Wigan; Paddington, on the Grand Junction Canal; Birmingham, on the Birmingham and Warwick Canal; Etruria, as being the most central town on the
   Trent and Mersey Canal; Wolverhampton, on the Staffordshire and Worcester Canal ; Manchester, the
   point of junction of the Bridgewater, Rochdale, Ashton, and Peak Forest Canals; Runcorn, Leeds,
   Liverpool, Blackburn, Coventry, Oxford, and Stafford, and one or two other places. It might be
   desirable to establish at some of these principal centres homes and schools combined for the
   accommodation of children during the absence of parents on their "voyages;” and it would possibly
   become, a question for consideration whether the Government might not contribute to some extent to
   the support of such school homes. In the cases where the boatmen’s families might be large it
   would be almost, indeed I have no hesitation in saying quite, impossible for parents to pay out of
   their earnings what might be considered as the cost for maintaining and educating children between
   four and twelve years of age who are prohibited joining the boats. In the event of tho Government
   finding itself in a position to contribute to the support of such schools, it would be a proviso,
   of course, that they should be reserved exclusively for the children of boat-people, If this could
   be brought to pass it would confer enormous benefit on our canal population, and would be of
   lasting advantage to the country at large. </p>
  <p> In conclusion, I may be permitted perhaps to add a few words on the religious aspect of the
   subject which has been engaging my attention for the past week. I am not prepared to admit that
   the people are more destitute of advantages in the way of spiritual education than are their
   fellow labourers of the world in the metropolitan or, for the matter of that, any other districts
   in the kingdom. The boatmen and their wives have churches and chapels to go to, if they will but
   go, and mission agents and other excellent men are always to be found willing to give them kindly
   advice and assistance. The fact is that, in my mind, it is just as useless trying to teach the
   Apaches the Chinese alphabet as endeavouring to bring the bargees to church, so long as their
   earnings depend in any way upon the quickness of the voyages they have to make. I am not referring
   now altogether to the great centres or "tying-up” places, but to the towns upon the canals
   generally. Pay the men weekly wages, and compel them to “tie-up” on Sundays, and they will go to
   church and chapel the same, I take it, as other Christian people. _ But a man must be able to
   withstand a great amount of temptation if he will sit in the church aisle in his work-a-day shirt
   or dirty jacket sleeves, in preference to adding a shilling or two to the miserable weekly wages
   of himself, wife, and little ones. I am putting the matter in my own fashion. I am compelled also
   to say, judging from personal observation, that many statements that have been made concerning the
   bargees are altogether over-drawn. In their habits and manner of life many them are bad enough;
   but not so bad as they have been painted, And were I a child of poor parents I would over and over
   again prefer to be the child of a Grand Junction Canal boatman than the child of a costermonger of
   Frying-pan-alley. </p>
 </div>
 <!-- Frying Pan and Bitt Alleys were visited in 1864 by the Vestry sanitary committee, following representations from the Commissioners of Police. This concluded that 'owing to the extremely careless and filthy habits of the people, nothing but absolute removal would improve the condition of these places'. (fn. 49) In 1869–70 houses in these two courts were condemned as unfit under the new Artizans' and Labourers' Dwellings Act (Torrens Act) and, in part, pulled down. The Builder complained that they were 'being rebuilt exactly as before, so that persons might shake hands from the windows of the opposite houses'. (fn. 50) Improved or not, the two alleys, together with Rose Alley and part of Broad Yard, were finally cleared a few years later by the Metropolitan Board of Works to make way for Clerkenwell Road. (https://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london/vol46/pp182-202) -->
</body></text>
</TEI>