<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Curran Bibliography: a selection based on authors published in LAE</title>
      </titleStmt> 
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>no publication statement available</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>Derived from spreadsheet of contributors downloaded from  https://www.curranindex.org on 2024-12-12</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <listChange>
    <change>
     <date>2025-01-04</date>
    </change>
   </listChange>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
<!-- manually edited output from curran.xsl 2025-01-03 -->
<!-- to derive a link for div/@n = XXX,  try
 https://www.curranindex.org/contributors/?selectedItem%5Bindex%5D=contributor&selectedItem%5Bid%5D=XXX&showModal=true
-->
<!-- @source contains the number of contributions attested in the curran index -->
 <div n="971" corresp="W0002"  source="contribs:2782">
  <head>A'Beckett, Gilbert Abbot</head>
  <p>Proprietor of several periodicals; edited Figaro in London; staff
   member of Punch; wrote for Times and Morning Herald; barrister and magistrate; wrote The Comic
   Blackstone (1846) and other comic works; wrote over 50 plays. See Boase I: 4-5ODNB; DNCJ.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="2849" corresp="W0003" source="contribs:1443">
  <head>A'Beckett, Gilbert Arthur</head>
  <p>Dramatist and librettist</p>
 </div>
 <div n="584" corresp="W0004" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Addison, Henry Robert</head>
  <p>Born in Calcutta; soldier; wrote dramas and farces for English
   theatre; wrote songs and articles for monthly magazines; author of about 12 novels. See Boase I:
   22, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="70" corresp="W0018" source="contribs:19">
  <head>Banim, John</head>
  <p>Born in Kilkenny, a novelist and playwright; supported Catholic
   emancipation; wrote Tales of the O'Hara Family with his brother Michael; contributed to many
   periodicals. See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1271" corresp="W0026" source="contribs:2">
  <head>Beazley, Samuel</head>
  <p>Architect, novelist, and playwright; wrote over a hundred theatre
   works and designed London theaters. See Boase I: 214.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="915" corresp="W0037" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Boucicault, Dion</head>
  <p>Dramatist; wrote London Assurance; lived in England and America; plays
   at leading London theaters (Haymarket, Lyceum, Adelphi, Holburn, Drury Lane, etc.). See Boase IV:
   459-461. ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1123" corresp="W0041" source="contribs:4850">
  <head>Brooks, Charles William Shirley</head>
  <p>Journalist, writer, and editor; wrote for Morning Chronicle;
   contributor to and editor of Punch; edited Literary Gazette; wrote plays and novels. See Boase I:
   419-420, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="943" corresp="W0047" source="contribs:2">
  <head>Bunn, Alfred</head>
  <p>Theater manager; managed Drury Lane and Covent Garden; adopted many
   pieces for the stage; wrote The Stage both Before and Behind the Curtain (1840); A Word With
   Punch (1847), Old England and New England (1853). See Boase I: 473, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1736" corresp="W0048" source="contribs:10960">
  <head>Burnand, Sir Francis Cowley</head>
  <p>Writer, playwright, and journalist; actor; editor of The Glow-Worm;
   staff writer and then editor of Punch; wrote a series of burlesques and farces. See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="447" corresp="W0052" source="contribs:5">
  <head>Byron, George Gordon</head>
  <p>Major British Romantic poet. See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="3209" corresp="W0053" source="contribs:174">
  <head>Byron, Henry James</head>
  <p>Dramatist, as well as an editor, journalist, director, theatre
   manager, novelist and actor; editor of Fun magazine.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1404" corresp="W0058" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Cheltnam, Charles Smith </head>
  <p>Playwright, translator; add dates to Wellesley; EMC, VPR 34 (2001), 354.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="2786" corresp="W0061" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Clarke, Campbell</head>
  <p>Journalist and author; librarian at British Museum; special
   correspondent in Europe; translated papers; adapted plays and wrote songs.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="985" corresp="W0073" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Craven, Henry Thornton</head>
  <p>Actor and dramatist; real name Henry Thornton; performed at the
   Adelphi, Strand, Covent Garden, Lyceum, City of London, Marylebone, and Princess's theatres;
   produced 29 plays. See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="2756" corresp="W0077" source="contribs:13">
  <head>Dance, Charles</head>
  <p>Dramatist and drama critic; taxing officer and chief clerk; wrote
   over 30 plays. See Boase I: 810.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1120" corresp="W0080" source="contribs:2">
  <head>de Girardin, Madame Emile</head>
  <p>Writer; née Delphine Gay, married Emile de Giradin in 1831; pen name
   Vicomte Delaunay, wrote poetry, romances, and dramatic pieces.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1946" corresp="W0083" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Dibdin, Thomas John</head>
  <p>Playwright and actor; wrote 2000 songs; founded a periodical, Tom
   Dibdin's Peney Trumpet (1832); wrote for several periodicals. See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1713" corresp="W0090" source="contribs:14">
  <head>Dubourg, Augustus William</head>
  <p>Novelist and playwright; wrote Four Studies of Love (1877), Angelica:
   Romantic Drama in Four Acts (1892), other works.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1681" corresp="W0093" source="contribs:21">
  <head>Edwards, Henry Sutherland</head>
  <p>Author and journalist; contributed to Punch and other periodicals;
   wrote light dramatic pieces; foreign correspondent; wrote The Russians at Home (1861); wrote on
   musical history and criticism; editor of The Graphic. See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="997" corresp="W0094" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Ellis, George</head>
  <p/>
 </div>
 <div n="3213" corresp="W0109" source="contribs:7">
  <head>Gilbert, Sir William Schwenk</head>
  <p>Dramatist, librettist, poet and illustrator best known for his
   collaboration with composer Arthur Sullivan, which produced fourteen comic operas; contributed to
   comic magazines.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1115" corresp="W0119" source="contribs:2">
  <head>Hale, William Palmer</head>
  <p>&amp;quot;W.P. Hale&amp;quot; is probably William Palmer Hale who was
   the son of William Hale Hale, master of Charterhouse; a barrister and friend of Edmund Yates, he
   wrote The Oude Question (1857) and poetry and prose in The Train Magazine (1856).</p>
 </div>
 <div n="994" corresp="W0139" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Holl, Henry</head>
  <p>Actor and author; wrote for Jerrold's Shilling Magazine in 1846; wrote
   a novel The White Favour (1866), The Forest Keeper: A Drama in Two Acts (1872), acted at the
   Haymarket.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1908" corresp="W0140" source="contribs:471">
  <head>Hollingshead, John</head>
  <p>Journalist, theatrical manager; wrote for Household Words, Cornhill
   Magazine, the Morning Post, the Leader, and other periodicals. See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="229" corresp="W0143" source="contribs:69">
  <head>Horne, Richard Henry</head>
  <p>Naval midshipman, edited the Monthly Repository (1836-1837), spent
   much time in Australia; wrote poems, dramas, histories; editor / author of A New Spirit of the
   Age (1844). See Boase I: 1539, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="106" corresp="W0149" source="contribs:2230">
  <head>Jerrold, Douglas William</head>
  <p>Playwright, magazine editor, perhaps best known for Mrs. Caudle's
   Curtain Lectures, a series of articles in Punch. See Boase II: 88-9, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="126" corresp="W0157" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Kenney, James</head>
  <p>Playwright and friend of Samuel Rogers and Charles Lamb. See
   ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1333" corresp="W0161" source="contribs:5">
  <head>Knowles, James Sheridan</head>
  <p>Physician, actor, schoolmaster, and playwright; friend of Hazlitt,
   Coleridge, and Lamb; ran school in Glasgow; wrote the tragedy Caius Gracchus (1815); wrote
   several plays for William Macready. See Boase II: 259-60, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="3208" corresp="W0170" source="contribs:7">
  <head>Lemon, Henry</head>
  <p>Son of Mark Lemon.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="932" corresp="W0171" source="contribs:51">
  <head>Lemon, Mark</head>
  <p>Dramatist and editor; wrote about 60 plays; a founder and editor of
   Punch; contributed to Household Words, Once a Week, and other periodicals; amateur actor. See
   Boase II: 386-7, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="3952" corresp="W0172" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Leslie, Henry</head>
  <p/>
 </div>
 <div n="538" corresp="W0174" source="contribs:48">
  <head>Lewes, George Henry</head>
  <p>Critic, dramatist, author, editor, and partner of Mary Ann Evans;
   edited Fortnightly Review, literary editor of The Leader; wrote many articles in the quarterly
   reviews; author of biography of Robespierre, A biographical history of philosophy (1845-6), The
   life and works of Goethe (1855), and other works. See Boase II: 408-9, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="2008" corresp="W0175" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Lewis, Leopold David</head>
  <p>Solicitor and dramatist; developed dramas produced at the Lyceum, the
   Adelphi, and Sadler's Wells; wrote A Peal f Merry Bells (1880). See Boase II: 417, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1318" corresp="W0180" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Lovell, George William</head>
  <p>Playwright and novelist; secretary of insurance company; wrote plays
   in 1830s-1840s; wrote the novel The Trustee (1841); the play The Wife's Secret was staged in New
   York and in London. See Boase II: 505, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="936" corresp="W0182" source="contribs:11">
  <head>Lover, Samuel</head>
  <p>Portrait painter, dramatist, poet, novelist; wrote Legends and Stories
   of Ireland (1831), Handy Andy (1842). See Boase II: 506-507, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="891" corresp="W0185" source="contribs:11">
  <head>Lunn, Joseph</head>
  <p>Playwright; member of the Dramatic Authors Society; his plays were
   produced at Covent Garden and other London theaters from 1818 through 1830; also wrote Horae
   jocosae, or, The Doggerel Decameron, ten facetious tales in verse (1823). See Boase II: 531,
   ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="711" corresp="W0204" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Mayhew, Edward</head>
  <p>Member Royal College of Surgeons and editor; edited and wrote works on
   animals and veterinary care. See Boase II: 815.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="2018" corresp="W0205" source="contribs:2">
  <head>Mayhew, Henry</head>
  <p>Journalist, dramatist, and travel writer; co-publisher of Figaro in
   London; manager of the Fitzroy theatre; wrote farces; co-founder of Punch; wrote The Rhine (1856)
   and other books on Germany; co-author of London Labour and London Poor (1851). See Boase II:
   815-6, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="3254" corresp="W0207" source="contribs:33">
  <head>Merivale, Herman Charles</head>
  <p>Dramatist and poet; works include: the plays All for Her (1875), The
   Butler (1876); the novel Faucit Of Balliol (1882), and a biography of William Makepeace Thackeray
   (1891).</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1433" corresp="W0209" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Millingen, John Gideon</head>
  <p>Died 7 June 1849 (death certificate). While 1782 remains the
   preferred year of birth, some confusion still surrounds this date. The d.cert. gives his age at
   death as 65, producing a d.o.b. of 1785; however, ages were sometimes rounded off. In 1862 his
   daughter, Letitia Millingen, told the RLF (case 1597) that her father was born in 1783, but she
   is vague even about her own age, which she gives as ‘about 48.’ For the only contemporary record
   of his d.o.b., see W.C.B., ‘English Freemasons in France, 1817,’ N&amp;amp;Q, 8 Nov. 1890, 384,
   which prints an 1817 list of the members of the Masonic lodge of St. Fréderick des Amis Choisis,
   Boulogne, most of them English military personnel ‘in cantonment’ nearby (Millingen was a
   military surgeon). This gives his dob. as 8 Sept. 1782, making him 66 at death. See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="2279" corresp="W0210" source="contribs:2">
  <head>Milman, Rev. Henry Hart</head>
  <p>Cleric and historian; Dean of St. Pauls; professor of poetry at
   Oxford; wrote drama and poetry: Fazio (1815), The Fall of Jerusalem (1820), and other works;
   wrote The History of the Jews (1830); translated Sanskrit works; published translation of
   Euripides (1865). See Boase II: 893-4, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="82" corresp="W0212" source="contribs:23">
  <head>Mitford, Mary Russell</head>
  <p>Author of four tragedies; books of poems; Our Village, sketches of
   rural character and scenery 1824-32 made her famous. See Boase II: 909-10, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1477" corresp="W0213" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Moncrieff, William Gibbs Thomas</head>
  <p>Dramatist; in Wellesley as &amp;quot;Moncrieff, William
   Thomas.&amp;quot; See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="729" corresp="W0224" source="contribs:1">
  <head>O'Keeffe, John</head>
  <p>Actor and dramatist; wrote Tony Lumpkin in Town (1778), Wild Oats
   (1791), Love in a Camp, and Omai (1785), and many other works. See ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="142" corresp="W0227" source="contribs:100">
  <head>Oxenford, John</head>
  <p>An English dramatist and translator, he wrote for Punch and about 1850
   became drama critic for the Times. See Boase II: 1295-6, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1198" corresp="W0242" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Phipps, Edmund</head>
  <p>Barrister; wrote The Memoirs of the Political and Literary Life of
   Robert Plumer Ward (1850). See Boase II: 1520, ODNB under Henry Phipps.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="93" corresp="W0246" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Planché, James Robinson</head>
  <p>Dramatist and theater manager; associated with Covent Garden, Adelphi
   theatre, Haymarket; wrote on costumes and heraldry, wrote his Recollections and Reflections. See
   Boase II: 1553-4, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="36" corresp="W0251" source="contribs:14">
  <head>Poole, John</head>
  <p>Dramatist, particularly for Drury Lane; extensive contributor to New
   Monthly Magazine and other periodicals; wrote humorous short pieces, poetry; wrote Paul Pry,
   Little Pedlington. See Boase II: 1583, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1642" corresp="W0257" source="contribs:14">
  <head>Reade, Charles</head>
  <p>Novelist, barrister, and playwright; wrote It is Never Too Late to
   Mend (1856), The Cloister and the Hearth (1861), and many other novels and plays. See Boase III:
   64-65, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="514" corresp="W0258" source="contribs:13">
  <head>Rede, William Leman</head>
  <p>Actor and playwright; involved with Dramatic Author's Society; wrote
   The Rake's Progress (1832) and The Peregrinations of Pickwick, or, Boz-i-a-n-a (1837);
   contributed to New Monthly Magazine; wrote novels serialized in the Sunday Times. See
   ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1861" corresp="W0259" source="contribs:6">
  <head>Reece, Robert, Jr.</head>
  <p>Playwright; clerk in emigration civil service; wrote many libretto's
   and plays. See Boase III: 78-9, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="4203" corresp="W0265" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Robertson, Thomas William</head>
  <p/>
 </div>
 <div n="539" corresp="W0279" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Serle, Thomas James</head>
  <p>Actor and playwright; cofounded with Douglas Jerrold the Dramatic
   authors society; lectured on Shakespeare; wrote weekly political letter for the Weekly Dispatch.
   See Boase III: 494.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="310" corresp="W0281" source="contribs:6">
  <head>Sheil, Richard Laylor</head>
  <p>Barrister; wrote several tragedies, struggled for Catholic
   emancipation; M.P. in 1830s, contributor to New Monthly Magazine. See Boase III: 537,
   ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1322" corresp="W0282" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Sheridan, Richard Brinsley</head>
  <p>Eldest son of Thomas Sheridan and grandson of the playwright and
   politician Richard Binsley Sheridan; M. P. For Shaftesbury and Dorchester; Indian civil servant;
   brother of Caroline Norton. See Boase III: 549.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1653" corresp="W0283" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Simpson, John Palgrave</head>
  <p>Playwright and journalist; also wrote novels, travel books;
   contributed to The Times, Blackwood's Magazine, Bentley's Miscellany, other periodicals. See
   Boase III: 583, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="495" corresp="W0285" source="contribs:21">
  <head>Smith, Albert Richard</head>
  <p>Surgeon, dramatist, entertainer, and writer; contributed to Punch and
   Bentley's Miscellany; published with A. B. Reach the monthly The Man in the Moon; wrote many
   works including The fortunes of the Scattergood family (1845) and The Marchioness of Brinvilliers
   (1846). See Boase III: 616-7, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1892" corresp="W0287" source="contribs:7">
  <head>Smith, Spenser Theyre</head>
  <p>Playwright; wrote Which is Which? A Comedietta in One Act (1871) and
   many other plays.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="744" corresp="W0288" source="contribs:9">
  <head>Smith, William Henry</head>
  <p>Barrister; contributed extensively to Blackwood's Magazine; wrote
   novels, poems, and plays; author of Discourse on ethics of the school of Paley (1839). See Boase
   III: 651, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1430" corresp="W0289" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Soane, George</head>
  <p>Novelist, playwright, and poet; wrote Specimens of German Romance
   (1826), The Night Dancers, an Opera (1846), and other works. Delete 1790 as year of birth; ODNB
   identifies the dob. as 28 Nov. 1789, followed by baptism on 18 Dec. 1789. See Boase III:
   663.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="638" corresp="W0298" source="contribs:3">
  <head>Stocqueler, Joachim Hayward</head>
  <p>Journalist, government employee, entrepreneur, and inventor in
   England, India, and U.S. Edited Indian sporting magazines; wrote histories and biographies. Also
   wrote under the name Joachim Heyear Siddons. See RLF case 1267, case III: 765, ODNB. (Documents
   were kindly provided by Peter S. Gill, his great-greatgrandson).</p>
 </div>
 <div n="77" corresp="W0299" source="contribs:5">
  <head>Sullivan, Robert</head>
  <p>Poet and dramatist; wrote The Silent River (1824), Fittings of Fancy
   (London: Henry Colburn, 1837).</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1641" corresp="W0302" source="contribs:100">
  <head>Taylor, Tom</head>
  <p>Dramatist and journalist; wrote for Morning Chronicle and Daily News;
   secretary Board of Health; editor of Punch; wrote many plays starting with Diogenes and His
   Lantern (1849). See Boase III: 902-3, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="3219" corresp="W0306" source="contribs:72">
  <head>Thompson, Alfred</head>
  <p>British musical theatre librettist, set designer, costume designer,
   theatre manager, journalist and artist, contributing to Punch and Vanity Fair. See Boase VI:
   679-80.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="3247" corresp="W0322" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Weatherly, Frederic</head>
  <p>Barrister and song writer; contributed to Punch in 1871.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="1406" corresp="W0334" source="contribs:1">
  <head>Wilson, John Crawford</head>
  <p>Poet; correct Wellesley birth year to 1825. EMC, VPR 34 (2001),
   357.</p>
 </div>
 <div n="548" corresp="W0339" source="contribs:7">
  <head>Yates, Edmund Hodgson</head>
  <p>Journalist and novelist; theatre critic for the Daily News; wrote
   gossip column for the Illustrated Times; central figure in Garrick Club scandal between Dickens
   and Thackeray; wrote plays, verse, and minor novels. See Boase III: 1553-4, ODNB.</p>
 </div>
 
  </body></text></TEI>
