<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L0616" xml:lang="en">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Extremes: TEI edition</title>
 <author ref="lacyp:W0097"><persName>Falconer, Edmund</persName><idno
type="wikidata">Q5339449</idno></author>
<respStmt>
<resp>TEI conversion</resp>
<name>Lou Burnard</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor>
<idno type="LAE">L0616</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy
Project waives all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which it
believes to be in the public domain. You may copy, modify, distribute, or
perform this work freely. </licence>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="originalSource" n="42.1"><author n="W0097">Falconer, Edmund</author>
<title type="main">Extremes; Or, Men of the Day</title>
<title type="sub">A Comedy in three acts</title>
<extent>73 pp (UM copy: 8 - 81)<measure type="pp" quantity="67"/>
<measure type="spCount" quantity="1036"/>
<measure type="spvCount" quantity="0"/>
<measure type="txWords" quantity="27476"/>
<measure type="spWords" quantity="25425"/>
<measure type="stWords" quantity="2051"/>
</extent>
<title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 42, No. 0616</title><idno
type="nic">N12144</idno><idno type="vpp">Vol42iExtremes</idno></bibl>
<bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref
target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/Source/VPP/L0616-vpp.pdf">LoB from
VPP</ref><ref target="local:Vol42/L0616/L0616-vpp.pdf"/><ref
target="local:Vol42/L0616/Vol42iExtremes.pdf"/></bibl>
<bibl type="surrogate"><ref
target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015005299667&amp;seq=8 ">UM
from HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol42/L0616/L0616-um.pdf"/></bibl>
<listEvent>
<event type="firstPerf" when="1858-08-26" source="textNic" where="Lyceum">
<desc>Premiered at Lyceum Theatre 26 Aug. 1858</desc>
</event>
</listEvent>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<!--L 3 Comedy C. COMEDY-->
<textClass>
<catRef target="#sizeL"/>
<catRef target="#act3"/>
<catRef target="nic:C."/>
<keywords>
<term>COMEDY</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person xml:id="L0616_M1">
<persName type="role">Sir Lionel Norman</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="110">Sir L.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_M2">
<persName type="role">Hon. Augustus Adolphus</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="89">Adol.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_M3">
<persName type="role">Dr. Playfair</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="86">Dr. P.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Dr. Playfair.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_M4">
<persName type="role">Mr. Cunningham</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="31">Mr. C.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_M5">
<persName type="role">Everard Digby</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="18">Everard.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_M6">
<persName type="role">Frank Hawthorne</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="132">Frank.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_M7">
<persName type="role">Robin Wildbriar</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="81">Robin.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_M8">
<persName type="role">James</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="57">James.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_F9">
<persName type="role">Mrs. Vavasour</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="56">Mrs. V.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Miss V.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_F10">
<persName type="role">Lucy Vavasour</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="128">Lucy.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_F11">
<persName type="role">Mrs. Wildbriar</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="108">Mrs. W.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_F12">
<persName type="role">Jenny Wildbriar</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="78">Jenny.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_F13">
<persName type="role">Miss Euphemia Cholmondeley</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="27">Miss E.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_F14">
<persName type="role">Jemima Simperton</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="7">Jemima.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0616_mult">
<persName type="role">[Multiple speakers]</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Dr. P. and Mr. C.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="21">Omnes.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="2">Sir L. | Everard</persName>
</person>



</listPerson>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-05-12">Add wikidata link to titleStmt where possible</change>
<change when="2026-05-11">Completed the bits Claude missed; hand checked against
VPP page images</change>
<change when="2026-05-10">TEI XML structure added by Claude (up to a
point)</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<titlePage>
<titlePart type="main">Extremes;</titlePart>
<titlePart type="sub">or, Men of the Day.</titlePart>
<titlePart type="sub">A Comedy in three acts.</titlePart>
<byline>By <docAuthor>EDMUND FALCONER.</docAuthor> MEMBER OF THE DRAMATIC
AUTHORS' SOCIETY, Author of <title>“The Cagot,”</title><title> “A Husband for an
Hour,”</title><title> “Too Much for Good Nature” </title><title>“Husbands
Beware,” </title>&amp;c, &amp;c.</byline>
<docImprint> THOMAS HAILES LACY, 89, STRAND, (Opposite Southampton Street,
Covent Garden Market), LONDON.</docImprint>
</titlePage>
<pb n="2"/>
<div type="liminal">
<p>TO HIS LANCASHIRE FRIENDS, WHOSE SOMETIMES EXTREME BLUNTNESS OF SPEECH, HE
ALMOST INVARIABLY FOUND NEIGHBOURED BY EXTREME KINDNESS IN ACT, THE AUTHOR, IN A
“GRADELY” SPIRIT, DEDICATES THIS COMEDY.</p>
</div>
<pb n="3"/>
<div type="liminal">
<head>PREFACE.</head>
<p>THE materials for so long a Comedy as <title>Extremes</title> unexpectedly
proved, must, of course, have been previously acquired; but no particular
consciousness of their existence preceded the design and composition of the
Drama, which, from conception to completion, as it is now presented, occupied
the Author a period of sixteen days. Although certain, that of mere haste of
production it must have many faults, its success upon the stage has made him
fearful of attempting to amend, that, which no longer seems his own work. When
the fire of composition has been suffered to die out, as it generally is once
accepted work passes the door of the studio, judgment, no longer warmed by the
spirit of conception, may be potent to criticise, but is feeble to improve; and
so, as an exercise to the always vigorous judgment of the critics, yet not
without an avowed dependance on their mercy, the Author leaves the faults of the
Comedy of <title>Extremes.</title></p>
<note>Note.—For various reasons the Author cannot particularize, and therefore
begs the Ladies and Gentlemen named in the original cast generally to accept his
sincere thanks.</note>
</div>
<pb n="4"/>
<performance>
<p>First performed at the Lyceum Theatre, August 26th, 1858.</p>
<castList>
<head>Characters.</head>
<castItem><role gender="M">Sir Lionel Norman</role>
<actor>Mr. Fitzjames.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Hon. Augustus Adolphus</role>
<actor>Mr. Charles.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Dr. Playfair</role>
<actor>Mr. Barrett.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Mr. Cunningham</role>
<actor>Mr. Garden.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Everard Digby</role>
<actor>Mr. Fitzhenry.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Frank Hawthorne</role>
<actor>Mr. Edmund Falconer.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Robin Wildbriar</role>
<actor>Mr. Emery.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">James</role>
<actor>Mr. James Rogers.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Mrs. Vavasour</role>
<actor>Mrs. Wallis.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Lucy Vavasour</role>
<actor>Mrs. Charles Young.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Mrs. Wildbriar</role>
<actor>Mrs. Weston.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Jenny Wildbriar</role>
<actor>Miss Kate Saxon.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Miss Euphemia Cholmondeley</role>
<actor>Miss C. Weston.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Jemima Simperton</role>
<actor>Miss Miller.</actor></castItem>
</castList>
</performance>
<div type="costume">
<head>Costumes.</head>
<list>
<item>Sir Lionel.—Fashionable morning dress for summer, dark hair, whiskers, and
moustache. Act II.—Fashionable morning dress for October, hat, and gloves. Act
III.—Full dress.</item>
<item>Adolphus.—Same, only a little more extravagant; light wig divided in c,
light beard, and long-peaked moustaches falling down.</item>
<item>Dr. Playfair.—Plain suit of black all through; low crowned hat with broad
brim turned up; iron-grey wig slightly bald.</item>
<item>Mr. Cunningham.—Black suit with over frock coat; white hair.</item>
<item>Everhard Digby.—Same style as Sir Lionel, but plainer; no
moustache.</item>
<item>Robin.— Green cutaway coat with canary-coloured waistcoat, and light cord
trowsers, wide-awake hat, light hair. Act II.—Grey suit, peg-top trowsers. Act
III.—Blue frock, velvet collar, snuff-coloured trowsers, and white
waistcoat.</item>
<item>James.—Smart modern livery; coat buttoned, large bouquet in breast, hair
powdered.</item>
<item>Frank.—Full dress suit of black. Act II.—Frock coat, grey trowsers and
waistcoat. Act III.—Morning winter suit; then fashionable wedding dress.</item>
<item>Mrs. Vavasour.—Fashionable morning dress. Act II,—Walking dress. Act
III.—Full dress for old lady.</item>
<item>Lucy.—Morning dress, hat. Act II,—Morning dress; riding dress. Act
III.—Morning dress, And last Scene—Bridal dress, wreath.</item>
<item>Miss Euphemia.—Morning dress, different for each Act.</item>
<item>Mrs. Wildbriar.—Handsome plaid silk and cap. 2nd—Claret-coloured silk
velvet, turban to match. 3rd—Light moire antique. 4th—Light green silk.</item>
<item>Jenny.—White muslin, 2nd—Fashionable silk, hat and feather. 3rd— Handsome
morning dress; wedding dress without wreath.</item>
<item>Jemima.—Plain coloured muslin, small apron, and cap.</item>
</list>
</div>

<set>
<p>SCENE—Hawthorne House, Dorsetshire.</p>
<p>Time—1857-58.</p>
</set>

</front>
<pb n="5"/>
<body>

<head>EXTREMES; OR, MEN OF THE DAY.</head>

<div type="act" n="1">
<head>ACT I.</head>

<div type="scene" n="1">
<head>Scene First.</head>
<stage>A richly-furnished Drawing Room, with large bay window at the back,
opening upon a terrace, and affording view of lawn fringed with flowers;
extensive woods beyond; an entrance to conservatory, R. U. E.; arched entrance
to a library, within which statues and paintings are visible, L. U. E.; doors of
entrance, R. and L.; books, writing materials, newspapers, vases, &amp;c. on
tables; sofas, screen, chairs, &amp;c.; a portrait of Lucy Vavasour, L. 2
E.</stage>
<stage>James discovered reading Times newspaper, L. C.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>“The bank having noted a further reduction in its rate of discount, the funds
rapidly rose from 93 1/8 to 95 1/4; and finally Three per Cent. Consols were
quoted at 95 3/8. New Three per Cents, and Reduced Annuities rose in an equal
ratio. Business on ‘Change yesterday was exceedingly brisk, and confidence
seemed completely restored in the money market.” That’s a comfort; while that
ere monetary crisis lasted, and the funds kept a bobbing up and down, and hevery
day brought hintelligence of a fresh smash, it was really hawful for people who
‘ad a little money, to think of what was a going to ‘appen.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Sofa. Screen. Chair. Window. Chairs. Chair. Chair. Small Table. Table.
Chair. Chair. Chair. Table. Chair. Chair. Small Table. Chair.</stage>
<pb n="6"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. Playfair.</speaker>
<p><stage>(outside, L.)</stage> Here, some one!—is there nobody in the house? I
object to being left alone.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>That is Dr. Playfair, one of the trustees and executors; and as he objects to
everything, he might object to my reading the news. <stage>(puts paper on
table)</stage></p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Dr. Playfair, L. 2 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Has the solicitor—I mean Mr. Cunningham—arrived?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> I {h}am {h}under the {h}impression, sir, that he has not;
but it is possible that I might be mistook.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> I object to that indirect and circumlocutory method of
answering a question. Why can’t you say that you don’t know—short and
straightforward? When a man’s ignorant of any matter, nothing like owning it off
hand.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>I never confesses total {h}ignorance upon any subject.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Then the greater humbug you. Do you know where the <title>Times</title> paper
is?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir; it is at this present moment deposited on the table to the
{h}extreme left of the apartment.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object—but there’s no use in objecting to noodleism when you are talking to
a noodle.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Shall I do myself the felicity of obtaining and presenting it to you?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>No, I shall get it myself; and, hark ye, I object to your society any longer;
so oblige me by leaving the room. <stage>(goes to table, L., takes paper, and
goes up to R. table)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>If it wasn’t that he’s {h}executor, and might {h}offer {h}obstructions to my
receipt of a legacy, if there should be one, I should tell him that he was no
gentleman. I have been in the service of a dook and a marquis, and never was
ordered {h}out of a room before. Oh, Jeames Dodsworth, this comes as a
punishment on your {h}avarice, and for demeaning yourself to take service with
commoners, merely because they give larger salaries, and {h}allows more
perquisites. The {h}aristocracy may be poor now and then; but they {h}always
{h}appreciates sentiment, {h}elegance of diction, and refinement of manners.</p>
<stage>Exit, L. 1 E.</stage>
</sp>


<stage>Enter EVERARD DIGBY, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Ah, my dear doctor! I am most happy to see you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to the use of the superlative most—humbug—twice as happy to see a
hundred other people. I like you well enough not to be annoyed at meeting you;
but don’t deal in humbug.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="7"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha! always the same contentious, but sensible adviser. I am glad to see
you in the positive degree, and comparatively more glad to see you than ——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>A dun or a bailiff—no compliment that. I like it the better, and accept it
frankly. <stage>(shakes hands)</stage> What brings you here? Don’t expect a
legacy, I hope? I’m quite sure that you’re not mentioned.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Oh, I never had the slightest reason to indulge an expectation. You know that
I am a lawyer, and being cousin to Miss Vavasour, she and her mother have
invited me to pass the long vacation here. It’s partly a friendly, partly a
professional visit; they may want my advice as to the settlements, after the
will has been read.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Oh, she has made up her mind to inherit?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Can there be a doubt of that?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Don’t know. Hawthorne, queer fellow, had relatives. Don’t
see why he should ignore their claims. Do you know his history?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Partially. I know that he was originally poor, but of a respectable family,
and ——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> In fact you know nothing at all about it; as it’s short,
don’t mind telling you. I think his family never heard the word respectability
in their lives, and I’m quite sure never understood what it meant. Hardly knew
their own surname. George had some difficulty in ascertaining that, in after
years. They were miners, or labourers in a mine—a coal mine; lived in darkness,
and died in it; plugged up, or stifled off by choke damp, or some other infernal
gas: that is, all of them except George, his scamp of a brother, and a cousin.
George went to sea, enlarged his ideas, returned, became a workman in an iron
foundry, got into the engineer’s room, showed talent for designs, learnt to read
and write, and draw—saved money, made foreman, married employer’s daughter:
employer died, wife died, became rich, invented all sorts of self-adjusting
machines, built steam engines, laid railroads, built iron ships, speculated,
made nearly a million of money, bought an estate; and, as he was a man of
progress, and his manners in a great degree reflected the favourable change in
his fortunes, found, when he was about fifty, an honourable lady—a poor
baronet’s daughter—willing to marry him, and share his wealth.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> What an extraordinary career, to be sure.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Not at all extraordinary—plenty of instances—national and individual—of
progressive ascents from insignificance to wealth and name. Well, his second
wife had no children, and he grew fond of her niece, the present expectant
heiress, Miss Lucy Vavasour; but before adopting, or rather <pb n="8"/>becoming
attached to her, finding that he was likely to be childless, he made some
inquiries about his own relations.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>The brother and cousin you spoke of as having escaped choke damp?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Yes; the brother he traced to a small maufacturing town in Lancashire, but
learnt that he was a bad mechanic, a supposed good writer of songs popular among
workmen, and a fluent tap-room orator when half drunk, which was usually the
case four days out of the seven. Intensely disgusted with each characteristic,
he determined to withhold all recognition of such a relative; but shortly before
his death he again made some enquiries, and the fact of his brother’s demise,
and of his one son’s industry, having raised him into a little independence,
which enabled him to support his mother in comfort and respectability, and to
look forward to a still better day, was modestly communicated to him by that
son. To his surprise he learnt that his brother and family had all along been
aware of his success; but from a dislike to subject him to a possible
humiliation, had refrained from seeking his assistance in the hours of their
greatest privation.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>That was very noble.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Perhaps it was—perhaps it was a stupid stiff-necked spirit of pride—don’t
know which—but he was touched by it, and again first nature asserted her sway,
and suggested the injustice of leaving all his property to a mere collateral
relation, while kindred in whose veins his paternal blood flowed, lived, and
were deserving, too; and still he felt bound by the moral obligation he had
contracted to Lucy. The expedient Hawthorne hit upon we shall know to-day, when
the will is read.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Do you surmise its nature?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> No; and if I did, I shouldn’t tell you one moment before
the seal was broken upon the will.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Quite right. What of the other relative?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Oh, the cousin; he had married some petty farmer’s daughter in Lancashire,
and had thriven well in a small way; he, however, made his exit from this world
some time before Hawthorne’s demise.</p>
</sp>

<stage>(Honorable Augustus Adolphus and Sir Lionel Norman laugh outside)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Who are those?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Sir Lionel Norman and the Honorable Augustus Adolphus.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to both. The former is too fine a gentleman for my taste, and the
latter too complete a puppy; let us walk and shun them for the present.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exeunt through window, L. C.</stage>
<pb n="9"/>
<stage>Enter Sir Lionel and Adolphus, L.; Mrs. Vavasour and Miss EUPHEMIA, R.;
preceded by JEMIMA, who places chairs, and then exits, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Good morning, ladies. My dear Mrs. Vavasour, how do you find yourself
to-day?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated, R.)</stage> As I always do in the country, Sir Lionel, alive,
and little more: the air is too bracing for my delicate organization. Augustus,
do me the favour to close that window. I am like an exotic, and can only live
out of Belgravia in a conservatory, or a house of like temperature.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside, L.)</stage> Dear delicate old soul, how well she is
preserved.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside, L.)</stage> It is the privilege of a lady to talk nonsense and
the duty of a gentleman to sympathise.</p>
</sp>

<stage>(Adolphus goes up and closes window, C.)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Let me draw this screen between you and the possible draught from yonder
door; and where is Miss Vavasour, has she not dawned this morning?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>I really don’t know. Euphemia, where is Lucy, have you seen her?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>I have heard—not seen. At present, I believe, she is in the gardens, or the
conservatory.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> By herself, out of doors at this hour?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> She had made an early breakfast and toilet, and knocked
at my door an hour ago, wishing me to accompany her to some favourite points of
view, but I was not ready, so she went alone.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>What robust habits the girl has, to be sure; acquired them from living as a
child so much with Mr. Hawthorne.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Lucy Vavasour appears on terrace, C.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Down, Bijou—down; don’t be naughty; you can’t come into the drawing room;
don’t look sad, little stupid. I shall see you again, and have another romp with
you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Can that be Lucy’s voice?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Yes; here is Miss Vavasour.</p>
</sp>

<stage>(Lucy opens window, runs in C., and closes it quickly, shutting out a
little spaniel)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> No, no; you must not come in; go away—go away. Ah, Sir
Lionel! Mr. Adolphus, good morning. My dear mamma—toilet made, and down, and
looking so much better. Ah, how I rejoice! I knew the change would do you good.
I vow you have a colour.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="10"/>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> I trust not—you alarm me—it must be hectic. You know
the country air never agrees with me. Nothing but the necessity of attending the
reading of this will could have induced me to risk the illness sure to
follow.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, don’t say so! I am sure that you must derive good from the purer air of
the country. I feel as if in another and a much more delightful sphere. The
emerald earth and azure sky, the fragrant, and yet nimble, jocund atmosphere,
formed, as it were, of beams and ether, dancing from the highmost hill to mingle
with the breath of flowers, murmurs of rills, and songs of birds, and all the
other healthful, joyous pulses that beat mirthful music in the ear of dear old
mother Nature—old, yet ever young—give to me a sort of second-better being.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Poetry!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Enthusiasm!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Miss V.</speaker>
<p>Nonsense!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside, L.)</stage> Rubbish!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> I sympathise with your admiration of the Woodlands; it
is a truly charming retreat.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I expected as much from your good taste, Sir Lionel.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>The shrine is as it should be, in keeping with the divinity.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Meaning me. Oh, that compliment is extravagant and premature! I am not
mistress of it yet—may never be.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>I wish, Lucy, you would not indulge in such surmises; they are very
disagreeable, and cannot possibly be correct. Mr. Hawthorne could not have been
guilty of such injustice.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I shall never accuse him of injustice; he was always good and kind to me; but
he may have had relations with stronger claims than mine: we should make some
allowance for the interests of other people.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> That depends upon the sort of people. Who are the others
to whom Miss Vavasour refers?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> I did hear from Dr. Playfair, that there were some
nobodies summoned to hear the will; but they can only be the recipients of some
small legacies.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> Your nobodies must be somebodies, my dear mamma. Three or
four of the best rooms in the east wing were prepared for them by Dr. Playfair’s
orders; and I believe they have occupied them since last night.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Heyday! this looks serious.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Low people in the house! what profanation! Please to ring, Augustus, for
James. I must enquire who those people are—what they are like.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="11"/>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Nay, nay, dear mamma! Will not that be a little unbecoming?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>At another time, under other circumstances, it might, but the interests of my
child are at stake. There may be some conspiracy at work. I should get all
information. Don’t you think so, Sir Lionel?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Well, it is but to inquire what company have arrived, and in that sense it
cannot be considered a breach of etiquette.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Money is at stake, and etiquette may go to the devil
both for fine lady and punctilious gentlemen. <stage>(rings)</stage> Oh, by all
means, let us have James’s evidence, its sure to be amusing.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter James, L. 2 E., crosses to L. C.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Ave I the ‘onour to be required?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Oh, James, be good enough to inform me who, and what sort of people those
strangers are, at present domiciled here.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>{H}am I to report as, I think, madam—or {h}as I {h}am bound out of politeness
to speak of any guests received into this noble mansion?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! a nice distinction.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes, a capital opening. I foresee some strange revelations; let us hear
his real opinions.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>The truth, James, as you think.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>By all means make a clean breast of it, James.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Then in my {h}opinion, madam, they are a rum lot.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>What?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>I beg parding, but I always speaks graphically, and in keeping with my
subject.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> Figuratively, I suppose, he means.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir; I means figuratively and graphically too. They are, madam, a
{h}invasion from the lower regions.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Figuratively also; no sulphur or brimstone odour, I trust?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Oh, no; but a deal of the clod-hopper odour about
them. The fust that arrived was a young man, good looking enough, and not badly
dressed, but one could see with ‘alf a {h}eye that he was no gentleman.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Indeed! why so, James?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Why? why because he seemed rather out of conceit with himself, which no
gentleman {h}ever {h}is.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha! Capital.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>What a discriminating rogue!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>What was his name?</p>
</sp>
<pb n="12"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Well, I think I knows, but I aint sure; there is some mystery over that part
of my {h}information.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>The interest increases.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Indeed! pray explain.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>He {h}arrived in a sort of a gig, or a dog cart, which was driven by a man in
a rough dress.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>His servant!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>I doubt that, for when he got down he shook hands with him, and said: “Well,
good bye Hedmondson,” and the other replied: “Good bye, Frank, lad, and I wish
you luck. Luck!”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Luck! Vulgar wretch.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Werry low, indeed, madam.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> But what about the mystery—where’s the mystery?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Why, sir, when we addressed him as Mr. Frank, he hopened his eyes, and looked
hastonished like, and seemed ha going to speak, and then stopped short, and shut
up as if afraid to speak, and afterwards muttered something to himself habout
its being no matter, and discovered soon. Werry mysterious conduct, I call
that.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>A capital story; quite a goblin legatee.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Now for the others, and don’t deal so much in detail.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Oh, the others are a greater mystery than the first; there are three of
them.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>All in one; a triple ghost.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no; nothing ghost-like about them; very substantial, especially the
{h}elder matron; {h}arrived in a flashy carriage and four, postillion and
coachee, but only jobbed from the town where the railway station is; the
company, fust a woman——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Why not say a lady, James?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Well, in compliment to the fair sex, I’ll call her a lady; rather a fine
figure, but {h}excuse me {h}inclining, to or upon the {h}edge of being reckoned
among the ‘as beens.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Daughter a nice looking girl, very tastefully dressed, and {h}exceedingly
genteel {h}in manner compared to the {h}other; {h}and a son in the most vulgar,
flashy style of getting hup that was ever seen at a country fair, or an
‘alf-bred race-course. They made noise enough, and {h}examined {h}everything.
The mother said the room into which they were shown was fitted up with gimcracks
and tinsel thingumbobs, not worth much.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>The son said the sofa on which he stretched himself was first-rate—a right
down plummy one. {H}excuse this <pb n="13"/> language, it was theirs, not mine;
but the daughter said that everything was in exquisite taste.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>The young lady seems to be a favourite with you, James.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>A case of love at first sight, eh, James?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no. I know my station and my dooty to society too well, and I left the
room rather than loose my ‘art. Left alone, they wanted refreshment, and rang
the bell. When {h}asked what they required, the old lady said, “Best in the
house.” I stared, and she said I needn’t, for that she could pay for it. As it
was late, I {h}enquired which they preferred, dinner or tea. “I’ll none of your
slops of tea,” said the mother; “I’m right down faint wi’ thirst.” “So am I,”
said the son; “but I want summat to eat.” I suggested wine and seltzer water for
the lady. “Wine—rubbish! it always made her ill; she wanted a mug of beer.” I
was so horrified, and in such a state of confusion, that I didn’t know whether I
was standing on my ‘ead or my ‘eels.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Poor James. I quite sympathise with you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>The young lady, stepping forward, said: “Be kind enough to bring, or order,
some refreshments, such as are usually set for a light supper or for luncheon,
with a little ale for my brother and mamma; and, please, a cup of tea or coffee
for me.”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Good little fairy, that was prettily said.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Well, I thought so myself, miss, {h}at the time; {h}at least, it was a
speechies of refined {H}english that I could understand.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh! James, James! you’ll be the death of me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Well, now for the names of these anomalies.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Oh, that the {h}old lady told me and the other servants twenty times—Mrs.
Betsy Wildbriar, her son Robin, and daughter Jenny Wildbriar.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Is it possible—our Lancashire witches memoried by months of laughter?
<stage>(crosses to L. C.)</stage> Sir Lionel, don’t you recollect the ball at
Preston, on the occasion of the militia being reviewed by old Sir Charles, where
we saw those wild roses blossoming in all their native simplicity of blush and
fragrance?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>I remember something of the occasion, but nothing of the people.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh, they are presented to the life. James, you are a capital
word-painter—quite a character photographist.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> As I said before, sir, I ‘ave eyes in my ‘ead, and wasn’t
born yesterday.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="14"/>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> That will do, James; you may retire for the
present.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Very well, madam. I think I have opened their {h}eyes, and sustained the
dignity of a {hupper} servant.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exit, L. 2 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>You really know these people?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Met them at the militia ball last summer; they had just
inherited—wonderful creatures—perfect studies for an antiquarian—original as
Lancashire itself—descended in an unmixed line from the aboriginal British, or
the first Saxon squatters on the banks of the Ribble—that is, the mother and
son. Sir Lionel, try and remember them?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Well, I begin to recall something in connexion with
them. Didn’t Everard fall in love with the daughter, and get laughed at by us
all?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Everard in love! That’s excellent!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>To be sure; the girl as James reports, very nice and as ladylike. But the
great joke was my telling the mother, in confidence, that Everard was a
marquis—the Marquis of Banterdown—ha! ha! travelling incognito for reasons of
state, and cautioning her not to address him by his title, or to betray the
slightest knowledge to him of the secret,</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> What a shame! I do not see the object of the ruse.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh, it was productive of the greatest fun in the world. She first told her
daughter, then her son, then all her immediate acquaintances. Then her open
admiration of Everard! She addressed him as Mr. Marquis, and then begged his
pardon twenty times. Everard was surprised, but never knew at what we laughed,
and, for mirth’s sake, don’t tell him now. Let us keep up the jest here. We
shall have such a meeting, as I believe both mother and daughter are in love
with him. Ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I shall be no party to a practical joke.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>You will not interfere one way or the other—such vulgar creatures are not
worth a moment’s consideration for or against. <stage>(knock at
door)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>What’s that?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Some one knocked at the door.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Strange—this is not usual with the servants.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh, it’s one of our Wildbriars, or the goblin legatee—let us have them. Come
in.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Frank opens door, L. 2 E.—about to enter, perceives Ladies; hesitates;
Gentlemen look at him with eye-glasses.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> I beg pardon. I—I am afraid that I intrude.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Well, you certainly do intrude if you have no further <pb n="15"/>
intelligence or business to communicate, but your suspicions upon that
matter.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Sir!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Eh!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Yes—ah! It is very possible; but I thought— that is, I know that I have
business, if this is the principal drawing-room, as I was left to surmise. Have
I made a mistake? if so, I beg pardon.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Why did you not ask guidance and information from one
of the servants, instead of troubling ladies and gentlemen to instruct and
chaperon you?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Sir!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Eh!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Confound his impudence. Sir, I did ask information
from a servant in the hall, at whose want of politeness in not answering, I no
longer wonder, having met a greater rudeness in reply from a gentleman in the
drawing room. As I know that I have business, and do not come here without
authority, it is only in compliment to the ladies present that I retire for the
moment, to spare them the annoyance of altercation.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Your chivalry is most <hi>distingué</hi>.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Much more than yours, Mr. Adolphus, in my opinion. <stage>(crosses
L.)</stage> Stay, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> And in mine, too. Courtesy should never be cast aside by
the gentleman. <stage>(goes back to table, R.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Frank, I presume?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(surprised, L.)</stage> Eh! madam. Yes, Frank is my name—that is, one
of my names.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Oh, most hybrids have two. <stage>(goes to Ladies, R.,
and then takes chair R. corner)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>One of the relatives of the late Mr. Hawthorne, summoned to attend the
reading of the will?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Yes.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>In that character, let me, as for the time being nominal mistress of this
mansion, assure you, that your right to enter this room is equal to that of any
one here, and may prove greater. It is the hour appointed for the reading; the
trustees and executors have arrived, I believe, and will be here in a few
moments. Pray remain. I entreat: you will pain me by refusal. <stage>(he
bows)</stage> Be seated, I beg. On that table you will find the London papers of
this morning, I believe.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I thank you. Much obliged; sorry to have disturbed you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Pray don’t mention it. These gentlemen did not, in the freedom and privacy of
an almost family conversation, recollect that strangers had equal business here.
I trust under <pb n="16"/>these circumstances, you will forgive my friend’s
apparent want of courtesy.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Certainly, madam. I never indulge in anger after an explanation. Forget and
forgive is a good—Ah! well, I— I am talking. I beg pardon; pray don’t let me
keep you from your friends. <stage>(she curtsies, and returns to her chair,
R.)</stage> Courteous and kind, as beautiful. The mistress? she deserves to be.
<stage>(Frank sits at L. table, and takes up newspaper)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>That was admirably done; ladylike in the extreme.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>You did quite right, Lucy. Adolphus was too severe; and, as lady of the
mansion, it is your place to show courtesy to all under its roof; but you should
not have raised hopes in the young man’s mind by talking of his possible
inheritance.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Why not? I was only Mr. Hawthorne’s favorite, not his relative.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>What relative is the newspaper <hi>solitaire</hi>?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>I can’t imagine. I never heard of Mr. Hawthorne’s having any relatives,
although he too frequently alluded to his humble origin, and was fond of saying
that he had no family connections, and was a self-raised man.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Surely, he did not spring into existence from the mouth of a furnace, to
engineer his cradle, and model his own pap-spoon?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>For shame. I will not listen to a jest in connection with his name. He was a
great man of his talent, and a good one of his kind heart, and he always loved
me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Who could help that? <stage>(L. C.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>He was a rich man, and made <hi>himself so</hi>, and therefore devilish
clever, I must own.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Mrs. Wildbriar and Jenny appear in conservatory R. 3 E. Dr. Playfair at
window, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! but it’s a bonny, a beautiful place, and summat like Crystal Palace. Eh!
there’s an old man will tell us the way. Here, you sir, which is road to
thingumbob—what do you call ‘um room?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that method of making an inquiry. I shall not answer any question
put in such a barbaric dialect.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>What’s the man mean? I speak good English, don’t I?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that assumption. I call it a most inexplicable jargon.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! he’s either soft, or right down impudent.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>No, no; pray, mamma, give me leave. <stage>(crosses to L.)</stage> You will
excuse us, sir, we are strangers here; will you be kind <pb n="17"/>enough to
inform me where we shall find, or perhaps, as doubtless you are going there, you
will point out the room in which the will is to be read?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Don’t object to that; nice little girl. This is the room, my dear; permit me—
<stage>(offers chairs at back, and advances)</stage> Good morning, good
morning—<stage>(Ladies and Gentlemen rise)</stage> Miss Vavasour, ladies,
gentlemen—so all the parties assembled and I saw from the terrace, Mr.
Cunningham coming up the avenue; we shall read the will at once.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! but my lad, Robin, mun be here first; do you know where he is? I mean
Robin, my son, Robin Wildbriar.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Don’t know—and I don’t care. <stage>(aside)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Drat the lad, I’m sure he’s up to some mischief. <stage>(comes a little
forward and perceives others)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Shouldn’t at all wonder, if he’s like his mother.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! what a lot of fine folks, and nobody to introduce us. Jenny, lass, now’s
time to show your education; just astonish them by doing it first rate. You
won’t—then I’ll do it mysen.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>No, no, mamma; by and bye; it’s not the custom— this is a business meeting—no
need of introduction—no acquaintance at present likely to be made; pray be
silent and sit down.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Does lass think I’m ashamed of my name or mysen? I’m none going to sit
mumchance when there’s people to talk to.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>But they don’t know you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Well, then, I’ll make ‘em know me. Yon old woman seems to be mother of the
family. I’ll speak to her first. <stage>(advances, C.)</stage> Dame, how are
you? hope you’re quite well, as I am, thank heaven. You dunnut know me, nor I
you. I’m Mrs. Betsy Wildbriar, fra’ Lancashire, and this is my daughter,
Jenny—and a nice lass ou is too, and well edicated; better than her mother; but
then her mother is none the worse for that;—we’ve comed up here to hear my lad
and lass’s second cousin’s—my old man’s that wur, first cousin’s will read: not
that we care over much for that, for, thanks to my poor dead and gone brother,
who died of yellow fever in Ingey, we’ve got plenty of money of our own, and
summat to spare for poor folk. And now I’ve telled you who and what we are, some
one of you do the same by me, and put us all right and straight and comfortable
like, that’s the way we always do. There, I think I’ve done that very well.
<stage>(crosses, L.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Isn’t she a glorious creature? <stage>(crosses, C.)</stage> Allow me to have
the honour of officiating, as I claim to be an old acquaintance of this lady,
having had the pleasure of meeting her at Preston on the occasion of the
pleasantest evening, thanks to her society, that I ever passed at a militia
ball.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh!—what the Honorable Mr. Augustus Adolphus, Esquire!—aye, for sure, and how
are you, lad? Eh I I’m so glad to see you, man—and here’s Jenny,—Jenny, come and
shake hands wi’ an old friend: <stage>(Jenny advances, L., and curtsies)</stage>
and how’s the Marquis? Eh! I forgot—how’s Mr. Everard Digby?—see how Jenny
blushes—eh! she’s rather sweet there, I can tell you. Oh, don’t need to frown or
deny it, lass; you’re as good as he—he’s but a man after all, if he is a Mar—.
Eh! bother that cognito of his. I wur nigh letting rat out o’ bag.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter EVERARD, through window—comes down, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>He’s here—and will be delighted to renew his acquaintance. Your charming
Preston acquaintances, Mr. Everard!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! it’s him, sure enough; and how are you, my lor—Mr. Mar— no, I mean Mr.
Everard? you’re looking prime. Here’s Jenny—same as ever; shy and backward as
ever hur wur. Come forward, lass, and speak wi’ an old acquaintance.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Ah, Mrs. Wildbriar <stage>(crosses to Jenny, and takes her up to seat,
L.)</stage>, and my piquante little partner in the Schottische; I am delighted
to see you. Pray be seated—permit me— <stage>(leads Jenny to chair, and talks to
her, L., at back)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>He’s just same as ever—pleasant and social like. Eh! he’s a gradely man. I
wish he wasn’t a Mar—bother that, I’m always boggling over it. If he were only a
cotton spinner, or a farmer, he might have her to-morrow, and one hundred
thousand pounds.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Permit me. Mrs. and Miss Vavasour; Miss Euphemia Cholmondeley; Sir Lionel
Norman.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>What! the Baronite!—Proud to see you, sir <stage>(he bows formally)</stage>
Isn’t he well, or has he the rheumatiz in his side, or pains in his back, that
he bows so stiff and grand loike?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>It’s his knightly dignity.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Oh, I hate such stuck-ups; the Mar—you know who—is twice as agreeable.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Dr. Playfair, who—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(coming down, L.)</stage> Objects to any character-painting, at your
hands, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>And this gentleman—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rising)</stage> Will introduce himself. I am, Francis, more commonly
called Frank Hawthorne.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Hawthorne!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Hawthorne? Any relation to my old man’s—that wur first cousin—that wur?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>His nephew.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="19"/>
<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Nephew?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! then we are relations, too. You are poor Bill Hawthorne, the poet’s son,
that used to write in Bolton Luminary, eh! I’m glad to see you, lad, for your
fayther’s sake; he used to come often to our house when on his tramp rambles;
many a meal’s meat he’s had wi’ us, and many a good bright shilling I’ve lent
him; but he drank it all. Don’t be ashamed; he was a good-hearted man for all
that. And your our Jenny’s second cousin? Jenny, come and shake hands wi’ your
cousin, lags.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(going up to Jenny)</stage> Pray don’t rise; permit me; I have much
pleasure in making your acquaintance. <stage>(shakes hands and returns to his
seat)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Oh, I’ve heard of you—you’re a good lad—you always took care o’ your mother;
and I hope your uncle has taken care of you in his will, as he ought, for you’re
his own brother’s son, and blood’s thicker than water.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p><stage>(comes down, C. L.)</stage> Hush, hush, mamma! consider there are
others here.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Oh, I’ll speak my mind, if there were twenty times as many—that I will, for
sure. <stage>(goes up stage)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>A nephew! I never dreamt of the existence of so near a kin; but the moment I
saw that man, I had an instinct of something wrong. He’s sure to have been left
a large legacy.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I hope so—in mere justice he should.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter James, L. 2 E., preceding MR. CUNNINGHAM; all rise to receive
him.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Cunningham, solicitor, trustee, and <hi>hex-e-cutor</hi>. <stage>(goes
up, R.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>Good day—good day, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(goes to him, and shakes hands; then returns to his seat)</stage> Ah,
Cunningham! I thought that you were going to be late for once.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p><stage>(looking at watch)</stage> Late—late; no—no; minute hand within
fifty-five seconds of twelve o’clock—will to be read at twelve—never waste time
by coming too soon or too late to an appointment. Are all the parties summoned
here?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I believe so.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>No—no; my son, Robin, isn’t. Drat that boy, wherever can he be? Robin! Robin!
<stage>(calling at window, C.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that noise—not here, will must be read without him.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Stop—stop a bit; here he is at bottom o’ steps. Here, Robin—Robin—this way,
lad; they’re going to read will here.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="18"/>
<stage>Enter Robin, up steps of terrace, vulgarly, but flashily dressed;
trowsers turned up, and boots mudded.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Robin, lad, just come in pudding time—as you always do, when pudding’s first.
Lots o’ fine folk here, and some old acquaintances. Take off your hat, make a
bow, and I’ll introduce you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Na; I dunnot want no introduction. I can speak for
mysen. <stage>(advances, C.)</stage> Lads and lasses, old men and old women, my
service to you. I’m Robin Wildbriar; oh, I aint ashamed of my fease, or my name,
for I’ve done nothing as yet to make me, and I don’t mean to; and if you can
only—all of you—say the same, you may hold up your heads any whur. <stage>(Jenny
signs to him)</stage> Eh! all right, lass; and now I’ve said my say, I’ll take a
seat. <stage>(takes chair and sits, C.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Good lad, couldn’t have spoken better if he had
studied it out a book. Eh! where have you been your boots are all mud?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Why, you see, I picked up an acquaintance with a terrier pup that belongs to
these parts, and he and I have been rat hunting in the stream down there. I
wiped boots dry upon the grass of the plat yonder; but if there’s any offence
I’ll take them off, and put them outside. <stage>(Jenny comes down on his L.,
and signs to forbear)</stage> All right, lass. <stage>(rises)</stage> Mother
doesn’t know Jenny’s dodge and mine—I’ll tell her. Mother, stick by me, and do
as I do. Jenny and I agreed, as I wasn’t up to the ways of the nobs, for her to
give me a sign whenever I put my foot in my mouth, and as she’s just done it,
I’d better shut up. <stage>(all take seats—Robin puts his chair
back)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Silence for Mr. Cunningham,</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated R.)</stage> One moment. James, you can leave the room.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>I beg parding, but as I was five years in the service of the lamented George
Hawthorne, Esq., I though it just possible that I might ave a {h}interest, a
slight one, of course, in the will.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Didn’t he pay your wages, man?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>That’s right lad—an impudent lacquey.</p>
</sp>

<stage>(Jenny signals again)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Hold hard, mother; Jenny’s tipped the wink.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Mr. C. Mrs. W. Everard. James. (table) Robin. (table) Sir L. Jenny. Mrs.
V. Miss E. (table) (table) Augustus. Lucy. Frank. Dr. P.</stage>
<pb n="21"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>James, you are not particularised in the will, I know; as I drew it up.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>That’s enough. <stage>(aside as he crosses to L.)</stage> You drew it up; you
drawed it out, you mean; but I thought as much, as soon as I saw his low
connexions {h}arrive. {H}ingratitude {h}always {h}accompanies {h}ignorance.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exit, L. 2 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>As the will will be hereafter open to every one’s perusal, I do not think it
necessary to read the somewhat lengthy preamble, which sets forth the testator’s
history, and some motives which induced the disposition made by him of his
property.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Aye, don’t give us any preamble.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Come to the point, lad.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Hush, hush.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>I shall only read the marginal abstract of its several bequests, and thus
dispensing with the lengthy forms and technicalities, put you in immediate
possession of the whole purport.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Speak plain English, man, and let us ha’ no climclavers.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Shut up, mother.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>I shan’t; and you had better not insult me before people, or I’ll give thee a
clout on the side of the yead.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Silence, woman!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(coming down, C.)</stage> Woman!—who do you call woman? I’m as good as
you, and have as much money—may be more; I dunnot care none for your will. I can
do about it, and if you speak two words more, I’ll go out o’ the house, now
then.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>I say, you’ve napped it, ould chap; haw, haw! <stage>(to Dr. Playfair—Lucy
rises and goes to Mrs. Wildbriar)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Pray excuse the doctor, madam; he is one of the executors, and is only
anxious that the will may be read without interruption, and I am sure, as a good
lady, you will excuse him, and oblige us all by listening in silence.
<stage>(goes back to seat)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>You’re right, lass. I’ll do anything for fair words, but I wunnot be
driven.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Na, I’m sure ou wunnot; mother’s like a pig feyther had—<stage>(Jenny checks
him)</stage> All right, lass—mum.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p><stage>(reads)</stage> “I, George Hawthorne, formerly of Alnwick,
Northumberland, and now of the Woodlands, Dorsetshire, being of sound mind,
declare this to be my last will and testament, and do hereby give, will, and
bequeath all and several of the various sums to the parties herein named and
described in this my will. Imprimis.—To my second cousin, Robin Wildbriar”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>That’s me.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="22"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“And his sister Jane, or Jenny Wildbriar—”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>My lad and lass first.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“The sum of two thousand pounds each.”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Well, we could ha’ done without that.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>It isn’t much, but it’s a summat, lad, as a token of remembrance; we’re
independent, thanks to my brother. <stage>(Lucy casts a glance at MRS.
WILDBRIAR)</stage> All right, lass; <stage>(to Lucy)</stage> I’ll say no
more.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“Items—To my old and valued friends, John Playfair, and William Cunningham,
whom I appoint joint trustees and executors of my will, the sums of two thousand
pounds each.”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>That’s as much as he has given us, his cousins.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>May be they want it, poor creatures, they look shabby enough.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“Item—To Mrs. Sophonisba Vavasour, relict of the late Henry Vavasour, the sum
of two thousand pounds.”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>That makes ten thousand pounds in all as yet.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“Item—To my nephew, Francis Hawthorne—”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Eh, that be my cousin—which be he? <stage>(Mrs. Wildbriar points to Frank,
Robin rises and goes to him)</stage> I mun shake hands wi’ him; how is thee,
lad?—I’m glad to see thee; I am for sure. <stage>(shakes hands with
Frank)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Silence, and sit down.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>I mun speak to my cousin.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Sit down; sit down do—or leave the room.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>Sit down; sit down, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Get off wi’ you! <stage>(sits down sulkily)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“Item—To my nephew, Francis Hawthorne, a life interest, chargeable upon the
general estate, of three hundred pounds per annum.”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>I breathe again.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>So do I. The heiress is now clear.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>And is that all to his own nephew?—shame of hissen.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Hush—hush, mamma.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>I cannot—I wunnot; it’s a shame, and I’ll give him summat mysen.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>So will I; we munnot see cousin wronged. Cheer up, lad.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“Item—To my second wife’s niece and long adopted daughter, Lucy Vavasour, a
life interest, chargeable upon the general estate, of five hundred pounds per
annum.”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Why he’s given her more than his nephew.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Great heaven, five hundred pounds a year, is that all? My poor child! And
what becomes of the rest?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>I guess; an hospital for ricketty engineers.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Or a bluecoat school for miners’ illegitimates.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“And all the remainder of my property and <pb n="22"/> personal estate,
inclusive of the mansion and manor of the Woodlands, the several farms and
rent-charges attached, and held under the same freehold, together with various
sums of money vested in railway scrip, government securities, Three per Cent.
Consols, Exchequer Bonds, and Bank Stock, &amp;c., &amp;c.,—”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside to Everard)</stage> Nearly a million.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“I give, will, and bequeath—ahem!”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>To—to whom?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“Jointly—to the said Francis Hawthorne and Lucy Vavasour, on condition of
their entering into and fulfilling a contract of marriage within six months from
the date of the publication of this my will.”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! that’s capital!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>First-rate!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Singular!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Wonderful!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Horrible!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Damnable!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>‘And in the event of the said Francis Hawthorne refusing to comply with the
prescribed condition, I give, will, and bequeath the whole of the above-named
property to the said Lucy Vavasour, her lawful heirs and executors.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>He’ll be none such a fou—eh, lad?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“Also, in the event of the said Lucy Vavasour declining to contract the
conditional marriage, I give, will, and bequeath the whole of the said property
to the said Francis Hawthorne, his lawful heirs and executors.”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>She’ll never be so soft—eh, lass?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>“And in the double event of the said Francis Hawthorne and Lucy Vavasour
mutually declining to accept of the condition, I give, will, and bequeath the
whole of my property and estate, subject only to the payment of the aforesaid
legacies and annuities, in trust, to my executors, to build and endow a
foundation school and hospital, for the pauper orphans of miners, born in the
neighbourhood of Alnwick, Northumberland, subject to the annexed rule and
conditions.” which I presume, it is quite useless for me to read to the present
company. And now, there are six months, short of one hour, left for the
interested parties to determine their acceptance or rejection of the condition;
during which, this mansion, with its usual establishment of servants, &amp;c,
will be at their service, for the entertainment of their friends and families,
in accordance with the testator’s directions to the executor’s, endorsed upon
this his will.</p>
</sp>

<stage>(all rise and put back their chairs except Lucy and Frank, who sit on
opposite sides of stage, L.C. and R. C.)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>My poor child!—disposed of!—doomed!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>No! neither disposed of, nor doomed. I am still mistress of myself; and who
knows—it may be for the best?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>I wish you joy!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Joy—joy!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Joy—joy! who knows—it may be misery?</p>
</sp>

<trailer>END OF ACT I.</trailer>
</div>
</div>

<div type="act" n="2">
<head>ACT II.</head>
<stage>A lapse of three months is supposed to have occurred.</stage>

<div type="scene" n="1">
<head>Scene same as in Act I.</head>
<stage>Enter James and Jemima, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Yes, Miss Jemima Simperton, {h}of all the {h}extraordinary positions that a
{h}upper servant {h}as ever been placed in, mine is the most trying and
{h}inimical to my feelings, {h}ever since that {h}eccentric will of the formerly
late lamented, but now {h}ungretted George Hawthorne, Esq., was promulgated, I
ave been in perpetual ‘ot water. How can a {h}upper servant preserve his dignity
to the lowers, when he don’t know who is his master, and when he has to deliver
his {h}orders as from one to the {h}adherents of the other?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F14">
<speaker>Jemima.</speaker>
<p>It is very difficult indeed; and nobody but yourself, Mr. James, could manage
to preserve any appearance of regularity in a house under such divided control.
As in the play, we have the Capulets and Montagues on each side, never meeting
but to wrangle.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>hexcuse me, but the play aint a comparison at all—hit’s {h}only {h}image is
the House of Commons, with two {h}oppositions, a {h}independent country party,
and some {h}outsiders, that don’t know their own minds; and I’m in the position
of the unfortunate Speaker, who is obliged to listen to all the jaw (eloquence,
I should have said, of the {h}uppers—the lords), and for the sake of the
respectability of the ‘ouse itself, is compelled to keep up a {h}imposing
{h}aspect of attention, and a wigilant {h}eye on the uproarious junior, and
Hirish members; and I see no prospect of a coalition neither; the <stage>R. L.
Adolphus. Robin. Jenny. Everard. Miss E. Sir L. Mrs. V. Lucy. Mr. C. Mrs. W.
Frank. Dr. P.</stage>
<pb n="25"/>leaders—as the leaders always is—are too polite to look each other
in the face.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F14">
<speaker>Jemima.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Miss Lucy will never marry Mr. Hawthorne, of that I am
sure: she was always partial to the baronet, and you see he is still here and
attentive.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> So he is; but he is only a trimming, I can see, and
{h}aint popped the question yet, and never will, if she loses the fortune: he’s
poor, and his ‘igh blood is worth a fortune, and he’ll not sacrifice at the
‘ymenial {h}alter unless Plutus gives away the bride.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F14">
<speaker>Jemima.</speaker>
<p>What a fine figure of speech to be sure. I should have thought that he was
above mercenary motives.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>So he is; {h}it’s his dignity that requires to be upheld by the needful, and
he must victimize his affections to the {h}integrity of the baronetcy, which is
mortgaged to the very verge of bankruptcy.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F14">
<speaker>Jemima.</speaker>
<p>If Mr. Hawthorne were only a gentleman now, he might be induced to sacrifice
the fortune and decline the condition.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>If he did he would prove himself a <hi>demned</hi> fool.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F14">
<speaker>Jemima.</speaker>
<p>Mr. James!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>{H}excuse the wigorous expression; but even an {h}aristocrat of the purest
Norman blood could not be expected to resign his claim to such an inheritance on
account of being inimical to the co-heiress. The days of such high-flown
sentiments and factions is faded and gone. We sacrifice our {h}affections, but
we never sacrifice our worldly interests. It {h}aint the fashion in {h}upper, or
even in middle life. Such things are only heard of now in {H}east {h}end
melo-dramas.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F14">
<speaker>Jemima.</speaker>
<p>What a nice little bit of flirtation there seems to be going on between Mr.
Everard Digby and Miss Jenny Wildbriar.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>I ‘ave observed that, and I hardly think it fair. She is the only member of
her family that’s deserving of respect, and he ought not to try and turn the
girl’s head if he don’t mean marriage, which her low birth and connections would
make disreputable for a barrister so highly connected.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F14">
<speaker>Jemima.</speaker>
<p>I don’t know that; he seems very much smitten, and he’s kept in countenance
by the Honorable Augustus Adolphus, who has begun to ogle that vulgar old woman,
the mother, and Miss Euphemia Cholmondeley, who actually affects a sentimental
attachment towards the cub of a son.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>You ‘orrify and astonish me with the noos. What is the {h}aristocracy coming
to after that? Pounds, shillings, and pence is a hobject—‘as ever been, I know,
with the best of us—but some regard for position, for {h}elegance, bought to
accompany it. Miss Jemima, if such should be the case—I—I <pb n="26"/>shall
leave the {h}aristocracy to hits fate, and whilst I can preserve some
recollection of its ancient dignity, retire into private life, and not {h}even
{h}open an ‘otel nor a liquor waults. As my favorite {h}author says—</p>
<lg>
<l>“Let wealth and commerce—arts and science—die,</l>
<l>But give us still our old nobility.”</l>
</lg>
<stage>Exeunt, L. 1 E.</stage>
</sp>

<stage>Frank Hawthorne enters from library, L. 3 E. He looks round, then comes
down and gazes a few moments on the picture of Lucy, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Like; very like—and oh, how beautiful! Not the beauty that dazzles at the
first glance—dulls upon the second— to grow vapid, vulgar, at the third—the
rarer beauty of expression, whose fascination steals over you as you gaze, and
seems to wile away your soul. And yet, I think a high spirit lightens in those
eyes. She will not sell herself for gold, she will sooner accept poverty. How to
win her confidence, to read her heart, to conquer it? No way. She must hate me
as the imposed and conditional husband, linked to no generosity, the
representative of the niggard doubt that tasked the golden boon. Seldom as we
meet, and quickly as we turn from each other, as by some repellant instinct, I
have noted that her cheek grows pale, and despite of her self-control, an
expression of repugnance—a shudder passes over her form. Well, well, the time
will soon come to spare her that; and yet would I give the world to prolong the
ordeal that sometimes yields her to my eyes. Yes, yes, to win her smile, I think
I could play slave and fool unto the very verge of baseness.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Dr. Playfair, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Umph! in the absence of the original, I see you make love to the
portrait.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I—I? oh, no. I am an admirer of good pictures, and I was just noticing the
exquisite finish of this portrait. I presume, from the style, painted by—by
Landseer.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that. If you had looked at the whole picture instead of the face
only, you would have remarked that there was no dog in it, and therefore not
likely to be by Landseer, who in my opinion in addition to being one of the best
painters, is the greatest satirist of the age, for he never paints man or woman
unaccompanied by a puppy. <stage>(Frank laughs)</stage> There, I’ve got you
nicely out of your anger, and your shame too. I object to both; particularly to
the latter. No reason to be ashamed of trying to scrape acquaintance with your
future wife’s character through the medium of her portrait. As yet <pb n="27"
/>you haven’t had much chance of studying the original: you ought—time’s getting
on.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> This gentleman may mean well, but he lays too rough a
hand upon the wound to be entrusted with its cure. Sir, if you speak in
badinage, you are quite welcome to a laugh at my expense; if seriously, allow me
to say, not in anger but earnestly, that this is one of the subjects upon which
I neither give confidence nor take advice. As for the picture, if you will look
at the scroll work in the left corner, you will find Edwin Landseer’s pencilled
autograph, who, in this instance as I dare say in many others, having to paint a
truly beautiful woman, thought but of his subject, and left—the puppy out.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exit, R. 3 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Out—outside I suppose the fellow means, implying me. I’m afraid its a truth.
I have no business to bark at his heels, since he objects to it. Confound him!
he always gets the better of me at the wind-up of a dispute, and hang me if I
don’t begin to feel a friendship for him. I shan’t be able to object to anything
he says by and bye.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Lucy, Mrs. Vavasour, and Sir Lionel, R. 1 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Oh, here is Dr. Playfair, and he will give us his
advice.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that. Never give advice—it’s a complete waste of time and
thought; for although everybody asks and endeavours to extort it, no one ever
allows it to exercise the slightest influence upon purpose or opinion.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>That may be the rule, Doctor, and you will allow me to be the exception.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that. Why should you be a greater fool than your neighbour, as
you must be if you permitted anybody’s judgment but your own to guide your
conduct?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Well, but, Doctor, you and I have always been friends, and surely I may task
your kindness to the extent of an opinion upon a matter that deeply affects my
welfare.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Well, I don’t object to that; you are one of the very few
people I like, so now propound your problem, and I’ll solve it if I can.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Well, the question is, what am I to do with him?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Him—and who is Mr. Him? Your lap-dog, with the snuffles in his nose, or your
cast-off beau, with the jaundice in the whites of his eyes?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, for shame! I am serious, and you know very well the disagreeable him of
whom I speak.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that, because I don’t.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>It’s Mr. Hawthorne. We want to devise some means of preserving the property,
and disposing of him.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="28"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>The readiest way to dispose of him, is to marry him.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>You wouldn’t have my daughter marry a clod?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Why not?— It was a clod of the same clay that made all the money; but I
object to the term clod, it’s not apposite. If you will be figurative, call them
nuggets.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Ah, well, the particular nugget that remains I don’t like.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Well, do as I tell my squeamish patients with a draught or a pill, gulp it,
and take the sugar after.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, to me, this is rude and unkind.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>So it is, and I beg pardon. If you really wish to keep the property——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Oh, that doesn’t admit of a question. <stage>(seats herself at R.
table)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>And to get rid of Hawthorne?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>That I certainly do.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>You must offend him, and incur his dislike.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Surely I have done that by avoiding him.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that—worst way in the world; he was rather struck with you, and
sees only the romance of the tie formed by the will. He’s in love with you: I
caught him a few moments since gazing in silent devotion on that picture of
yours;—he’s always to be found on the terrace, or at one of the windows, slily
peering at you every time you go out into the grounds; in fact, he watches and
worships your rising and setting, as a fire-worshipper the sun, or a lunatic the
moon.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Vulgar creature!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(at table, R.)</stage> Impudent puppy!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Poor fellow!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> She pities him; and I don’t object to that. He dreams
of you in your retirement; and his fancy makes you twice as handsome as you
are.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(curtseying)</stage> Thank you, doctor.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(comes down, R.)</stage> Surely——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Don’t speak, Sir Lionel. I know you were going to say that that is scarcely
possible.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Bosh!</p>
</sp>

<stage>(Sir Lionel goes to table, R.)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha! you hear! but don’t interfere—the doctor and I are old friends.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>And gives you four times the number of virtues and graces that any woman
possibly can possess. In short, he idealizes you into a divinity; and all this
is due to your avoidance.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Now, doctor, you are really too ungallant. Surely you do not mean to imply
that my presence must necessarily <pb n="29"/>dissipate any good opinion that
may have been previously formed of me?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>That depends upon your conduct. He’s sensitive and high-minded, and seems to
have a good stock of common sense; you have only to surprise him with a little
drawingroom coquetry; alarm him with an exhibition of frivolity; vex him with
some heartless badinage; and season the whole with a huge admixture of twaddle
(you must know how, having lived so long in good society); and, my life on it,
he’ll reject you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Ha! ha! ha! the doctor’s recipe for getting rid of a
sensible, sensitive, high-minded man.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> About whom you begin to feel an interest, despite of
your professed dislike. It will bring them together; and if she likes him, she
will soon give over playing a part.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Well, I’ll do it; that is, I’ll try to conceal my natural graces—ahem,
doctor—and to assume as many disagreeable airs and follies as the aforesaid will
permit.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>But what if the fellow should prove, as I think, a mere simpleton, and not
take umbrage at this treatment?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>As a dernier resort, I can always decline.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises)</stage> And lose the property, my child! you must not
entertain such an idea.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> No, no; for then to decline would be my dernier
resort.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>He’s coming this way to have another gaze at the picture. Present him the
original, and commence your game.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Well, if it must be done, the sooner it is got over the better.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Shall we remain?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh no! you must be my reserve corps, upon whose aid I can fall back, if
necessary; at first, I must attack the enemy single-handed.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>You’ll find him a formidable foe, or I am much mistaken; he has always put me
to the rout.</p>
<stage>Exit, L.</stage>
</sp>

<stage>Exeunt Sir Lionel and Mrs. Vavasour, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Dear me! Now that I am alone, I begin to feel a little nervous, and my heart
flutters. I wish I had not heard of his admiration of my portrait, or the
doctor’s encomiums on his good sense. It is not pleasant to be obliged to incur
any sensible person’s contempt. I feel a great disposition to run away. No, no—I
am too English for that. He must not see me when he enters, or perhaps he’ll run
away. I’ll entrench myself in this chair, and not open fire until the enemy is
within range. <stage>(she sits in large easy chair, L. C.)</stage></p>
</sp>
<pb n="30"/>
<stage>Enter Frank, R. 3 E. from conservatory, looks round, and comes down as
before, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>It is true—my portrait, sure enough, is the object of his attention.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Heigho!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>He sighs, poor fellow—fool, I should say; and yet I pity him. Heigho!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(overhearing, turns and perceives her)</stage> Miss Vavasour!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>La! Mr. Hawthorne, is it you? <stage>(smiles graciously)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Yes; I beg your pardon; I didn’t know that you were here—I shall retire.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, pray do not! Is my company so very—very disagreeable, that you can’t
endure it for a moment or two?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no—no. Can it be possible you think that such is my feeling?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I must think so, if you continue to run away every time we chance to
meet.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>True—true; but I was only fearful of intruding upon you an unwelcome
presence.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, that doesn’t matter; it is—heigho!—our duty to become acquainted. It is
not, Mr.—Mr. Hawthorne?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Yes; that is, if it is your pleasure.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, I dare say I shall have much pleasure, if you’ll only permit me. Pray, be
seated. <stage>(he looks awkwardly around)</stage> Do sit down.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(taking a chair at a distance, R.)</stage> There is something under
this sudden change.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I can’t look at him. Excuse me, will you do me the favour to hand me my fan?
You will find it on the table near you. <stage>(he rises and gives it, and
returns to his chair)</stage> Thank you; I am sorry to trouble you, but I’m so
affected with ennui this morning, that I can’t bear to get out of my chair, and
in a <hi>tête-à-tête</hi> with a gentleman, I can never speak, or even look at
him, save from behind my fan. <stage>(aside)</stage> He’s rather good-looking,
but awkward to a degree.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>My idol’s feet, I begin to fear, are made of clay. Or is this a ruse? If so,
I’ll balk it. She thinks me fool. I’ll play the fool.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I saw you looking at my portrait. Do you think it like?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I did—very like.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Did, but don’t. I’m getting on famously. Didn’t you think it rather
dreamy-looking with that sort of expression the critics term ideal, but which I
call moonishness?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated R.)</stage> I think it conveys the expression of which you
speak.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Which does he mean, I wonder? Oh! then it must <pb n="31"/> be very unlike
me, for I’m not in the least moonish or poetical. Will you pardon me? I have
some crochet work in that little basket on the table over there, which you will
favour me by handing. <stage>(he rises and brings it from upper table, R., takes
fan, and places it on table)</stage> I can work now, as I have got rid of the
nervousness consequent upon our first <hi>tête-à-tête</hi>. You needn’t wander
all the way back to that distant chair, there is one close by.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> This is barefaced coquetry, or it masks some designs.
Thank you—as you please. <stage>(takes chair R. C., and seats
himself)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>As I please! How gawkily done. You admire the Woodlands?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Much. Eh!—that is, I think it a nice place enough.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Nice place! and that is all he has to say of my beautiful Woodlands. He’s
either soulless, or vexed; so much the better. Will you excuse me again? I think
I should prefer my embroidery to this crotchet work, Mr. Hawthorne, you’ll find
a frame and design on that table to my left hand. I can’t shake off this
<hi>ennui</hi> to-day, and am as changeful in desire as a child. I’ve all my
life been a spoilt one.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(gets embroidery frame from L. table, and comes down L.—aside)</stage>
So it would appear; and yet there is a soul-like light flashing from under those
half-closed eyes— there is a melody of tenderness rippling through those
affected tones, that, like spells, charm me into yielding to this folly.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated, L. C., pouting)</stage> No silk on the reel!—oh! here is a
skein. Ahem! Mr. Hawthorne, will you think it too feminine a task to hold it on
your hands whilst I wind? Hercules, or some very heroic gentleman of olden time,
I believe, did something like it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.—aside)</stage> I don’t wonder at him, if Omphale was anything like
you.</p>
</sp>

<stage>(he holds his hands awkwardly and close together, she puts them apart—he
then raises them very high and afterwards drops very low)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>You are too tall, or you hold your hands too high— and now too low. See,
there is a footstool upon which you can seat yourself. <stage>(pushing footstool
towards him—he sits on low stool, L.)</stage> Docile and patient as a spaniel.
<stage>(winds silk, and labours to restrain laughter)</stage> Ha! ha! ha! Excuse
me, Mr. Hawthorne, but—but you do look so ridiculous. Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(on the stool)</stage> I dare say that I do. Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh! you can be good-tempered enough to laugh at yourself.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="32"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Perhaps I should not, if I had not perceived almost from the first that you
were acting a part, and disguising your real nature for some purpose.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Pray pardon me, sir, I confess it. <stage>(rises, crosses, R. C.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>You do? Ah! that is honest, and I most sincerely admire your frankness, and
forgive the ruse. <stage>(rises)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, dear, what have I done? I’m spoiling all. Yes—yes, I had a motive—a
purpose—one I didn’t mean to tell you, though; but I suppose I must, now. I—I
wanted to see—to see how you would go in harness.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Harness! what does she mean?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Yes, you know that under our circumstances it wouldn’t be comfortable to find
ourselves straining to go separate roads when we are harnessed.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Excuse me, but I don’t understand what you mean by being harnessed.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Why, married, to be sure. The will says we are to be; and what is marriage,
but the fettering of two parties together whose tastes generally differ, but
whose interest and convenience it is to travel the same road, and not quarrel by
the way.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Dare I tell you what I think marriage to be?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh! yes, I should like to know your ideas. I have told you mine.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Pardon me, I think not. You have but echoed the cant of the <hi>blazé</hi>
inconstants—the reckless <hi>roués</hi> of the world—who seek to bury principle
in the grave of passion. Marriage is at once the most solemn and the most
beautiful mystery of this life; and as among nations, a reverence for its
sacredness, as an indissoluble, an untransgressible bond between two beings, and
only two, is the highest test of civilization, so the nobler the estimate
individual man or woman forms of its obligations, the higher must each be lifted
in the scale of humanity. Do you not believe me?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I do, I do, with all my heart and soul.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Ah! I thought so.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh! I’m ensnared again! I can’t play the game any longer without aid.
<stage>(laugh outside, R.)</stage> Ah! here comes that Mr. Adolphus, and my beau
ideal of a preux chevalier, Sir Lionel Norman.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Mrs. Vavasour. Augustus, and Sir Lionel, R. 1 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! a capital design! I’m so glad that you have made me a party to the
joke.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Yes, it’s a disagreeable necessity <stage>(affecting
surprise)</stage> What, Lucy and Mr. Hawthorne <hi>tête-à-tête</hi>?</p>
</sp>
<pb n="33"/>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Yes, mamma: you know it is necessary that we should become acquainted.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>So, the play begins again.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes! Let people be ever so unlikely to be found together after marriage,
it is customary to preface the ceremony with a little show of sociality.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Oh, of course; we do as we like afterwards. He can speak tolerable English, I
suppose. <stage>(seats herself)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes, mamma; he speaks very well, and is not near so dull as you might
imagine. <stage>(seated)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Is this said to test the extent of my love, or to offend me?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>He bears that; his spirit has sunk many fathoms deep in love or
stupidity.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>As he has just come up, as it were, from the other world, no doubt you found
the gentleman’s conversation highly entertaining?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Yes; of its very novelty, however bizarre, it must have served to amuse.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, dear, no! it was edifying. Mr. Hawthorne is rather of a serious bent of
mind; and on the solemn subject of marriage, did not fail to improve the
occasion.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>What, a Spurgeonite! imbued with the afflatus of the conventicle!—the large,
the very large conventicle! Catch-em-alive, oh! He would make thee a sister of
grace before leading thee to the tabernacle. <stage>(goes up L.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha! <stage>(Frank laughs heartily)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>The fool laughs at himself.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Really, that pathetic mingling of piety and passion— of the parson in the
Romeo—the puritan in the Corydon— seems to me as the most incongruous—the most
laughable of bipeds.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>I have never beheld one when the spirit moved: I should so like to hear him
hold forth.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(crosses to Frank)</stage> Perhaps the gentleman will oblige us?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>He doesn’t understand, and is silent.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>I addressed you, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Did you? Then allow me to say, that I could not have imagined so fine a
gentlemen capable of such point blank rudeness.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh! I vow he’s angry! <stage>(goes to Frank)</stage> Now, my dear fellow, be
good humoured. You really mustn’t attempt to sermonize us. <stage>(turns up
stage)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>No; If you can’t lightly give and take, nor yet endure the privileged
sarcasms—the badinage of drawing-room<pb n="34"/> society—you had better not
venture within its pale. <stage>(goes up, R., and sits)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(crosses to Frank)</stage> Sir Lionel is quite right; you must not
lose your temper at a little banter: if you can’t reply in the same spirit, you
had better hold your tongue. <stage>(crosses, R.)</stage> Sir Lionel, I go to
make my toilet for our drive. Mr. Hawthorne, we shall meet again soon, I hope.
Why, what’s the matter? <stage>(returns, L.)</stage> You are not jealous of my
going to take a drive with Sir Lionel?—you must not, because I like Sir Lionel,
and I hate jealousy. I shall expect you to prove a very gentlemanly husband, and
to forgive all my caprices and follies, and extravagancies—and I’m over burdened
with them, I can assure you; if you doubt it, ask my friends yonder, and they’ll
give me such a character: even Sir Lionel will tell you that I am very captious;
but then, you know, I have always had my own way, and we are to have so much
money, that were I even wicked, you could not help but have me. How you look!
Oh, no! I don’t mean quite that; I am not so unwomanly.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I thought not.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>There, I’ve forgot again; <stage>(crosses, R.)</stage> so be good humoured
when next we meet, and we may be good friends in—in time. If that doesn’t
determine him to reject me, my game is played out.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exeunt Mrs. Vavasour and Lucy, R. 1 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>We may be good friends in time—never, never— did you mean what you say? but
you don’t—you don’t; your lips scorn the words that cross them, and your eyes
recant them quicker than your lips pronounce, or love conspires with thee to
make me slave and fool.</p>
<stage>Exit into library, L. 3 E.</stage>
</sp>


<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>The fellow is a complete puzzle; he’s not likely to be shaken off.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>I’m afraid not, and your chance of adding the Woodlands to the entail of the
baronetcy is but slight, but you will have a beautiful wife.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Perhaps; but she must be an heiress.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Oh, lady heiresses are few and far between. Our
friend, the Marquis of Banterdown, has wisely enough marked down the nabob’s
niece.</p>

<stage>Frank re-enters, to take his hat and gloves from table—they do not
perceive him)</stage>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>She is a very nice little girl. <stage>(seated)</stage> How she ever grew
upon the Wildbriar tree is a puzzle; but the mother and son are
insufferable.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh, the Wildbriars are not so bad after all. Country bred, with amiable
aspirations.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="35"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Ah, you have been taken into confidence, Adolphus—and see them by the light
of a lac of rupees.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Ah, well, their manners are certainly rustic—I may say very rustic—but time
will amend these—must, for the widow has been left £250,000.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>You astonish me! £250,000? Why, that in amount treads upon the heels of the
Hawthorne fortune.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Yes, she talks of giving son and daughter each a hundred thousand, and of
keeping fifty for herself, to make presents to her granchildren, when such buds
blossom.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Well, although whilst a hope remains of her inheriting, I’m the Endymion
proper, most professedly a minion of our Diana of the Woodlands, I think I could
contentedly retire from the chase, if that little Hebe, Miss Wildbriar, were to
be caught and hid away from her Satyr-like kindred.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Ahem! <stage>(they start and turn)</stage> Good morning, gentlemen.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exit, L. 3 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises)</stage> Confound it, that fellow here? I hope he has not
overheard my last remark.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises)</stage> If he has, what does it matter; he can’t translate it.
Your classical metaphor were as much a riddle to him, as Greek proved to the
majority of a reformed House of Commons.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! true, it is likely; but Miss Vavasour’s toilet is, I dare say,
complete.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>And Diana awaits her Endymion.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exeunt Sir Lionel, R., Adolphus, L.</stage>
</div>

<div type="scene" n="2">
<head>Scene Second.</head>
<stage>A Chamber (1st grooves).</stage>
<stage>Enter Mrs. Wildbriar, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Here, Jenny, Jenny, lass; Hob, Rob, where are you? Drat that lad and lass,
they’re always out of the way when I want them.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Adolphus, L. 1 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Did I not hear Mrs. Wildbriar’s voice? Great heaven! whom do I behold; surely
my ear must have deceived me, and yet the contour, the figure can only belong to
one— it is Mrs. Wildbriar.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Yes; I’m mysen sure enough. What is’t makes man doubt?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>This magnificent toilet has so added to your natural advantages, that,
joined, they took me by surprise; and I fancied I beheld a still more beautiful
woman.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Got away wi’ you. I’m well enough, but I’m not<pb n="36"/> so soft as to
swallow all that blarney; I don’t like saft sawder, so ha’ done wi’ it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>I beg your pardon, but I assure you that that dress becomes you
amazingly.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Oh, the dress: well, I think it does favor itsen— it ought, for it cost
enough of money. Eh! I dunnot mind telling you it took a start out of me when it
was first brought home. My servant lass had put it out in the middle of my
bedroom, and it was standing up of itsen, and spread out, so that when I saw it,
I thought some one was inside, and going to run away wi’ it, and I shrieked out
for help—eh! didn’t my lad and lass laugh at me—it was the iron thingamygigs
inside—they call ‘em crinoline—that stuck it out like a balloon, and I wouldn’t
wear none o’them: I couldn’t ha’ gotten out of door if I had put it on; I’m sure
I couldn’t, I’m big enough ‘about.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh! you are by no means remarkably <hi>embonpoint</hi>.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>That’s French for plump, isn’t it? I’ve heard it before from my Jenny. Eh! I
was as slim as she is when I married my poor old man; he wouldn’t know me now
were he alive.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>He must have been a very happy man. Heigho!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>What’s the matter wi’ the man, aint you well, that you breathe so hard?—hast
the cholic-spasm, or a stitch in thy side? You can cure either immediately by
taking a sup of burnt brandy.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no; it’s an affection of the heart.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Heartburn, mayhap?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Yes, my heart does burn.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Well, a little soda, or a bit of magnesia, will make that all right; if
they’re not handy, nibble a bit of chalk. I often do myself.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Ugh! sentiment here is thrown away; where ignorance is
bliss, ’tis folly to be wise. No, no, my dear madam, it was a flutter of the
heart, to which I am always subject—<stage>(aside)</stage> in the neighbourhood
of any woman worth a certain number of thousands.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Flutter of the heart, eh? I never had that but once, when I saw my old man in
company with another lass, just a day before he got my leave to put up the
askings; and he owned to me after that, that he did it on purpose to make me not
hold him too cheap. Ah! he was a sly chap, my mester, but a good man for all
that. But tell me, have you seen my lad or lass anywhere?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>I think Miss Wildbriar is walking in the avenue with Mr. Everard Digby.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>With the marquis? I’m afraid he’ll turn the girl’s head; if he doesn’t mean
to marry her it’s a great shame, and <pb n="37"/>so I’ll quickly tell him. She’s
as good as he, if he were twice a marquis, and may be has more money; for I’ve
heard that some of these lords and ladies are just as poor as they are proud.
<stage>(Adolphus looks abashed, thinking the conversation levelled at
him)</stage> Eh! and do you know I begin to think that that stuck-up Miss
Euphemia is as sweet upon my Rob as the marquis is on Jenny. I wonder where she
is?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Ahem! I think I may gain favour by revealing the truth as respects Miss
Euphemia. May I propose a stroll while I impart a secret to you, Mrs. Wildbriar?
<stage>(crosses to R.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>I wanted either the lad or the lass to keep me company, as I have got the
rheumatiz in my ancle, and must have some one to lean on; and besides, I hate
walking alone.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>I shall be most happy to be permitted to offer my arm; pray lean on it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! it aint much of an arm you have to lean on, man; I should tire you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Fear not; animated by a spirit of admiration, it would sustain you for a life
time.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! it ‘ud break in two under half my weight in a jiffey; but as I cannot do
‘bout a stick of some sort, I may as well have you as another, and I shan’t lean
heavy on thee; so come along, and tell us your secret.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exeunt, R.</stage>
<stage>Enter Robin and Miss Euphemia, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>I say, mother!—oh, she’s gone.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>And so, Mr. Wildbriar, you don’t share in the general admiration bestowed
upon the Woodlands?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Oh, the place itsen is first rate; but there aint no
pleasant sociable company in it—all stuck-up baronets and honourables, and fine
ladies with their noses in the air. There’s that cousin of mine, I did think to
have found a bit of a chum in him, but he’s no better than the rest: don’t care
a bit about a rat hunt, ferreting rabbits, or bowls, or skittles, or dog fights.
Jenny is in love with one of the stuck-ups, and mother thinks o’ nothing now but
dressing and undressing hersen; and if it weren’t for that terrier pup, I should
have no society at all out or in doors.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Oh! don’t say that; I’m sure I’m always happy to meet
you, and ever find pleasure in your conversation.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>No, do you? well that is kind of you; but may be it’s because no one else
cares much about speaking to you;— excuse me, I come fra Lancashire, and always
speaks my mind. <stage>(aside)</stage> except when sister Jenny’s by to put the
stopper on.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>I admire your candour; and it may be a sympathy arising from the neglect we
mutually experience, that suggests the friendly interest that exists between
us.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="38"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Oh, I have no interest at all in the matter; you speak to me, and I speak to
you in return, and much obliged. I’m a civil lad, and no wastrail. Are you fond
o’ toffey?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Toffey!—I must plead ignorance of what it is.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>No! Where were you brought up?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>In Paris principally.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Ah, that accounts for your not knowing English. It’s made of sugar and butter
baked in a pan. I’ve got some real Everton—brought a stock with me—and I’ll let
you have a lump when I see you again.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>I shall prize any gift of yours.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Eh! you mun eat it, woman, and not prize it. I say, you don’t like their
manner of living in this house, do you?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Ahem!—not much.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Neither do I;—there’s no getting a meal in decent time; they eat their
breakfast when they should be taking their dinner, their dinner when they should
have done their tea, and their tea when it’s supper time, and their supper when
they should be waking out of their first sleep.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Earlier hours would certainly be more healthful.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Aye, that they would; and what’s worst of all is the lots of slops and
made-up dishes that come on the table before you can get anything substantial to
eat, and nothing much then. I did think to enjoy my dinner yesterday, because
there was a giblet pie, but there was no black pudding in it, and it warn’t
worth much. You like black puddings, of course?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Black currant puddings?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>What!—Black currant pudding in a giblet pie? Noa, black puddings made wi’
pig’s meat and groats or oatmeal, Eh! when we lived on the farm we always had
such a stock; mother makes them prime! but what’s worst here is that they never
have a dumpling to begin with. You know what they are, I suppose?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Yes, when a child I remember being partial to an apple dumpling.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Oh, I mean suet dumplings; hard ones, to eat wi’ gravy, pepper and salt, or
it may be treacle—good hard ‘uns; them’s the chaps to fill up; if I could only
catch mother out of a fine dress, I’d persuade her to go down into the kitchen
and make some, just for once; she makes them better than any one else—first
rate. Oh, you should taste mother’s dumplings.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>I should be most happy.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Would you?—then, ecod, I’ll get mother to make some to-day, eh? This is the
only bit of pleasant conversation I’ve had since I’ve been here. She’s a
stunning nice girl after all; rather thin, but dumplings would bring her round
soon. She seems to be sweet on me, and I’m in a great mind to make <pb n="39"
/>up to her. Hem!—that is the way them stuck-up chaps do— Hem! hem!—Were you
ever in Lancashire?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>No; I should like to visit it much—it’s a delightful expectation with me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>No; is it? I say, you’re a rare nice wench to talk to. If I were to offer to
gi’ thee a buss, you wouldn’t lug or pow my hair, would you?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>I really don’t know what you mean.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Don’t understand Lancashire English at all?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>I must confess ignorance of those words.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Ah, I shall be obliged to give her up; never get along wi’ her so
ignorant.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>But I should be very willing to learn.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Noa, would you?—ecod, then I’ll begin to teach you. You see, this is a buss.
<stage>(kisses her, she slightly screams)</stage>
<stage>Enter Sir Lionel and Everard, R., she runs off, L.</stage> Eh, don't be
frightened, lass; I don't care the toss up of an old button for these chaps, wi'
all their grandeur. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Sir L. | Everard</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha, ha!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<stage>(L.)</stage>
<p>Haw, haw! wwhat are you laughing at ? I'll be bound that both on you ha'
kissed your sweethearts in secret as well as me, and when you're alone — you wi'
my sister, and you wi' Miss Lucy, I don't interfere or intrude on you — do
I?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Sir L. | Everard</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha, ha!</p>
</sp>
<stage>Cross stage and exeunt, L.</stage>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Haw, haw! — you may haw, haw, as much as you like; but I'll fight either of
you, with or without clogs on, Lancashire fasion, on the grass plat yonder if
you please.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Mrs. Wildbriar, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>I’ll fight you, if I hear you making such a noise in the house. What’s up wi’
you at all, man?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Well, them two stuck-up chaps were laughing at and jeering me, because they
caught me give Miss What-you-call-her a buss.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! did you give her a buss?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>I did.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Buss her again, lad, if thou likes it; I didn’t think thee had so much pluck
in thee. Let them laugh as wins. Gie me a buss, lad; you are as good as they wi’
all their parade, and I’ll make thee some dumplings for thy dinner.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Noa, will you? Hurrah! Dumplings for ever!</p>
</sp>
<stage>Exeunt, L.</stage>
</div>
<pb n="40"/>
<div type="scene" n="3">
<head>Scene Third.</head>
<stage>The Central Space within a maze of shrubberies. A little fountain
margined with flowers; seats set around; the termini of the paths opening on
stage, and describing a crescent, the front of stage being supposed to complete
the circle; some of the shrubs in blossom, others with beds of flowers
underneath; small terminal statues, with parasites twined round pedestals,
&amp;c., at back above the shrubberies a side view of the house; lawn; woods
beyond.</stage>
<stage>Enter Miss Jenny Wildbriar, R. 4 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Everard Digby does not seem to know his own mind, except to the extent of
being in love with me—that’s of course. Very innocent or very stupid he must be,
if he cannot see that I am only waiting to be asked: to blush, hesitate, look
aside, and say, or rather sigh, Yes.—This problem I ought to solve, will solve,
shall solve. Oh! I know I shall, for I know that I’m a clever little girl, and
that he’s in love with me, and that I’m in love with him, and with plenty of
money there can be but one solution—marriage! Bravo! clever little girl. But
it’s still to be wrought out:—how? Make him jealous. Yes: of whom?—the elegant
but sly Sir Lionel Norman, who has seen that I am pretty and well-mannered, if
not so handsome or high-bred as Miss Vavasour, and possibly may prove richer,
and so spares me a little indirect attention, just sufficiently pointed, when I
meet him alone, to suggest a motive, and to be an excuse for a grand avowal, if
that should hereafter prove politic. Clever man; but what of that? there never
was a male coquette a match at his own game for a clever little girl. Oh, he is
here.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Sir Lionel, R. 1 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>One hundred thousand pounds, with a reversion of twenty-five thousand pounds
at the least; and she’s pretty, very pretty, and surprisingly well-mannered.
Soft! she is here. Young girls like sentiment, and adore heroics. Ahem! “Is it a
nymph, a naaid, or a Grace, that with her presence queens this lovely
place?”</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Sir Lionel, is it you? Oh, dear! Strange too: although
you have taken me by surprise, you have caught the very spirit of my day-dream,
echoed the very motive of my musing.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>And “What didst thou muse on, meditating maid?” Shall I go on? “On earth thou
standest, thy thoughts ascend to heaven.”<note type="ed">Quoted from John Home's
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_(play)">Douglas (1756)</ref>
</note></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh, dear, no! mine were very terrestrial thoughts, I was just thinking what a
beautiful place the Woodlands is, and wishing ——</p>
</sp>
<pb n="41"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>To be mistress of such another.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Nay; it is too large a setting for a little Lancashire diamond, too extensive
a kingdom to be queened with becoming dignity by such a little rustic body as
myself. I should like to steal a nook out of it, like this; no grand woods, but
orchards and shrubberies, and a <hi>petite</hi> lawn, that a couple of limes or
sycamores would serve to embower, and a low, quaint, old-fashioned house,
cloisteral in its outward appearance, but luxuriously elegant, and yet cozy, if
I may couple the terms, within. I should feel at home there; a sort of Rosamond
in her bower, or Amy Robsart at Cumnor:<note type="ed"
>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amy_Robsart_(play)</note> the Woodlands is too
much of a Windsor, or a Kenilworth, for poor little me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>What charming naïvete! Of all wildbriar roses, surely this is the
prettiest.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>I have heard it said that Norman Abbey is not unlike my ideal, Sir Lionel; is
it so?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>You have poetized, and yet most faithfully described my ancestral home.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh! I should so like to see it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Would you? you may—you shall, if it so please you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>And yet, no; for if it should realize my dream, I should be loath to leave
it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> I begin to think that I should be loath to let you
leave.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>And you know that I should have to do that.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> I don’t know any such thing; there could be no more
welcome presence to the house or to the master.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh! now you flatter.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Indeed, I do not: short as our acquaintance has been, Miss Wildbriar, I
assure you that it has sufficed to awaken feelings in my breast of the warmest
admiration, and the most earnest respect for my new and charming friend.
<stage>(aside)</stage> That is hinting a great deal, and not saying too
much.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>And this is not a mere compliment?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>It is a profound truth.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Heigho!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>You sigh; surely I have not offended?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no. Have you to learn, Sir Lionel, that sighs are sometimes expressive of
happiness?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> That is a fair challenge, but I must not go too far.
May I, in remembrance, and in token of the acknowledged sympathy between us,
present you with this beautiful camelia japonica?</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Everard and Frank at back, and come down, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Thank you. Sir Lionel. My cousin and Mr. Everard Digby.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="42"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Confound these fellows, they seem to be ubiquitous.
Yes, it is a very beautiful specimen of the genus, indeed.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Oh! that is to imply that I have been showing it him,
and asking his opinion; but you shant get off so. Sir Baronet. Look, Mr. Digby,
at this rare camelia japonica, which Sir Lionel has just presented to me; is it
not beautiful?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>It may; I have not much taste in these matters, but it seems to me common
enough. <stage>(goes up and seats himself, R.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> That is because you look at it through green
spectacles. So much the better. What think you, Mr. Hawthorne, of Sir Lionel’s
camelia?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>It is very pretty, but Sir Lionel is mistaken, it is not a camelia, it is a
new and elegant variety of the common pansy, vulgarly termed, “two faces under a
hood;” <stage>(aside)</stage> and the most appropriate present, as the most
emblematical of himself that he could make. <stage>(goes up and sits,
L.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> As I am not a gardener, professional or amateur, I may be
excused the mistake. Miss Wildbriar, I salute you for the present.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exit, R. 4 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> She was flirting with him, and he with her. Oh, woman,
woman! always caught by the tinkling sound of a title. I cannot hide my anger,
and yet I cannot be rude to her. I shall go.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> Surely you are not going, Mr. Everard, soon as you have
come?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>I came to look for Miss Vavasour, I was told that she was here, or at least
in the shrubberies. Excuse me; I have some business to communicate.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exit, R. 3 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> He is jealous—jealous unto vexation, and is gone to
meditate revenges—deep revenges! Delightful! he’ll soon come back to my feet—my
very feet—and beg me to put the chain around his neck, and then for the
solution, and a sly laugh at sly Sir Lionel. Bravo! clever little girl.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises, L.)</stage> Miss Wildbriar, or rather let me call you cousin,
as I would be privileged to speak seriously.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>My dear cousin, I shall be most happy to listen, for I’m in excellent
spirits, and almost need a sermon to keep me from laughing.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(comes down, L.)</stage> Because you have just given pain to a sincere
admirer, by flirting with an affected one. Cousin of mine, that is not the pulse
of the honest, unsophisticated heart of girlhood, as it should beat in the
breast of an English farmer’s daughter. It is the tricksy, inconstant setting of
the artificial woman’s, met with but in Vanity Fair, and whose <pb n="43"/>
nominal heart is just as substitutive for the one she has lost, as her false
locks or her false teeth are for those she has shed.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>That’s very harsh.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>It is true. We are out of our place here, let us not lose here the virtues,
the absence of which would make us out of our place at home.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Cousin, you are a very superior man, but you will allow that another member
of the family may be clever too—not to the same extent, for you’re a great man,
and I’m only a little girl, but on certain subjects clever little girls are just
as wise as great men; and now let me give you a bit of advice, not in the way of
retort, but out of a cousin’s regard and a woman’s respect for your good heart
and your great talents, which she does not like to see subjected to the double
grief of insult and disappointment.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I guess—I guess; but go on—I listen.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>You are more out of your place here than I am. You love Miss Vavasour, and by
the tenor of the will, despite your low birth, you are authorized to seek a
return of your affection. That is hopeless. She was all but pledged previously
to Sir Lionel Norman. She would have refused you at once, but was over persuaded
by her mother and friends to wait the issue. She has been further persuaded to
play a part likely to offend or provoke you (as your admiration has been
apparent), in the hope that you would decline, and so dower her with the
fortune. If she should be induced, as by Sir Lionel’s doubtful conduct and her
mother’s persuasion she may, to accept you, it will be for the money, and not
love, nor even liking. <stage>(Frank goes up L.)</stage> Forgive me, for I see
this pains you deeply; but I believe that you would rather know the truth, for
all the pain of the moment, than be the dupe for life.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> You have read me rightly, and I thank you; yes, I thank
you from my—my heart. My heart! no, no—not from my heart—my slavish, bruised, my
coward craven heart, that cries out beneath the lash, and weeps upon its wound,
but from my soul;—the man’s soul that rises up within to put its heel upon that
heart, and crush it out if it should groan again. <stage>(crosses to R., then
back to L.)</stage> I thank you, all is well. I understand the comedy. ’Tis
well—’tis well; we’ll play it out, but with a change of parts. <stage>(sits,
L.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> I am almost sorry now that I have cautioned him. He has
bit his lip until the blood has started; but he has a great soul, and the strife
fought out ’twill gain the mastery. That’s the way we English win our battles,
little people as we are. Oh! here comes a goodly assemblage.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="44"/>
<stage>Enter Sir Lionel Norman and Miss Vavasour, R., Hon. Augustus Adolphus and
Mrs. Wildbriar, L., Everard Digby, Mrs. Vavasour, and Dr. Playfair, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Ah, here’s a bonny place, and seats too; that’s right; for I’m right down
tired, and want to rest mysen. <stage>(sits down)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Yes, this, of all places in the grounds, is my treasure trove—my sanctuary.
Heyday, ’tis already occupied. Mr. Hawthorne and Miss Wildbriar
<hi>tête-à-tête</hi>. Faun and wood-nymph. Oh! it is my turn to be jealous
now.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Thou hast no need, lass—second cousins can’t marry—first may.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, indeed—a consolatory regulation.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> To be found only in a Lancashire rubric, I should
say.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> He doesn’t speak; my play begins to tell. I’m glad of it,
for I tire; and I don’t want to earn his contempt, as well as his dislike.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> I should object if you did; <stage>(aside)</stage> but
I’m afraid you have.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> This place must ha’ cost a deal o’ money.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Yes; it was arranged under my direction—all the shrubs and flowers are rare
exotics—not more beautiful than some native to our gardens; but then the price
gives them an additional value.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated, R.)</stage> I object to that; in my mind, it takes away from
the value.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated, L.)</stage> That’s the only sensible word you’ve spoken
to-day, old man. I always think more of a thing the cheaper I get it, when it’s
a bargain.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that; I don’t believe that you are any such exception to the
general rule of your sex.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>I don’t care what you think; I tell you it is so.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated, R.)</stage> Dr. Playfair—a word—you spoil my play; you must,
for once, get off your hobby-horse, and leave all the objections to Mr.
Hawthorne. <stage>(aside)</stage> Oh, for my part, I value most things by their
price. I like extravagance, and think in dress, flowers, bijoutry, it is a
woman’s privilege. Don’t you admit that, Mr. Hawthorne?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>No.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Sir L. Adol. Mrs. Vavasour. Mrs. Wildbriar. Lucy. Everard. Jenny. Dr. P.
Frank. L.</stage>
<pb n="45"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(coming down, L. C.)</stage> Only no! I should like to have a reason
for that no.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Indeed! Well, as it may add to your limited stock of
ideas, I shall give you one.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Sir!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises)</stage> Oh, you object to drawing-room badinage in the open
air, do you?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Ha, ha!—the retort courteous. Adolphus, you must accept
it good-humouredly.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes; but nothing vexes me so much, as being accused of a paucity of
wit.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> As the conscious insolvent is always most indignant at
the suspicion of poverty. <stage>(takes stage and back to situation)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated, R.)</stage> Ha, ha, ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Not bad—yield him the honours, Adolphus—the Dacian is only learning to fence,
and handles his foil like a club. <stage>(they go up, R.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(overhearing, aside)</stage> Does he? You had best mind your fence, or
it may tap at your ribs before long.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>We still lack enlightenment, Mr. Hawthorne: your reason against
extravagance—woman’s pet privilege.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> Extravagance is a waste, a vice, and a vice cannot be the
privilege of either sex, much less of the weaker and more delicately organized.
Over indulgence of any desire—intemperance—a riotous, inconsiderate waste of
money in the gratification of any passion—the antetype of excellence, cannot be
any part of refinement of taste. It is a debauchery.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated)</stage> Oh, really this language is too bad.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>It’s insufferable!—offensive in the extreme!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises)</stage> You have indeed made use of a shocking word, Mr.
Hawthorne;—it wounds the ear.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I am glad of it; but the habit of extravagance is much worse—more vicious
than the word—more hideous behind any mask it may assume; it vitiates and leaves
a gangrene—a slime upon the soul.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Truth—truth! I can’t object to that.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>But I do; for it’s a very disagreeable doctrine. Our little elegancies of
costume—our delicate devices of ornament for boudoir or bower—as they improve
our appearance, and shed light and fragrance on our journey through life, lift
us above the level of the mere sensual wayfarers, and repay the expenditure.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(looking at her)</stage> Sensuous; if not sensual. <stage>(retires to
his seat, L.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>That arrow sped; the bear has retired to his den to grumble over his
discomfiture.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I shall make him come forth again, and speedily. <pb n="46"/>Do you go and
talk to Sir Lionel. He’s looking the other way—<stage>(rising, and crossing to
shrub opposite)</stage> How beautifully this magnolia blossoms. I must have a
sprig—<stage>(plucks one, and then in returning to seat, deliberately throws
handkerchief down)</stage> Mr. Hawthorne—Mr. Hawthorne, you are remiss.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Indeed, on what account?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Sir, do you not see my handkerchief?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Oh, you wish it to be picked up?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(who turns and hears)</stage> What a boor—permit me. <stage>(advances,
C.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no; having asked Mr. Hawthorne, I can receive it only from him.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Oh, if the gentleman can acquire a merit in the performance of the office of
a lacquey, by all means let him. It is a service I should never volunteer.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Indeed! may I ask why?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Because I could not suppose you to be so foolish as to throw your
handkerchief down, for the mere purpose of having it picked up again.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Throw it down?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>You certainly did. I saw you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> So, he was watching me, for all his pretended
indifference. I confess it. I was anxious to test the difference in the
politeness of certain gentlemen, and I have succeeded. <stage>(goes to seat—Sir
Lionel picks up handkerchief, and presents it to Lucy)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I am glad of it; it has, doubtless, enabled you to distinguish the man from
the fopling.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Sir, you are personal.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises, L.)</stage> Mere drawing-room badinage; and you must make
allowance for the Dacian, who is only learning to fence, and handles his foil
like a club.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.C.)</stage> Ha! ha! the retort courteous; you must accept it
good-humouredly, Sir Lionel.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Yes; but hang it—a fopling!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I admit your objection to be classed with the mere neophytes and tadpoles,
such as your friend; and will acknowledge you to be a master in the craft—a B.A.
of the foppish <hi>beau-monde</hi>. <stage>(goes up, L. C.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I can’t object to anything this fellow says. I shall be obliged to avoid his
company, or I shall lose the only pleasurable excitement that life affords me.
<stage>(seated)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> He’s rather a clever fellow.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>He’s a d—d deal too clever; and I rather suspect that he has seen through our
game from the first. <stage>(goes to ladies, R.)</stage></p>
</sp>
<pb n="47"/>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>If so, how he must despise me—with what a sense of superiority he must look
down upon this petty device.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Bravo, cousin; he begins to understand the game, and to play it well.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p><stage>(without)</stage> Mother—where’s my mother?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Here, Rob. Eh! now I shall have some one to speak English to me, and needn’t
sit mumchance any more. I haven’t understood a word that has been spoken here
for the last half hour. What does thee want, lad?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Eh! all the nobs here—and Jenny, too—to frighten the thoughts out of my head,
whenever I open my mouth, with her winks and nods? Mother, I mun speak in
private wi’ you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>No, lad; speak up—whispering ain’t good behaviour in dacent company. What’s
got to say?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>What’s o’clock? my watch has gone down; but I know by my stomach that it must
be near mealtime, and them dumplings mun be done.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(up L. C.)</stage> No, lad, no; they’re big and hard, and take a deal
of boiling. Eh! the damp grass has brought my rheumatiz on again—help me up,
lad.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(crosses to her)</stage> Allow me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>No; I dunnot want thee now. I’ve got my lad, Robin. Get off wi’ ye.
<stage>(Adolphus crosses back)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(comes down)</stage> Where’s thy lass, lad?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.C.)</stage> Eh! she’s gone home by hersen’—she wouldn’t come
here—she’s sheamfaced, I suppose, by reason of these chaps laughing at her.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Corydon without his Phillis. Ha! ha!—Mrs. Vavasour, the gentle Euphemia has
proved susceptible, and made a conquest, too, at last.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>What mean you?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated, R.)</stage> Behold the Adonis who has charmed that hitherto
marble heart.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Adonis!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>What’s he calling me names for?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(coming down, R. C.)</stage> Cymon—Cymon, you mean—the veritable
Cymon—“the clown who never dreamt of love,” and “whistled as he went for want of
thought,”—chancing at last upon his destined Iphigenia here, is about to undergo
the wondrous transformation which love alone achieves on clowns.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> True; whilst the ductile nature of a gentleman,
self-interest, sways at will, without apparent change, to jeer the clown, and
woo his mother.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Woo the mother, eh?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>What's that, Adolphus?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Oh! nothing. Some more badinage, which of course I must
take good-humouredly. <stage>(aside)</stage> Damn his quick perception! he is
Argus-eyed. <stage>(goes up, R., to Ladies)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(coming down, L. C.)</stage> Robin, lad! How ist thee?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Eh! you can speak Lancashire English?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Yes, lad, and I needn’t be ashamed, for it’s getting into great favor in this
quarter. Which is to take place first, thy mother’s wedding, or thy own?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>My mother’s? Haw! haw! haw! She’s none going to make such a fou of
hersen.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I don’t know that. There’s a gentleman here so much attached to you and
yours, that he’s anxious to become thy stepfeyther.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(comes down, R.—aside to Frank)</stage> Sir! sir!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Badinage! badinage! take it good-humouredly.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>A gentleman! No—eh! Shan’t I have such a laugh at mother. Which be he?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Oh! Of course the gentleman who accompanies her in her morning walks, and who
just now was so desirous to save you the trouble of helping her from her
chair.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>What, that whipper-snapper? What, that chap with the Billy-goat beard? Haw!
haw! haw! <stage>(Frank goes up)</stage> He, my feyther! Mother! mother! thee
ain’t a going to make a fou of thysen, and get married again, art thee, and set
all the neighbours laughing at thee!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Noa, lad. What’s put that in thy head.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Because that chap yonder is making-up to thee.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>It’s nought o’ sort!—it’s nought o’ sort!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>He wants to be my feyther. Haw! haw! haw! What a feyther he’d be!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Get along wi’ you. If I thought he wur, I’d box his ears.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>It’s for sure. What does he go a walking wi’ you for, and a sniggling up to
thee, and offering his arm? It’s thy money he wants, and not thee, woman.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! if I was sure he meant it, I’d break his head.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I shouldn’t object to that.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>How dare he think a woman of my time of life would have the loikes of him, a
laced-up dandy, wi’ a waist as small as my Jenny’s? Eh! if I wanted a husband,
which, Heaven be thanked, I dunnot, it’s summut of a man to look at I’d have,
and not a hop-o’-my-thumb skipjack. He’d better not come near me agin, or I’ll
slap his face.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> Do as you used to do to me, mother, lug and pow his hair,
and it will be sure to come off, for I know it’s a wig. Haw! haw! haw!</p>
</sp>
<pb n="50"/>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> I’ll cuff thee if thee laughs when I’m in a passion.
Didst thee mean it, man—did’st thee mean it? <stage>(rushing up to
Adolphus)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>No, no; I assure you, on my honor, it’s all a mistake.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that; I believe he meant it, on my soul.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> A mistake! well, I hope it is. You mun excuse me, ladies,
for getting in such a passion, and making so much noise, but the idea of his
making up to me! He might as well to you, Mrs., and you’re older than me by long
chalks.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R., seated)</stage> Oh, dear no! Was there ever such a vulgar
woman?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Oh! well, if it’s displeasing to you, never mind; but it’s plain to be seen,
for all that. I always speaks my mind.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>That’s right, mother; so do I! no double fence about straight-forward
Lancashire folk.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exeunt Mrs. Wildbriar and Robin, L. C.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated)</stage> Some merit in their candour.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated)</stage> It would be none the worse if graced by a little
courtesy.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(comes down, C.)</stage> True; but courtesy ceases to be a grace, when
used as a cloak to deception.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises, R. C.)</stage> The emphasis of your remark seems to level it
at me, sir, but I am not pregnable to the point.</p>
</sp>

<stage>(Lucy advances, R., Jenny, L.)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Achilles upright in his armour, but mine is only club wit, and boasts no
point at all; and yet, abroad in the Woodlands, I thought your Arcadian reveries
might have suggested a supposititious Endymion, who, in the chase of a Diana,
had marked down a Hebe among the satyrs, as a prize positive, if the superlative
divinity should escape.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Sir, this inference is impertinent.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>What, you bleed? But I forgot when Achilles knelt at Hymen’s shrine, he laid
aside his armour, and proved vulnerable in heel as well as heart.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Sir, I—I—damnation. <stage>(crosses to L.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> Why, I vow he’s angry; my dear fellow, if you can’t
lightly give and take, or endure the privileged sarcasms—the badinage of drawing
room society—you had really better not venture within its pale. <stage>(goes up,
R.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(comes down, R.)</stage> Ha! ha! fairly foiled, Sir Lionel; don’t be
angry. I am most undeservedly complimented by the comparison, and feel honoured
in being accounted first prize by the refined taste, whose second may so fairly
claim the soubriquet of Hebe. Miss Wildbriar—I mean my dear Hebe— will you
stroll with me, and be Diana’s nymph for the nonce? Dr. Playfair, give your arm
to mamma, and lead her to the house. <stage>(crosses to C.)</stage></p>
</sp>
<pb n="50"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside—rises, R.)</stage> I should like to object to that, but
courtesy forbids.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Gentlemen, adieu! don’t follow, or beware the fate of Actaeon. Mr. Hawthorne,
we shall meet, I hope, at dinner.</p>
</sp>

<stage>(curtsies—he bows—Lucy and Jenny exeunt at back, C.— Dr. Playfair and
Mrs. Vavasour, L.)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>You have fairly avenged yourself.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> No; I have but vindicated a man from the assumption of
a clique.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> He shall apologise, by heaven; he shall instantly, and
before Digby.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Should he refuse?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Refuse—refuse; he shall not—he dare not, for the
consequences. Mr. Hawthorne, you have been rude to insolence; had you been the
clown you were supposed, I should have treated it with contempt. I pay you the
compliment of admitting your intelligence and equality, by demanding an instant
apology.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> I do not appreciate the compliment. Had you been the
gentleman you assume to be, you never would have committed the error of
premising that a stranger, however diffident, and humbly born, must of necessity
be a clown. I treated that insolence with silent contempt, until it became the
assailant. I have made use of its own weapons to retort, and I shall certainly
not apologise, because in the contest you began I happen to have so far
succeeded as to have ruffled your equanimity.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>You have taken an unfair advantage in the repetition of words not intended
for your ear.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>You meant to take an unfair advantage in assailing the barbarian, as he was
deemed, with the weapons of your supposed superior civilization.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>To end this, sir, I demand an apology.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Which I decline to make.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>I thought so.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Then, sir, you compel me to waive all further courtesy of consideration, and
to seek the satisfaction usual amongst gentlemen.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>A duel? I thought that had become unusual amongst gentlemen; but I forgot,
you would rather type one of the actual paladins of the past age, than be the
representative of their spirit in the present. How if I refuse?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>I shall feel authorised to speak of you in public as an insolent, and a
coward.</p>
</sp>

<stage>(Lucy and Jenny pass to and fro at back)</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>A disagreeable alternative enough, although a man of sense might hope to live
it down. Let me see; I heard you boast the other day that you were a capital
pistol shot.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="51"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>As you may be.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I am not good enough to make it a boast.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(half aside)</stage> So much the better.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>The assassin-like sentiment of your friend, Sir Lionel, I will suppose you
are too lineal a descendant of our chivalric conquerors to echo.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Confound his quick ear.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>You said, at the same time, that although you had been a pupil of Angelo’s,
from your disinclination to enlarge or afflict with ridges your
characteristically small hand, you had never practised with the broadsword;
neither have I, and my hand, by some extraordinary freak of nature, is as small
as yours. The only shadow of a grace that can belong to a duel, is that which
makes the chances equal between the belligerents. Suppose we send for a couple
of Andrew Ferraras,<note type="ed"
>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Ferrara</note> and like doughty knights of
old, cross blades, cry havoc, and lay on.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Sir, the proposal, if seriously meant, hath an air of complete savagery. It
would sink us at once to the level of mere barbarians. No, sir, to that I cannot
consent.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>But you would level your pistol at my body, in the confidence of a skill
certain to send a bullet through heart or brain. The savagery is worse, because
more cold-blooded and assassin-like. <stage>(crosses to L.)</stage> Pshaw!
appoint your time and place,—bring your pistols. <stage>(crosses to C.)</stage>
I shall prove as good a shot as you: I fear not the skill that shrinks from an
encounter with an unexpected danger: ’twill lack both physical and moral
self-possession in the trial.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Enough, sir. To-morrow, at sunrise, beyond—</p>
</sp>

<stage>Re-enter Lucy and Jenny.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(C.)</stage> No, no; this must not be, for my sake. I entreat—I
implore—I command! <stage>(to Sir Lionel)</stage> Were you to kill him, I should
hate you. <stage>(to Frank)</stage> Were your hand to be stained with his blood,
it—it would break my heart.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> True, and in either case, you could hardly become his
wife. Well, well, I can risk all chance of cowardice to play the true gentleman.
I own to having taken a somewhat unfair liberty with words lightly uttered, no
doubt, in jest, and not meant to reach my ear, and for that I beg to offer an
apology to Sir Lionel.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Which he most readily accepts.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(sinking on her knees to Frank)</stage> Bless you! Bless you!</p>
</sp>

<stage>Jenny. Adolphus. Sir Lionel. Lucy. Frank. Everard.</stage>

<trailer>END OF ACT II.</trailer>
</div>
</div>
<note>Another lapse of three months is supposed to have occurred.</note>
<pb n="52"/>
<div type="act" n="3">
<head>ACT III.</head>

<stage>Scene.—Same as in Act I.</stage>
<stage>Frank discovered, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>The last day of doubt has passed; within an hour or two must hesitation
cease, and yet she gives no sign. True, since the day on which I was surprised
into a betrayal of my feelings, and then goaded into a retort of her friends’
scorn, her manner has changed. It is now deferential and observant, at times
hesitating and nervous, as still doubtful of the result. Hopeless of inducing me
to recede, and persuaded by her mother and her friends that it were better to
sacrifice her feelings than the fortune, she accepts me as a fate, and is
endeavouring before marriage to accommodate her manners unto mine; a submissive
baseness of soul, of which I did not think she could have been guilty. I wish
that she had kept up the mask—the play; it was finesse, but still warfare, and I
could have carried into solitude a reverence for the idol of my dream, though
that idol had not listened to my prayer.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Dr. Playfair, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Alone, and soliloquising? I object to that upon your wedding day.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>My wedding day?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Yes;—if by twelve o’clock you are not married, the fortune either goes to the
lady, or comes to you, or is locked up in trust for an indefinite number of
unknown brats. I object to that, and to the principle of Chartered Charity
Schools in general: their endowments—particularly if they increase in
value—always become objects of peculation to trustees and governors, and in the
end the greater portion is subverted from the original purpose of the
investments; schools turned into close boroughs, that there’s no poking any
little snub-nose into without some great influence, like a hydraulic ram at his
back;—mostly used for rich men’s illegitimates, keeping fatheaded deacons in
greasy sinecures, and a few unfortunate boys in a fantastic dress, that makes
them ashamed of themselves for the rest of their lives.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Ha, ha! very true. Such has often been the issue of
charitable bequests; but rest assured the Hawthorne property will not be
disposed of in that manner.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Glad of it—was sure of it;—wrote to Cunningham that all
was right, and have been over to the Bishopric myself, and obtained a special
license for the marriage of Francis Hawthorne and Lucy Vavasour, in the little
parish church that neighbours the entrance to the park of the Woodlands.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>That was premature; our formal consent to an <pb n="53"/>union should have
preceded, and would have sufficed for the present.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Your formal consent goes for nothing without the marriage, as the will is
worded: thought of that; and as you are the only man to whom I don’t object,
resolved to look after your interest in time.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, I thank you, and it matters but little.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>You speak lightly, and I object to that upon so important a subject. You
surely can’t be careless about your wife; you did admire, respect—did love her;
must so still.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Yes; no.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object emphatically to such a contradictory reply. People should know their
own minds.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Doctor, I have faith in you. Your very eccentricity, if a
little gnarled, is still a natural growth. There is no need with you to exact a
promise—to set the seal of silence upon a confidence.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Well, I don’t object to that.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I will confess to you that I did love, and still could love, Lucy—Miss
Vavasour; that I did admire, respect, even when most consciously the object of
her scorn; but that now I cannot give my esteem, nay, have some difficulty in
withholding my contempt, from the woman who seems base enough to give her heart
to a title, and yet sell her person for wealth.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> I object to an argument founded like yours on assumption.
Lucy’s not so bad; accustomed all her life to wealth, she must look upon it as a
necessity.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R., sighs)</stage> True.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> She has seen so many sacrifices of feeling made for its
preservation or acquirement, thinks it not a crime, but a custom; then it is so
mixed up, or rather baited with sentimental lures, tacked cleverly on by
affected willing victims, and humbugging old mothers—bleeding hearts, sleepless
nights, pearly tears, bliss of secret agony, romance of a strife between duty
and inclination, no wonder a young girl, not quite sure of her own mind, should
rather prefer to be a victim than otherwise.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Doctor, doctor, this is special pleading. The cant of the nursery, or of the
boudoir, should neither find utterance on the man’s lips, nor echo in the
woman’s heart. No, no; romance may heighten, beautify with its tinted light the
sacrifices made for truth’s sake, even as the hues of the stained window serve
to enrich the twilight atmosphere of the cloister, or to soften the sunbeam on
the cenotaph; but you must not take it into the service of self-interest, or
make it pander to the legalization of vice, and hope to preserve its loveliness,
or to make its charms a plea for sinning. Romance risks poverty, adventures
peril, to wed hands with hearts, even as natural alliances are made among the
simplest, least sophisticated, and <pb n="54"/>so most civilised of the
civilised races of men; and, wanting the grand element of a natural instinct, no
romance is worth the telling or the hearing, how much less, then, the acting?
<stage>(crosses to L.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Can’t object to that; he always gets the better of me in an argument.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>But dismiss your fears on my account; with moderate desires I can live, even
without the annuity accruing to me, should I refuse a joint share in this
princely inheritance.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> But you are not going to refuse? I object to that. You
owe it to your uncle’s and father’s memory to keep it in the name of
Hawthorne.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>My dear doctor, what I shall do as yet, short as is the time, is a secret to
myself. The sequel you will know almost as soon as I shall. <stage>(Doctor goes
up R.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Sir Lionel Norman, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Gentlemen, good day. Mr. Hawthorne, if you are not particularly engaged, I
should feel obliged by a few minutes’ private conversation.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Certainly, if Dr. Playfair will give me leave.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Oh! I don’t object to that. <stage>(aside)</stage> Never shall, to get out of
that over-refined gentleman’s company.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exit, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(L.)</stage> Now, Sir Lionel, I am at your service.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Mr. Hawthorne, I must beg your allowance of the liberty I
am about to take, which courtesy, even under peculiar circumstances, can alone
excuse. I come to speak upon a very delicate subject, and one that requires the
nicest treatment. In fact, the suggestion I am about to make could only be
volunteered from one gentleman to another. <stage>(Frank bows)</stage> It is,
that you will not force upon Miss Vavasour the marriage prescribed by the
will.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Delicate with a vengeance. I do not. She is at liberty
to refuse me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes; but not without an enormous sacrifice of wealth.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Which enormous sacrifice she has sent you to suggest that I should make?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no; she is not aware that I have interfered in the matter.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Then why do you?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Why out of consideration for her, as she does not love you—In fact—ahem!—may
be presumed to have long loved another.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>What a delicate gentleman! <stage>(aside)</stage> She has said as much?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>No, not exactly; but it is an inference—a fact to be implied from the whole
tenor of her conduct.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Indeed! I had thought, Sir Lionel, that the sacrifice <pb n="55"/>she is
expected to make—I mean, of course, not of wealth, but of feeling—affection, was
not unusual in fashionable life.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Well, neither is it; but as you are a new man, and seem to have stricter
principles in these matters, I thought your early prejudices in favour of the
opposite kind of sacrifice might induce you—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>To make myself the victim, and enable Miss Vavasour to become Lady Norman,
and Sir Lionel Norman lord of the Woodlands! Upon my word, Baronet, you
compliment me so highly by your generous and chivalric opinion, that I should be
only too happy to oblige you. But, pray why did not this suggestion come from
Mrs. Vavasour, who must have her daughter’s confidence in the matter.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Oh, because she did not think you likely to be persuaded; and, believing that
the marriage must take place, she was fearful it might prejudice her daughter’s
future peace of mind, should it provoke your anger.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Oh, she does not hold so high an opinion of me as you do. I am again your
debtor, Sir Lionel, but at present can hold out no hope of compliance with this
particular request. It is too late; wants but an hour or so of the appointed
time. Egad, I must go and dress. You will be present at the ceremony, of
course?</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exit, L. 2 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Um! I gave him credit for more high principle: the mercantile spirit of the
age has depraved even the scholar and the puritan.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Exit into library, L.</stage>
<stage>Enter Lucy, with scroll of music paper, and Jenny, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>And are you sure—quite sure—that Mr. Hawthorne is the author of these
words?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Am I sure? Am I a clever little girl?—Listen and judge. Yesterday, passing
one of the rooms upon our side— the Montague side of the mansion—I caught the
sounds of a piano; I entered, and found my cousin Romeo, I mean Frank, playing
from a new score, and humming, rather than singing, the words. He was confused,
apologised for having remained, and when I enquired his theme, said it was an
old strain he had been endeavouring to arrange to some new words, but as the
work was imperfect, he declined to submit it to my judgment. In his confusion,
and the haste of his exit, he did not notice that on the table he had left a
copy—the first, I should presume, from the erasures. I found it, liked, and
thought it expressed a feeling that you ought to know.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Is he not yet conscious of its being in your possession?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>I don’t know—I have not seen him since; he is very sensitive, and if he has
discovered its loss, would rather slight <pb n="56"/>its importance, by not
seeming to care about it, than suggest its having been the echo of a real
feeling by an enquiry.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Yes ; that is in keeping with his character.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>(r.) Oh ! you have taken some notes of that. Have I guessed rightly in
believing that you have learned at last to feel a little interest about this
self-willed cousin of mine?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>The peculiarities of his character are too apparent to escape notice, even
had not the relation in which we stand compelled some observance.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>That is said in the very spirit of a grand lady ; but the grand lady has a
heart in her bosom, as well as the little girl; and yours, which I am sure has
not been vitiated, must be susceptible of a nearer interest than can possibly
belong to mere observance about the character of your future husband.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>(l.) My future husband—who knows ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>(r.) Love ever suggests liking in return, and he loves you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Nonsense, child. He dreamt of an Egeria,—an ideal mistress—but, looking on
the idol, found it false-—very dross and clay. Love me !—he makes no effort to
win my love—he moves, speaks, and thinks, independently of all reference to me.
No, no ; he accepts me as his destiny—hopeful, perhaps, that at the last moment
I may refuse. It is but a fair retort; I did the same, and earned his contempt,
and my own, too. {<stage>(seats herself at L. table)</stage>} I know that, but
he shouldn't show it so plainly—wouldn't, if he had a spark of love. Pretty
wooing.</p>
<p>Jenny, <stage>(aside)</stage> It is excellent. I believe that he has acted in
the very best way to win your love ; his instinct is almost as shrewd as my
skill, clever as I know myself, <stage>(to Lucy)</stage> And, so you don't love
him? It's a sad fate to look forward to, and you might have been so happy with
half the fortune, and Sir Lionel Norman.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Sir Lionel?—-perhaps.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>You can sing at sight; I wish you'd just try over that song for me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>No, no; I—I couldn't.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Do, do; see, here is a piano; let me accompany you; it's very pretty; just
listen, <stage>(plays symphony)</stage> Pray, try the words over.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>No, no. Pshaw—it's very childish.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Then please give it back to me, as you don't like it, and I do.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Take it; and yet I—I should like to copy the words. {<stage>(rises)</stage>}
No, the music, I mean ; it seems to be a quaint old style of air, but prettily
arranged. I shall restore the original in the course of the day.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>{<stage>(aside)</stage>} If you do I shall become a nun, which I am too
clever a little girl, and know my vocation too well, ever to <pb n="57"
/>meditate. I shall be in attendance as your bridesmaid before the ceremony
takes place; at present mamma may want me.</p>
<stage>Exit, R.1 E.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>The ceremony—will it ever take place ? And are these his real sentiments, or
is it a mere poetical fancy ? There is an air of truth in the very simplicity of
the words ; they are not brain wrought, but heart sung : should I reject him,
'twere noble; but then, how to convince him of my motive, <stage>(crosses to R.
table)</stage> Love should cling unto the faintest hope. Let me try to sing this
song ; it may reveal, as music often does, the true pulse of my heart,
<stage>(seats herself at piano—plays and sings)</stage>
<lg>
<head>Song.</head>

<l>Though beauteously blossoms the myrtle tree, </l>
<l>And the laurel a nobler shrub may be, </l>
<l>Oh ! the willow's the plant that most likes me, </l>
<l>For in spite of thy scorn I still love thee,</l>
<l>Aye, more than thy bridegroom, whoe'er he may be ; </l>
<l>Sing hey! ho ! willow—green willow for me.</l>
<l>Come, kiss me, despair, and new life impart,</l>
<l>Take mine, and to me give thy bold, brave heart,</l>
<l> To endure, not deny, the deep, deep pain,</l>
<l> And yet anger none at her high disdain;</l>
<l>For love unto pride can a true love be;</l>
<l>Sing, hey ! ho ! willow—green willow for me.</l>
<l>Though one glance of love from thy glorious eyes </l>
<l>Far richer made me than the wealth you prize, </l>
<l>Twere better from thee in thy scorn to part, </l>
<l>Than to win one false smile, and abase thy heart;</l>
<l>Oh! no: in thy pride I can still love thee ;</l>
<l>Sing, hey! ho ! willow—green willow for me.</l>
</lg><stage>(at end bursts into tears; rises, and crosses to L., then back to
R.)</stage> Weeping ? fool! I care neither for him nor for his money ; let him
keep it; I don't want it. Pshaw! he contemns me—can't love. Shall I stoop to woo
his respect ? Never !</p>
</sp>
<stage> Enter Sir Lionel Norman, L. 3 E.</stage>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Pardon, Miss Vavasour, if that I intrude. I have been speaking seriously to
your mother, and the result is a desire to do my duty honourably by you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Sir Lionel, one word first. I have not the remotest claim upon your
consideration or duty, and perhaps this assurance will spare you further
avowal.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>{<stage>(aside)</stage>} Strange !—can't mean it; angry because I have not
spoken before. Pardon me; I may have seemed absent, cold of late.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="58"/>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I have not noticed it, and fully pardon that which gave me no concern.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside, L.)</stage> Still wrath? Well, Miss Vavasour, I rejoice to
hear you say this, because you will have less difficulty in accomplishing the
painful but necessary sacrifice of feeling you are required to make.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>What sacrifice ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>That of your feelings to your interest.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>What feelings?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage>} She wants an eclaireissement in the hope of evoking
the spirit of the past, and inducing us both to make fools of ourselves.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>You do not reply.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>It is useless to particularise feelings that must of necessity be laid aside,
and buried with the past.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> I really don't understand you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> Well, then, Miss Vavasour, it is my duty honourably to
inform you, that much as I esteem, truly as I admire, have loved, and still love
you, were you to resign this fortune out of regard to the past, it would not be
in my power to atone in some part for the sacrifice; and therefore, in a spirit
of self-abnegation, I set you free. I advise you— </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>To marry another man, whom you think I do not like ; and yet you talk of
respecting—loving me in the same breath. Oh, shame ! Oh, Chivalry, thou hast
indeed fled the earth, and Mammon has established his empire over the heart of
youth itself, in peer and peasant, <stage>(crosses to R. corner)</stage>
</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Pardon me, it is not for myself I speak, it is from a consideration of your
welfare.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Which you think more likely to be assured by a fortune than by your love.
That is probable ; but I will give you more credit than you do yourself, Sir
Lionel: your advice commits no outrage upon the character of your love, which
could not co-exist in the same breast with the feelings that prompted your
honourable consideration for my welfare. You never loved me, nor I you, of that
I have been long convinced : we moved in the same society, went to the same
balls, danced in the same set of quadrilles, applauded the same operas, and
being equally young and heartless, thought we were a pair, but we were not; and
this act, which completes, or rather establishes, the fact of our severance,
does not cost the slightest pang to either.— Good day, sir. <stage>Exit,
R.</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(C.)</stage> Mere spleen and vexation. I expected an explosion. Poor
thing, she'll go and cry now. I'm sorry for her —sorry to have lost her, for I
really liked her; but the man who has the dignity of a baronet to sustain upon a
mortgaged estate, and who marries a poor lady, is little less than a scoundrel:
because, if he should have children, they must not work, and <pb n="59"/> they
must live, so he becomes the father of a race of genteel sharpers—otherwise
fortune hunters.</p>
<stage> Enter Jenny, R. 1 E.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Sir Lionel, I am fortunate in finding you, as from your professed friendship,
I am sure of your advice on what is to me a very important subject.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Miss Wildbriar, I am most honoured by your confidence. Command every service
in my power to render you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>You have so often noticed me, and always with so much kindness, that not
having any one in my own family who is familiar with high life, or capable of
advising me, I thought of you the moment I was asked to become a
marchioness.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>A marchioness!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Yes; and I said to myself, Sir Lionel, who is the very pattern of high life,
the beau ideal of a fine gentleman, can best tell me whether or not I ought to
accept this offer— whether I could hope to move in the fashionable world without
provoking a question as to my birth and breeding.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> Upon that subject, let me, my dear Miss Wildbriar, give you
the best proof of my most favourable opinion, by myself soliciting the honour
and happiness of your alliance.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>You, Sir Lionel—you—why, I always thought you were in love with Miss
Vavasour.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Miss Wildbriar, I shall be candid with you, and own that for a long time I
was devoted to that lady—was indeed— until your star rose over the horizon, and
drew the eye of my affection after it; doubtless with more ease, because the
terms of the will made it a duty, upon my part, to avert my thoughts from Miss
Vavasour.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh, dear me ! I wish I had known this sooner; for as a baronet is not so high
up as a marquis, I think I should not be so likely to lose my self-command and
stumble ; and the worst of it is, I have given my promise.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Promise ! This is really too bad, Miss Wildbriar. Why come to ask my advice
as to what you should do, when you have already decided your fate?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p><stage>(R.)</stage> Isn't that what people always do? But don't be angry;
mine was not a formal promise, it was only the half consent, that not saying "
no," with women, particularly young women is, it is mostly taken for an
affirmative, but they can always deny having said "yes" afterwards, if
necessary. And are you really serious, Sir Lionel, in—in your proposal ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Miss Wildbriar, I should else be worse than a scoundrel—a puppy !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>And you would make me mistress of that dear delightful place, Norman Abbey
?</p>
</sp>
<pb n="60"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>And of its master, too,</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R.)</stage> Well, then—oh! but I forgot, and perhaps you did. My mother
and brother—what am I to do with them ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Miss Wildbriar, as your mother and brother, I should respect them, at a
distance. I must be candid. I could not introduce them into my circle.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh! and I should never see them?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Nay, I should not object to your visiting, and passing a day or so with them
once a year.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>But they might never come to Norman Abbey ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> Certainly not, on account of the servants' remarks.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Don't you think, Sir Lionel, that all circumstances considered, it were
better for you not to risk any connection with a family you regard as likely to
bring you into discredit even with your servants ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no. The beauty and manners of Lady Norman are certain to approve Sir
Lionel Norman's taste, and the wife's individuality is merged in the husband's.
Not so with her family. I should marry you, not the others.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Not though each of them was dowered with £100,000? </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>No.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Well, Sir Lionel, your honesty has a particular merit on the part of a very
fine gentleman, and compels a like return of honest avowal upon my part. I would
not marry a marquis who was ashamed either of me or mine. From the first moment
of our acquaintance, I have seen that my mother and brother's provincialities
were subjects of scorn and of ridicule to you, and to your clique, and yet each
one of us has been tolerated and flattered in private, as the great people's
interest suggested. While making love to Miss Vavasour you coquetted with me,
and I confess that I did the like with you, for the purpose of leading you on to
this proposal, and of paying back the slights put, both covertly and openly, on
plain, but honest people whose possessions are coveted by fine, but disingenuous
gentlemen. Sir Lionel Norman, the little Lancashire farmer's daughter begs to
decline the honour of your alliance.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> In the hope of becoming a marchioness.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no: I suspected that jest the moment I heard it, and almost immediately
satisfied myself by reference to a directory, which told me there was no such
peer as the Marquis of Banterdown, but that there was a Mr. Everard Digby,
barrister.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Well, Miss Wildbriar, I am in your hands. You have gained your point; you
triumph, and I seek no mercy.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Spoken like a hero that deserves some. I am mute Sir Lionel, from this
moment, as to the past; and as I think Miss Vavasour did once like you, and may
be induced again and as my cousin is a strange man, let me advise you to keep
<pb n="61"/> your own counsel, remain here, and wait the issue; who knows, the
fortune may be yours yet.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>Thank you, my good fairy. <stage>(crosses, R.)</stage> But I cannot, with any
grace of gentlemanly feeling, meditate its acquirement now. Your servant.
<stage>Exit, R.</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Poor Sir Lionel! I think he will give over coquetry from to-day.</p>
</sp>
<stage> Enter James, L.</stage>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>She his {h}alone at last. I thought the baronite was about to {h}anticipate
me, but, from the 'igh tones in which they spoke, there can have been no
proposal. Miss Wildbriar, may I 'ave the {h}extreme 'appiness of {h}addressing a
word to you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Mr. James, is it you? Certainly. What is it? A message from Miss
Vavasour?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>No, Miss Wildbriar; it's a message from my 'art; it's a personal
communication, which you will be pleased to consider marked private and strictly
confidential.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Dear me, you surprise me ; what is its nature ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Miss Wildbriar, let me ask you, hare you {h}aware of my {h}antecedents, and
of the 'igh position I 'ave {h}ever held as a {h}upper servant in the most
recherchiest establishments in Belgravia and May Fair ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Well, no, Mr. James.</p>
<stage>Enter Mrs. Wildbriar, at back. </stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>What's Jenny talking to that flunky for? I'll listen.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Miss Wildbriar, I {h}am {h}of a particularly sensitive nature, {h}and I
meditate retiring into private life. I am proud to say not without resources. I
have an account at Coutts', and credit for three oughts with a very respectable
numeral before them.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>I am glad to hear it; your's will be a dignified retirement.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>I 'ope it will; but I 'ave all my life been accustomed to society, and I hope
to be accompanied {h}into privacy by a companion of the softer sex.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh, you are going to be married, I presume to Miss Jemima Simperton ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no ; I {h}am {h}aware that there is a softness in that quarter, but I
have had a glimpse into her bank-book, and the figure don't suit.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Then who is to be the happy woman?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> That's a home question, and brings us to the point. The
'appy woman—and 'appy she may be, as I {h}offer her my 'and, and my 'art—a werry
unusual circumstance with {h}uppers—the 'appy woman I sees before me.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="62"/>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>In your mind's eye, I presume ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>I {h}am not {h}aware that my mind has any {h}eye. No ! I sees her now with
the {h}eyes in my 'ead.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>What, me ? Oh, this is too good.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no; I don't want to make a merit of the condescension. I have but one
objection to make, that his to the other members of your family, whom I should
{h}expect you, as soon as the settlements are made, and your fortune secured
tightly, to cut altogether.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Kind and condescending, Mr. James—even more exacting than the baronet. Oh !
if mamma could only hear this. Mr. James, upon this subject I must refer you to
mamma.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p><stage>(falls on both knees)</stage> I should prefer your breaking the matter
to her first; has there is a {h}absence of sympathy between us, she might
object.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(coming forward, C.)</stage> I should think she would ; why, you
brazen-faced impudent flunky, to dare to think my daughter, wi' her edication
and a hundred thousand pounds, would demean hersen to wed wi' the loikes o'
thee. Jenny, you ought to be ashamed of yoursen to talk to him at all.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>I perceive this must be a case of Gretna Green, Miss Wildbriar, if it is to
come off at {h}all.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha ! ha !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Be off wi' you, or I'll Gretna Green thee. I shall forget mysen if thee
doesn't go, and shake all the flower out of your powdered nob.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>{H}assaults are {h}actionable.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(seated, C.)</stage> I dunnot care; I shouldn't mind payin' for the
pleasure of beatin' thee. Away wi' you, my hands are itching to serve thee
out.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L. C.)</stage> In that case I had better go.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Do, Mr. James, and preserve the dignity of an upper, in the calm
contemplation of a great mistake.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>That's very pointed; she rejects and turns me into reticule—sneers at me,
too. <stage>(sings a line or two of "Love Not," in broken voice — burlesque
style. Mrs. Wildbriar rises, comes down, and threatens him)</stage> Oh !
{h}agony !—oh ! {h}agony ! <stage>Exit, L.</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> Oh! this is delightful.—Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>For shame of thysen for laughing at, or listening to, him at all; thou ought
have boxed his ears, and thee going to wed wi' a marquis.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh, dear no, mamma; truth must out: Mr. Everard Digby is no more than a
barrister.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Aye, to be sure; that's his cognito.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Ha ! ha ! mamma, the fiction of his being a marquis <pb n="63"/>was only a
stupid jest, put upon you by Mr. Adolphus, and one to which Everard was never
privy.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! have they all been laughing at me for my mistakes. Well, they may call
themselves ladies and gentlemen, but they couldn't do more if they were Bolton
trotters; but never mind, I'm not so foolish as to make them laugh more by
losing my temper. Thee shall wed wi' him all the same ; and may be it's all the
better, for thou might'st make a very good wife, wench, to a plain gentleman,
and be but a poor catch for a marquis.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Oh, mamma! a marquis can be no more than a gentleman. But you are right, I
might falter, and trip under the weight of a coronet and an ermined robe; for
I'm only a Lancashire wild rose, after all.<stage>Exit, R. 1 E.</stage></p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Robin, L.</stage>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> Where's my mother ?—oh, she's here.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R.)</stage> What is it you want, lad ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Well, you see, there's a lot of folks going to be wed. Jenny and her
cognito—that's either a lawyer or a lord—I don't know which; and cousin and Miss
Lucy; and so, ecod, 1 think I may as well have a turn mysen.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>What do you mean ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Why, I wants to get wed, too.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Go on wi' you—it's too soon yet, wi' your smock face, to think of getting
wed.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Why, I have as much right as Jenny, and more, if it comes to that; for I'm
older, by a matter of two years.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>That's nought to signify. The lad should always be a deal older than the
lass. I don't mind thee flirting and sweet-hearting a bit, for lads will do
it—it's only natural; but thee munnot think of getting wed these four or five
years, when thee'lt look summat like a man.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Get off wi' ye! I mun not ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>No ; you mun not.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Then all fat's i' th' fire; and you mun pay damages for breach of
promise.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Why; what hast done ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Why, I ha' done it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>What hast done?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Why, I dun it—axed lass to marry.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Well, she'll take no harm o' that, and won't die of fright.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>No ; but you told me I might gie her a buss; and when I met her again, and
tried to, she wouldn't let me, and said that it was only proper between folks as
wur going to wed; and so I up and axed her to wed wi' me; and she seemed struck
of a heap, and couldn't answer; and that Mr, Adolphus coming <pb n="64"/> in
overheard me, and advised her to take me, and told her I wur a good match—the
only civil word he ever said before— and that she mightn't have such a chance
again; and I said that he was right, for I wouldn't ax her or anybody else twice
over.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>That was right enough, and straight forward.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Well, then, she said summut about it's only being a joke, and that I wasn't
in earnest; and Mr. Adolphus told me I mun write a letter, promising to marry
her; and he wrote out a form, in which I promised to wed her right off, or
forfeit £5,000; and I signed, and gie'd it lass, and she took it, but wouldn't
gie me a buss then, till she saw you, and had your consent.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh ! you soft one—I'll consent her—where is she?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>There, outside the door, waiting till I call her in, to get your
blessing.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Call her in. I'll give her a blessing.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>No, will you? It's all right, then—come in, lass, mother consents.</p>
<stage>Enter Miss Euphemia, L. 1 E. Robin puts her across to C.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Come here, and look me in the face ; thou shameless baggage, to go and take
advantage of a poor, soft, ninny loike that lad, and hook him into a promise.
For shame o' thysen; but thou shan't have him, nor touch a penny o' my money.
I'll spend it all, to the last fraction, sooner than thou should'st get a
farthing.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(C.)</stage> What is the meaning of this?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>To come over lad wi' your sly ways, and your coaxing looks, and your humming
and hawing, and all the time you don't care the snap of my finger for him, and
only want to get a tight hould of his bit o' money.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Oh ! this is too much, <stage>(bursts into tears, crosses to L .)</stage>
</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(C.)</stage> Eh! mother, dunnot be too hard on lass; see, thee'st made
her cry.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R.)</stage> Let her cry—she's only shamming—they can cry when they
like—she's laughin' in her sleeve; but let her bundle out of my presence, or
I'll put my mark on her—I will.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Na, na, mother, <stage>(crosses to C.)</stage> Dom me, if I stand it any
longer. I'm my own measter, and I'll wed wench if I loike, and if I don't I'll
go to sea, or list for a sodger, and I'll never see thee never no more; and you
may gie all the money to Jenny. I'll earn my bread for mysen, for you're none
behaving to me like a man—like a woman, I mean—nor a mother to me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh! that's more than lad ever said to me before.</p>
<stage>(begins to cry)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Mr. Wildbriar, you should not make use of such language to your mother on
any account. Don't let me be the cause of strife. Forget me—I make no claim—have
<pb n="65"/> no right. Be ruled by your mother, she is the best guide for you,
for no one can have your interest so much at heart.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>And he talks of never seeing me, never no more, and all on account of
you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>He does not mean it; as for me, I shall not be the cause of dispute—I resign
my hopes—I give him back his promise, <stage>(crosses to C.)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>No, will you—the written one?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>What written one ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Haw! haw! haw! <stage>(crosses to C.)</stage> Eh! mother, didst think I was
so soft, and I born in Lancashire? I wanted to try lass, and I offered to give
her bond ; she didn't know I was only trotting her, Bolton fashion ; but she
wouldn't take it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Not take bond for £5,000!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>No !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>No ! for by refusing five, I made sure of a hundred.<stage>(aside)</stage>
</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Nor give me a promise without your leave, and then I made up my mind to have
her; but I thought it best to trot you a bit first, and I have done it nicely,
too. Haw ! haw! haw !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R.)</stage> Eh! I dunnot mind, sin you were not so soft as I thought.
Gie me a buss, lad, thou'rt thy mother's son.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>And my feyther's, too.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Come here, lass, thou'rt a good wench. <stage>(Robin passes her to
C.)</stage> And if you'll only wait five or six years ——</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Get off wi' ye, five or six years !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Well, then, a year or so; thou shalt have him, one hundred thousand pounds,
and my blessing.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> Hooray! hooray! And now mother and I'll both have a
buss.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Aye, that we will. <stage>(kisses her)</stage> Come along, lass, and let's
have a bit talk together, and get acquainted like. Thou'rt a bonny lass, too
!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Eh ! that she is, or she might ha' whistled for me.</p>
<stage>Exeunt, L.</stage>
</sp>

<stage>Frank Hawthorne, L., dressed as for wedding, and Mrs. Vavasour, R., enter
from different sides) </stage>

<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I have been informed, that you wish to speak to me, madam.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Yes, Mr. Hawthorne; our mutual position, on the verge of a very close
relationship, must excuse the freedom and confidential character of my speech.
You appear to have taken umbrage at the little device Lucy and I put in practice
in the early stage of our acquaintance with you, the motive of which was rather
to elicit your character than to offend you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>You are quite sure of that?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R.)</stage> Well, I think—I'm sure that such was Lucy's idea.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="66"/>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> It is not true; but on the woman's lips we forgive the
white lie the mother's heart suggests.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Now, although previously Lucy may have had other prospects, of course she has
of late looked forward only to her union with you, and has endeavoured to adapt
herself to your ideas and views; and it has pained me to observe that you have
not seemed to appreciate her amiability in this matter.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>I thought the compliment was paid rather to the future fortune than to the
future husband.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Mr. Hawthorne, you do yourself and my daughter, too, an injustice. Of
course the fortune is an object —a great object—but we must have some little
consideration for the husband as well.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(aside)</stage>} Extraordinary condescension !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Now, Mr. Hawthorne, Lucy has noticed your neglect, and, I perceive, feels it
deeply. I have seen traces of tears in her eyes even this morning, and I wish
that just before you depart for the church, or sign the settlements, you would
say a few gentle words to Lucy, which will assuage her fears of not being liked
by you, and give a little grace to the sacrifice she has made of all former
views.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.— aside )</stage> Sacrifice! still sacrifice, and yet this plea. You
think it possible, then, that otherwise, she might refuse me at the last moment
?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage>} Refuse! he mustn't think that. Refuse! oh, dear, no;
she likes you too well for that, she must obey the will, she had always such a
respect for your uncle ; his wish was law with her, and there is so much
dependent on it, to refuse would be madness; but she might show grief, perhaps
burst into tears at the altar, and that would be such a scene— so painful, you
know. A few kind words from you will spare us that, if you will be only good
enough to speak them beforehand.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Well, madam, I shall think the matter over.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Oh, I am sure that you will oblige me; it will so comfort and encourage my
poor child. <stage>Exit, R.</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>How anxious this woman is to rose over the sacrifice of her child's feelings;
what tender care, what a delicate consideration, she has for appearances; and
with what cold-blooded determination she puts the knife into the breast of a
first affection, that murmurs rebellion against the sway of self-interest! With
what surgical indifference she cuts off the superfluous growth of passion, and
smiles the while the patient writhes and groans! And yet she thinks herself a
good mother, and is really acting and speaking under the instinct of a fond one.
It is the Mammon worship that has perverted and corrupted in her breast that
purest and most holy of all instincts, a mother's love, into a worldly policy,
and made it a blight, and not a beauty—a curse, and not a blessing.
<stage>(crosses to r,)</stage></p>
</sp>
<pb n="67"/>
<stage>Enter Dr. Playfair and Mr. Cunningham, L.</stage>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> Here is old Punctuality as usual, not a minute before or
after his time.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p><stage>(crosses to C.)</stage> Ah, Mr. Hawthorne, good day ; glad to see you;
particularly as you are—toilet complete, exact to your appointment, and ready
for the occasion. I congratulate you, sir, upon this business-like
self-possession at such a moment; marriage and inheritance—a lady wife, and a
large fortune— very great trials for the nerves, as prosperity is harder to bear
with equanimity even than adversity.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(aside)</stage> Yes, for I am cool and calm, with the catastrophe of
an epic foreshadowed on my heart.<stage>(crosses to L. table)</stage>
</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>Where are the other parties ?—no time to waste; must put in appearance before
twelve o'clock; just eleven hours three minutes and fifteen seconds of the day
gone ;—it will take fifteen minutes to sign settlements, &amp;c, and another
quarter of an hour to reach the church.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that—only ten minutes, as the carriages are ready at the
door.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>Tut! we must make allowance for the ladies, shawling and bonneting, sure to
waste time.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I don't object to that; they always do. <stage>(at L. table)</stage> I sent
word that you had arrived, and, see, our friends are here.</p>
<stage>Enter Sir Lionel Norman, Hon. Augustus Adolphus, Mrs. Vavasour, Jenny,
and Lucy, R., dressed as for bridal —Everard Digby, Mrs. Wildbriar, Robin,
Jenny, and Miss Euphemia, L. ; Jenny crosses L. to Lucy.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>Good day, good day, ladies and gentlemen. You are all aware that this is the
last hour of the six months prescribed for determining the recipients or
application of the large amount of the late Mr. Hawthorne's property, under his
will, formally read by me. Here are two forms of assent and dissent, for Lucy
Vavasour and Francis Hawthorne, either of which they will please to sign within
the five minutes <stage>(looks at watch)</stage> that I can spare for a
reconsideration of their previous determination, <stage>(hands two forms to
Lucy, ditto to Frank— Frank rises)</stage>
</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(up, C.)</stage> What nonsense ! as if either would be so soft as to
refuse.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p><stage>(up, L.)</stage> Cousin won't, I hope : but no fear ; he was <pb
n="68"/> brought up in Lancashire, and he's got his head screwed on right
way.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(who has crossed to Frank, C.)</stage> Oh, Mr. Hawthorne, won't you
say a kind word to Lucy ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>No, madam; your daughter's feelings, or her policy, must direct her choice. I
shall not light one false beacon on her path, nor cast the lure of one
persuasive word to tempt her into infamy.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, don't speak so loud, she might hear you.</p>
<p><stage>(crossing back to Lucy)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L., to Frank : rises)</stage>} Remember, if you make a fool of yourself,
and refuse, I shall object to you all my life. <stage>(seats himself
again)</stage>
</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Oh ! Lucy! Lucy! don't refuse; don't rush into poverty. I'm sure he'll be a
kind man, and let you have your own way.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Heaven grant that now he may prove a harsh one.— But, hush! mother, hush ! I
am listening to my heart.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R.)</stage> Oh ! don't—don't ! listen to anything but that;—listen to
your mother's prayers and entreaties.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R.)</stage> He's watching us ;—his mind is resolved. I know—I know his
thought. Ah ! a gleam of hope ! I see the way. Yes, mother, yes ! I, too, have
resolved.</p>
<stage>( embraces her mother, Frank shrugs his shoulders: she sits down to
table, R.; hesitates for a moment ; signs one of the papers, and then buries her
face in her hands on table)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>,<stage>(l , aside)</stage>} She has signed the consent—I am sure of it. Yes,
the struggle was fierce, but short, and Mammon has prevailed, <stage>(goes to
sign, L.)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Mind what you're about, lad; and don't sign wrong paper.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R., aside to Sir Lionel)</stage> If he should, the mortgages upon the
baronetcy would soon be liquidated.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Tis done!</p>
<stage>(Dr. Playfair takes paper to Cunningham, and returns to seat, L. C.
)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Hawthorne—Miss Vavasour—the five minutes have expired. The assentforms
that you have signed, if you please.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(to her mother)</stage> Take it—give it—I cannot!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(at table, L.)</stage> Some shame left still; even that's a virtue—a
poor one—only to be prized from all the others' absence.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>Here, here, Mr. Cunningham, is my daughter's— good child. I am so happy !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p><stage>(reads at table, C.)</stage> " I, Lucy Vavasour, do hereby " affirm,
declare, and make known, to the executors and trustees, " under the will of the
late George Hawthorne, and to all parties {"} having an interest therein, that I
accept the condition attached " to a joint inheritance with Francis Hawthorne,
under said<pb n="69"/> " will; and agree to contract the bonds of legal marriage
with " the said Francis Hawthorne, on this day, January 6th, 1858. " Witness my
hand and seal—Lucy Vavasour."</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(up C.)</stage> Good lass, and a happy wedding to thee!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p><stage>(up C. L.)</stage> And many of them !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Eh ! the lad thinks a wedding like New Year or Christmas day.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Hush ! mother, hush !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(reads)</stage>} " I, Francis Hawthorne, do hereby affirm, " declare, and
make known, to the executors and trustees under " the will of the late George
Hawthorne, and to all parties "having an interest therein, that I " Ahem! eh !
bless my soul! Have you mistaken the document, sir?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>No.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p><stage>(reads)</stage> " That I decline to accept the conditions " attached
to a joint inheritance with Lucy Vavasour, under " said will." <stage>(Lucy
starts up)</stage>
</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Why, he's gied her all the property.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L.)</stage> Eh ! the d—d fool !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p><stage>(reads)</stage> " And hereby formally and finally refuse to contract a
marriage with the said Lucy Vavasour. Witness my hand and seal—Francis
Hawthorne."</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rushing forward, and falling on her knees)</stage> Thank Heaven!
<stage>(R. C.)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises, L. C.)</stage> Aye ! thank Heaven that I have had more pity on
thee than thon hadst upon thyself; that I have spared thee the equal sin and
torture of an unholy marriage— the life of wretchedness that must have ensued
from wedding one your heart abhorred.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R. c, rising)</stage> Sir?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Aye, look angrily ; it had become thee better but a moment before.
Listen—harken all—my motive for this deed, not from vain-glory do I publish it,
but to vindicate the act from any suspicion of recklessness, or want of due
consideration. I did admire—did love this woman. I have no shame in the avowal,
even when I knew she loved me not. I might have continued to love her, had she
continued to make plain her known dislike, but tempted by this mighty wealth,
she made a bargain with her pride—her heart—to hide themselves, till she had
grasped some part of the golden prize.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Indeed, sir?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Indeed, indeed. What, then, remained? The sacrifice of wealth— vast wealth,
'tis true, and almost fabulous, or the sacrifice of honesty and self-esteem, the
double sacrifice between us —man's honor, woman's purity—those first great
principles, in which consists the soul's true likeness to its Maker—more vast
than time or space—the true illimitable—the eternity ! I could <pb n="70"/>
not—did not hesitate, and have no pride of what I've done, save what accrues
from simple self-respect preserved. I am accustomed to an humble life, can live
it contentedly; you could not; and in a worldly point of view, the lesser
forfeiture is mine. May it lift thee to the full height of the generous
nobleness that often springs from vast possession, never doomed to companionship
with pettiness of thought, a little meanness, or a wrangling envy.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R.)</stage> Oh, this is truly noble—truly generous.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>He's a great character.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p><stage>(up, R.)</stage> Accept our thanks.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Spare thanks—acknowledgments. I do not reciprocate your esteem. I have no
wish to be rude, but henceforth we are strangers. <stage>(crosses L. to Doctor,
and then goes up stage)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p><stage>(comes down, C.)</stage> He's the man for my money. He shall have my
daughter Jenny.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Hush ! No, no, mamma. <stage>(coming down)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Second cousins can't marry, you know. <stage>(jestingly)</stage>
</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Then I'll have him mysen, if he'll have an old woman and £50,000.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Get off, and sit down, do. Shut up, mother!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(to Frank, who has shaken hands with Dr. Playfair, and is
going)</stage> Stay, sir, one moment, if you please; we have had too much of
double-dealing and stage-play. I would escape all further deception—run no risk
of a snare. Is this document really formal and sufficient, Mr Cunningham ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>It needs but our attestation as witnesses, that we have seen him sign.
<stage>(Frank comes down L. C.)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>Let that be done, and, pray, in the gentleman's presence. <stage>(Dr.
Playfair and Cunningham sign)</stage> And now you tell me, in your character of
executors and trustees, that this makes me mistress of all—that the whole of the
fortune belongs to me—to me alone.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Dr. P. and Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>It does.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(crossing to Frank)</stage> Then I shall wear the willow all my life,
and have it planted on my grave, if you a second time refuse me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>How?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p><stage>(holding up scroll)</stage> I know by these dear words, <stage>(shows
song)</stage> you love me still; and I am thine—thine, heart and soul, and have
been long.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Oh, heaven! Can this be true, or is it a cruel jest ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>I knew your doubts; I guessed your proud resolve. Had I refused, all had been
lost. This mighty wealth, your just inheritance, I made but mine to give it with
myself to thee,</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Lucy, <stage>(they embrace)</stage> God bless thee!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Hurray ! hurray ? Lancashire for ever !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Silence !—No, I don't object to that. Hurrah !</p>
</sp>
<pb n="71"/>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Who cares if thee did, man ? The lad's our cousin, and lass mun be our cousin
now, and I'm glad on it, for she's best in house.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>It was my device that brought you together—taught you to know each other. You
owe all your happiness to me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>I object to that, doctor. My cousin will own to having taken a hint from a
clever little girl, and Lucy must admit being in my debt for a glimpse into her
lover's heart.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>No, no; I will not admit being in debt to any one but to my husband, to whom
I owed all my heart three months ago.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>My love had still an earlier date ; it sprang into existence with my first
glimpse of thee.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>There's ingratitude!—what selfish creatures lovers are!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to that, or you and I would mind our own business.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Why you are not in love, are you? With whom?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I object to telling you, or anybody else.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Never mind, I shall find out, as sure as I'm a clever little girl. I suspect
already it's with my mother.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>No, no, no; I object to that.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha ! ha! that's the very reason I believe it. Ha ! ha ! mamma, will you
have the doctor for a beau ?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>Noa, I should object to that; no, thank you; if I wanted to make a fool of
mysen, I should have a better excuse for it than a cranky old body like
that.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(R.)</stage> The poor baronetcy has lost its chance of escape from the
usurious clutch of the mortgagees.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>But the baronet has received a lesson that has raised him above participation
in such regrets. Mr. Hawthorne, I trust you will this time accept the
congratulations on your great and deserved felicity, which I most sincerely
proffer.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Manfally and generously spoken, Sir Lionel, and in the true spirit of that
chivalry which has ever been, and I trust ever will be, the prevailing
characteristic of an English gentleman. <stage>( shakes hands)</stage>} And hark
ye, Messrs. Executors, if not upon so great a scale as suggested by the codicil,
still we shall have the school; for to be a man of the day, one must have regard
to the interests of the coming man.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p><stage>(rises and comes to R. C.)</stage> Mr. Hawthorne, if you should feel
disposed to extend your investments —</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>Unfortunately, I have no overstock of modesty or of common sense, or, in
charity to your need, I should lend you some, Mr. Adolphus.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>I should object to your lending him anything. Both his head and his heart are
fruitless soil, and never would repay culture.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>I beg pardon ; look at my hair and whiskers. <stage>(they all laugh)</stage>
Oh, I don't mind being laughed at by such an exceedingly happy and fortunate
gentleman as Mr. Hawthorne, or even by his friends, on the occasion of his
wedding; but Dr. Playfair, I must object to being made the butt of your jests,
after to-day.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>Well, I don't object to that, for I hope never to see you after to day.</p>

</sp>
<stage> Enter James, L.</stage>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>Here comes James, to tender his resignation.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no; I perceive there is going to be a coalition between the {h}opposition
and {h}independent parties, and as my politics are very promiscuous, I beg to
say, that I am willing to continue in {h}office, which his always the grand
{h}object of a {h}upper.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>And so the great Hawthorne property having been legitimately disposed of, and
to everybody's satisfaction, ladies and gentlemen, I beg to inform you, that we
have just thirty-five minutes, seven seconds, and a half left, to reach the
church and get the marriage over: make haste; even a wedding can have no greater
grace than punctuality.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_mult">
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes, yes!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M4">
<speaker>Mr. C.</speaker>
<p>Indeed I shall give you one minute and a half, to name its rivals.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M1">
<speaker>Sir L.</speaker>
<p>High connexions !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M2">
<speaker>Adol.</speaker>
<p>Good investments !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M5">
<speaker>Everard.</speaker>
<p>Honour and affection !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F12">
<speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
<p>A little shrewdness !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F11">
<speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
<p>No double dealings on either side !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F13">
<speaker>Miss E.</speaker>
<p>Sentiment and simplicity !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M7">
<speaker>Robin.</speaker>
<p>Ay ! wedding first, and dumplings after !</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M3">
<speaker>Dr. P.</speaker>
<p>A little objection to be got over.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M8">
<speaker>James.</speaker>
<p>{H}office and perquisites to follow.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F9">
<speaker>Mrs. V.</speaker>
<p>A great inheritance.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_F10">
<speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
<p>No ; the union of hearts with hands, <stage>(giving her hand to
Frank)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0616_M6">
<speaker>Frank.</speaker>
<p>The truth lives not alone in one grace, one virtue, but in all; and as we are
certain to lack some, to ensure happiness we should temper the conscious pride
of our respective merits with a charitable consideration for their companion
faults, and so preserve them from that dangerous affinity to vice, which
virtue's self acquires when she runs into Extremes.</p>
</sp>
</div>

<trailer>Printed by Thomas Scott, 1, Warwick Court, Holborn.</trailer>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
