<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L0623" xml:lang="en">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>The Rifle and how to use it:: TEI edition</title>
    <author ref="lacyp:W0038"><persName>Bridgeman, J. V. </persName><idno type="wikidata"
      >Q131370278</idno></author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>TEI conversion</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor>
    <idno type="LAE">L0623</idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives
      all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which it believes to be in the public
      domain. You may copy, modify, distribute, or perform this work freely. </licence>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="originalSource" n="42.8"><author n="W0038">Bridgeman, J.V.</author>
     <title type="main">The Rifle and How To Use It</title>
     <title type="sub">An Original Farce in one act</title>
     <extent>26 pp (UM copy: 386 - 412)<measure type="pp" quantity="26"/>
      <measure type="spCount" quantity="498"/>
      <measure type="spvCount" quantity="0"/>
      <measure type="txWords" quantity="8435"/>
      <measure type="spWords" quantity="6851"/>
      <measure type="stWords" quantity="1584"/>
     </extent>
     <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 42, No. 0623</title><idno type="nic"
      >N09732</idno></bibl>
    <bibl type="surrogate"><ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uiug.30112069425913">UIU from
      HT</ref></bibl>
    <bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref
      target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015005299667&amp;seq=386 ">UM from
      HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol42/L0623/L0623-um.pdf"/></bibl>
    <listEvent>
     <event type="LCP" when="1862-09-16" where="Haymarket">
      <desc>Licence sent 16 September 1859 for performance at the Theatre Royal, Haymarket. </desc>
      <bibl type="msSource">BL ms LCP_52984.O</bibl>
     </event>
     <event type="firstPerf" when="1859-09-20" source="textNic" where="Haymarket">
      <desc>Premiered at Theatre Royal, Haymarket 20 Sept. 1859</desc>
     </event>
    </listEvent>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <!--S 1 Farce F. FARCE-->
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#sizeS"/>
    <catRef target="#act1"/>
    <catRef target="nic:F."/>
    <keywords>
     <term>FARCE</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
   <particDesc>
    <listPerson>
     <person xml:id="L0623_M1">
      <persName type="role">Mr. Percival Floff.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="194">Perci.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Percival Floff.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Percival.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0623_M2">
      <persName type="role">Mr. Sidney Jubkins</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Jubkins.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="86">Sidney.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0623_M3">
      <persName type="role">Alfred Charles Mutton</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="70">Alfred.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0623_M4">
      <persName type="role">Pad</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="21">Pad.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0623_F5">
      <persName type="role">Mrs. Percival Floff</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="55">Mrs. F.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0623_F6">
      <persName type="role">Mrs. Sidney Jubkins</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Mrs. G.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="34">Mrs. J.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0623_F7">
      <persName type="role">Mary</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="32">Mary.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0623_mult">
      <persName type="role">[Multiple speakers]</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Mrs. F. | Mrs. J.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Sidney. | Perci.</persName>
     </person>
    </listPerson>
   </particDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2026-07-01">Add wikidata link to titleStmt where possible</change>
   <change when="2026-07-01">Checked against UM copy and hand edited</change>
   <change when="2025-12-06">Text extracted from PDF and initial structuring by Gemini</change>
  </revisionDesc>

 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <titlePage>
    <titlePart type="main">The Rifle and how to use it:</titlePart>
    <titlePart type="sub">An original farce in one act</titlePart>
    <byline>BY <docAuthor>J. V. Bridgeman, Esq.,</docAuthor> Member of the DramaticC Authors'
     Society</byline>
    <docImprint>THOMAS HAILES LACY, 89, STRAND, (Opposite Southampton Street, Covent Garden Market),
     LONDON.</docImprint>
   </titlePage>
   <pb n="2"/>
   <performance>
    <head>The Rifle and How to Use It</head>
    <p>First Performed at the Theatre Royal, Haymarket, Under the Management of Mr. Buckstone. On
     Thursday, September 20th, 1859.</p>

    <castList>
     <head>CHARACTERS.</head>

     <castItem><role gender="M">MR. Percival Floff.</role><actor>Mr. J. B.
      Buckstone</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">MR. Sidney Jubkins</role><actor>Mr. Rogers.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Alfred Charles Mutton</role><roleDesc> (a
       Policeman)</roleDesc><actor>Mr. Compton.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Pad</role><actor>Mr. Worrell</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="F">Mrs. Percival Floff</role><actor>Mrs. B. White.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="F">Mrs. Sidney Jubkins</role><actor>Mrs. Wilkins.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="F">Mary</role><actor>Mrs. Fitzwilliam.</actor></castItem>
    </castList>

   </performance>

   <set>
    <p>The action takes place at Mr. Percival Floff's house at Clapham.</p>
    <p>Time –– 1859.</p>

   </set>


   <div type="costume">
    <head>COSTUMES.</head>
    <list>
     <item>Floff.—Knickerbocker rifle uniform. </item>
     <item>Mutton.—Policeman's uniform. </item>
     <item>Mary.—Cotton dress, cap, &amp;c. </item>
     <item>Jubkins, Mrs. Floff, Mrs. Jubkins, and Pad.—Fashionable morning dress.</item>
    </list>
   </div>
  </front>
  <pb n="3"/>
  <body>
   <div type="act">
    <head>THE RIFLE AND HOW TO USE IT.</head>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE. A Room in Mr. Percival Floff's House at Clapham.</head>
     <stage>Bow windows, R. and L., opening into garden—doors, R. 1 E.—R. U. E. and L. 1 E.—tables,
      chairs, &amp;c.</stage>
     <stage>Mrs. Percival Floff discovered seated at table, L., and sewing. Ring heard at garden
      bell, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking up from her work)</stage>
      <p>Visitors' bell! I wonder who that can possibly be! <stage>(rises and advances to window,
        L.)</stage> Why, no! yes! it is not, though—Yes, it is. Mrs. Sidney Jubkins.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Mrs. Sidney Jubkins, D. R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(L., kissing her)</stage>
      <p>My dear Mrs. Jubkins, how are you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <stage>(R.)</stage>
      <p>Thank you, my darling, quite well.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Who would ever have dreamt of seeing you here? and so early, too!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>That's just it. I have dropt in early on purpose. I have come to suggest we should all go
       and have a delightful day at the Crystal Palace.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>At the Crystal Palace?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Sidney will defray all the expense. He did not come home till I don't know what o'clock
       last night, or rather, this morning, from the grand dinner of the new Volunteer Rifle Corps
       they have got up. And he was in such a state. I did not say much to him <hi>then</hi>,
       because I could not. He was off to sleep in no time. But this morning, when he woke, I told
       him a piece of my mind. He requested me to be quiet, because he had got a headache. Of
       course, my dear, I was not foolish enough to throw away an opportunity like that! He has
       given me the money to purchase a love of a dress I have long wanted,
       <pb n="4"/> and is coming directly to take us to the Crystal Palace. Where's Mr. Floff?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Upstairs, locked in his room. Talk of your Sidney! Percival has been going on far worse.
        <hi>He</hi> didn't return from his Rifle dinner till just five o'clock this morning, and the
       first thing he did was to turn all my chest of drawers topsy turvy!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>I'd topsy turvy him! what did he do that for?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>He said he wanted a pen. I told him he would be more likely to find one in the inkstand. On
       this, he went down stairs—in about a quarter of an hour I heard him go out again, and return
       in about five minutes or so; when he came up, I inquired where he had been—he replied, "To
       post a letter!" and on my asking to whom, answered—"To the devil!"</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, the wretch! if he had done that to me, my dear, I would have made the place so hot for
       him that he would have considered it a relief to go after his letter. But you are too
       good-natured.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>I can't help it! Percival has such a sweet temper; and it's only when he's ruffled—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, but he's ruffled very often—go on, though. What did he do next?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>He usually goes off to sleep the moment he gets into bed. Besides which, he is accustomed
       to undress himself. This morning, however, he sternly refused to take off his uniform, as he
       calls it, and was not still a minute.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>You don't say so!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, he kept tumbling and tossing about so, that, at half past seven, I got up, perfectly
       worn out. Directly I left the room, he jumped out of bed, bolted the door, and has refused to
       open it since. I have not the slightest notion what he has been doing, except that, at
       frequent intervals, he paces up and down like a lynx in a cage.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>That's headache, my dear. But such proceedings cannot be allowed. We must prove to these
       gentlemen riflemen that, whatever they might– and of course would– do with a foreign foe,
       they can't get the better of their wives so easily. But come, go and get ready. Sidney will
       be here soon—at least, he had better.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Just let me finish these two or three stitches. There's the paper—our local paper—" The
       Clapham Scourge," with which is incorporated the "Brixton Scarifier."</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Thank you! <stage>(they sit at table, L—Mrs. Floff, R.—Mrs. Jubkins, L.—MRS, Floff resumes
        her work—Mrs. Jubkins takes up paper and glances her eye over it—suddenly she stops and
        exclaims)</stage> Oh, dear! what is this?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="5"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>What?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>I do not know yet, but I will read it. "Infamous Conduct at Clapham!" Oh, how interesting!
        <stage>(arranges herself more comfortably in her chair, and reads)</stage> "We stop the
       press to acquaint our readers, and hold up to the execration of posterity the perpetrator,
       who is at present unknown, of the following diabolical act:—It would appear that Mr. Gloss,
       tailor, had resolved to have his establishment whitewashed. Not to interfere with the
       business, the painters and other artificers were not admitted until half past eleven o'clock
       at night. In the course of the operations, one of the workmen, in order to gain room, placed
       on the pavement, in front of the shop door, a valuable lay figure, or dummy, life size, on
       which Mr. Gloss was in the habit of displaying his celebrated suits at four four. Suddenly a
       loud report was heard, followed by a frightful crash—the artificers and others rushed into
       the street, and beheld the valuable figure stretched on the ground, damaged beyond the limits
       of human ingenuity to repair, with the head completely severed from the trunk. Is such
       conduct to be tolerated? We boldly answer in the negative. From the loud report and a leaden
       bullet being eventually discovered in the head, we have every reason for concluding the
       dastardly deed was perpetrated by some description of firearms; but even this shall not
       screen the miscreant from justice—the police are on his track, and we therefore say to him,
       beware!"</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>How exciting! and how well written!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Is it not? but what a wanton act. A poor dummy! I declare I shall be afraid to trust Sidney
       out after dark. <stage>(garden bell rings—Mrs. Jubkins starts up)</stage> Ah! there he is!
        <stage>(throws paper down on table, L.)</stage> Let us waste no time—run up stairs and put
       your bonnet on.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Come with me—perhaps Percival will undo the door more readily if he hears your voice.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MR. Sidney Jubkins, D. R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, good morning, Mrs. Floff—quite well, I hope?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Quite, thank you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Where's Percival?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking at him sternly)</stage>
      <p>Mr. Floff has not come down yet. Like some other person, who shall be nameless, he was not
       home till late.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(coughs)</stage>
      <p>Oh, indeed! Yes, I—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>But we are going up stairs <stage>(crosses R.)</stage> so that Mrs. Floff may get ready—and
       we will inform him you are here.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="6"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Do, my dear—we have not much time to lose, if we are to have a nice long day at the Palace.
        <stage>Exeunt Mrs. Floff and Mrs. Jubkins, R. D.</stage> She's not quite mollified yet. I
       must see what a new bonnet will do, in addition to the dress. No, I won't—I'll—I'll—not stand
       this any longer—I'll—I'll throw off this degrading yoke —I'll do so immediately, if not
       sooner. Yes, I'll begin at once, I—I won't take her to Sydenham. <stage>(walks about at first
        in a determined manner, but by degrees he grows more and more vacillating, till at length he
        stops)</stage> After all, it's not worth while kicking up a shindy to-day—and there would be
       a shindy, without the slightest shadow of a doubt—and in Floff's house, too. No, for his
       sake, I'll wait till to-morrow—that is the wiser and the more gentlemanly course. Besides, my
       head still aches confoundedly—I may as well have my headache in peace and quietness.
        <stage>(goes up to window, L., and stands looking into the garden)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Percival Floff, R. D., dressed in rifle uniform—he paces slowly forward, stopping
      now and then, and muttering—to himself—he looks pale and haggard—his hair is dishevelled, and
      his dress that of a man who has been to bed in it—after a pause, Sidney turns round—on
      perceiving Floff, he goes softly up to him, and slaps him suddenly on the shoulder.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, Floff, old boy, how are you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(starts, in great terror)</stage>
      <p>Oh! <stage>(looking round, and perceiving Sidney)</stage> Don't!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>What?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Don't! If you don't don't, it will be the worse for you. <stage>(resumes his walk, still
        muttering.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>What is the matter? How queer you look; and still in uniform. Have <hi>you</hi> been
       catching it too?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Catching what? I have attempted to catch nothing, therefore, I say, catching what?
        <stage>(fiercely)</stage> Explain yourself this moment.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>How excited you are!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I am not excited! I am simply irritated, and with good cause. As a baby, I was remarkable
       for an angelic sweetness of temper, and, as an adult, I have not belied the promise of my
       infancy. I am the gentlest creature in the world, and I never get angry except when any one
       puts me in a passion. Do you hear?—except when any one puts me in a passion.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Calm yourself!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I shan't.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="7"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Ain't you well?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Ain't I well? <stage>(sepulchrally)</stage> Ah!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Come, we are all going to the Crystal Palace.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>That is a falsehood. We are not all going to the Crystal Palace—I<hi> </hi>am not going to
       the Crystal Palace—I am going a trifle further—I am going to America.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>To America?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>To America. A, m, e, r, i, k—no, с, а.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>You are joking.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I am <hi>not</hi> joking. I would give three pounds ten at this moment for a flat iron—a
       simple, domestic flat iron—to break your head for daring to make such an assertion.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Why, Percival, my boy, what have I done?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>What have you done? You have made me what I am.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>What are you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Don't you know?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>No—unless you are drunk.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(seizing him by the arm)</stage>
      <p>Ha, ha! I wish I were. Do you pretend to forget what occurred last night?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I know we were very jolly, and came home part of the way together, after having dined with
       each other at our mess.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>The real mess had not begun then. Don't you remember what happened afterwards?.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>You alarm me. What?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>What! Good gracious! have you forgotten that, as we were nearly home, on turning a corner,
       we saw, opposite Gloss's shop, a—a man—a—a human being—in fact, with his back towards us.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I have not the smallest remembrance of such a thing.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking at Sidney fixedly)</stage>
      <p>Then you were more intoxicated than I thought you were. On beholding the individual in
       question what did I do?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>What?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Nothing.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Well!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>It is not well. I forbid you to use that—that—<stage>(as seeking a word)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Word.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>No—that—that pronoun again—It was not well. There was a demon by my side—that demon said to
       me " I say, Floff, my boy, what a mark that fellow would be at a long range." Giving way to
       my natural spirits—or, perhaps, to the wine I had taken, I—the innocent Floff—the "Floff, my
       boy," of the
       <pb n="8"/> tempter—in martial playfulness, put my rifle to my shoulder, as if to pink off
       the being we had observed—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>And—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I<hi> did </hi>pink him off.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>You—you—you don't mean to say you—you—you killed him?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Your assertion is both premature and erroneous—I do mean to say so—I saw the wretched being
       fall—I flung away my rifle, like a fool—so did you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(eagerly listening, and repeating his last words)</stage>
      <p>So did I—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Like another. I ran, followed by you. When I stopped I was in a profuse perspiration, and a
       brick field at Hackney—you were nowhere. I took breath, and then took a cab to
       Hammersmith.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Why to Hammersmith, when you reside at Clapham?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>To put the myrmidons of justice off my track. I then got into a cab, and drove to
       Whitechapel, where I saw another—I took it, and drove to Battersea—I alighted, and walked to
       Clapham. I reached my own once happy dwelling. I went to bed, but I could not sleep, no more
       could Euphemia; she said I kicked about so. Did you ever go to Madame Tussaud's Chamber of
       Horrors?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Never.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>You never enjoyed the artistic and humanising treat of seeing our glorious British
       murderers in waxwork?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Never.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Then save the extra sixpence, and look at me. <stage>(sits at table, R.)</stage> You can
       now contemplate a real assassin for nothing.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>This is frightful! I now remember all. I had fancied it was a dream..</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(starting up)</stage>
      <p>The officers of justice will soon be on my track. Every knock I hear at the door I expect
       to be a policeman. I have written to Consols—my stockbroker—to realise for me without loss of
       time. I went out and posted the letter myself before I retired to to bed last night. I am
       awaiting his answer every minute. Directly I get the money, I am off to America—to the
       backwoods—to the very backest of the backwoods, where they're not particular about shooting a
       man.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Does Mrs. Floff know of your determination?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Not a word. She is profoundly ignorant both of that and of my crime. Mind you do not arouse
       her suspicions. If you do—tremble! you are my accomplice.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="9"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I beg your pardon, I—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I beg yours—you urged me to the fatal deed. Whether you wanted the man's watch or anything
       else, I do not know—but you had, no doubt, your motives.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I won't put up with this—I won't be bullied any longer by any one.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(fiercely)</stage>
      <p>Who wants to bully you? I say you are my accomplice. Indeed, I am not sure you ought not to
       be considered the murderer.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I never shot him.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>But your rifle did.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>My rifle !</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Remember, we were comparing rifles. I had got yours, and you mine, and, when the weapons
       are found, as they no doubt will be it will be evident which of the two launched the deadly
       bullet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>But you know the truth?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Nobody else does though.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>You could never be base enough—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I could. Hush, here come our unhappy wives.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Mrs. Floff and Mrs. Jubkins, R. D.—Mrs. Floff dressed to go out.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Well, gentlemen, here we are. Why, surely, Percival, you are not going in that costume?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I am not going at all.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_mult">
      <speaker>Mrs. F. | Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Not going at all?</p>
     </sp>

     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>To you, Mrs. F. I answer decidedly not. <stage>(crosses to her)</stage> To you, Mrs.
       Jubkins I beg to reply at greater length. I exceedingly regret my inability to accompany
       you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>How can Jubkins take care of us both?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Jubkins will not go either.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>This is most extraordinary. But I am afraid you are mistaken. <stage>(crosses to
        Sidney)</stage> Jubkins, my dear, you intend to escort us do you not?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking affrightedly—first at his wife, and then at Floff)</stage>
      <p>Why, my dear—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Of course you do—that is enough. <stage>(retires up)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, that is enough.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>But not sufficient. <stage>(crosses to Sidney—aside)</stage> Go, if you dare.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>The fact is—I—<stage>(aside to Floff)</stage> What shall I say?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside to Sidney)</stage>
      <p>Anything. <stage>(goes up)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="10"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Business of importance—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>No prevarication, sir! <stage>(down on his R.)</stage> Besides, you have no business to
       have business when it's your wife's pleasure to have pleasure.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, I know that—I—but—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Jubkins!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Polly—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Don't Polly me, sir! <stage>(rather loud)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Might I suggest, as you seem to be growing rather warm, that the air of the garden would
       prove cooler, and, consequently, more agreeable than the atmosphere of this room?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>I understand you, Mr. Floff. <stage>(proceeds majestically towards window, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Thank heaven, for her sake, she has gone! I felt my blood rising. I am determined to throw
       off this dreadful yoke.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <stage>(turning round suddenly and making an imperious sign for him to follow)</stage>
      <p>Mr. Jubkins, may I request the honour of your society?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>With pleasure, my dear!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit Mrs. Jubkins, followed by Jubkins, window, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Your friend, Mrs. Jubkins, seems a sweet creature.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>It would be well if all women possessed her spirit.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Perhaps it would—but if, Mrs. Percival Floff, you wish by that remark to convey any
       allusion, however distant, to yourself, I beg to state that I have no objection to your
       possessing quite as much spirit as your friend—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Well then—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Provided you keep it carefully bottled up.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(taking out her pocket handkerchief)</stage>
      <p>Oh, Percival, my pet! Why do you speak thus harshly, my own one?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(half crying)</stage>
      <p>Don't, Euphemia, don't! Don't address me in that way—I can't bear it—it is too much for my
       mild and yielding disposition!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(coaxing, and as if speaking to a child)</stage>
      <p>What is a matter wiz a little darling, then?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Wife of my bosom—I—but—no, I must be firm—I must resist your affectionate, though slightly
       childish, blandishments.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>No, you musn't! Does a pretty darling lookee ill? <stage>(goes up to sideboard, C., brings
        down decanter and glass to table, L.)</stage> He sall have a glass of wine, he sall!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>No, he shan't! Stop! on second thoughts, he shall. Give him one. <stage>(sits R. of table,
        L.—Mrs. Floff pours out a glass which he tosses off, and then holds to be refilled)</stage>
       Give him another! <stage>(she fills again—he drinks it)</stage> Give him another!</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="11"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>No, his darling does not think another glass good for him.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Perhaps it is not! Then give him the decanter! <stage>(Mrs. Floff tries to keep the
        decanter from him, but he succeeds in wresting it from her, and, turning L. puts it to his
        lips. Suddenly his eyes fall on something outside window, L.—the sight seems to choke him,
        and he is seized with a violent fit of coughing, during which Mrs. Floff pats him on the
        back—at length recovering his breath, and pointing to window)</stage> Wha—what is that?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>That! why a policeman to be sure.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Is not <stage>(eyeing her steadfastly)</stage> is not he examining this house with more
       than professional vigilance?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, that is because—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Hush! <stage>(putting his hand before her mouth)</stage> How he eyes every window
        <stage>(leads her forward)</stage> Be good enough to go to the front door and request that
       representative of the executive to walk in –and let Mary bring lunch.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(surprised and hesitating)</stage>
      <p>My pet—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>My sweet one, oblige me by doing as you are desired, and leaving me for a while, I—I—have
       something of importance to discuss with that individual—go, there's a sweet dear!
        <stage>(Mrs. F. crosses slowly—suddenly and very savagely)</stage> Go! <stage>Exit Mrs.
        Floff hastily, L. D.</stage> I must be determined! At any rate, I am not harsh or unkind.
       —The crisis of my fate approaches, I know how it is. That policeman has been sent to watch
       me. <stage>(looking through window L.)</stage> Ah! she is speaking to him! goodness gracious!
        <stage>(staggers to L., table, as if to take the decanter, when his eye suddenly falls on
        the paper which Mrs. Jubkins has thrown down)</stage> Ah! what is this?
        <stage>(reads)</stage> "Infamous conduct at Clapham," hem, hem! "We stop the
       press—execration of prosperity—" no, "pos-terity" oh! <stage>(staggers, but supports himself
        by the table)</stage> Ah! where was I? <stage>(running his eye over the paper)</stage> Is
       this it? yes! "a leaden bullet discovered in the head—police on his track!" Oh, good heavens!
       Courage, Floff! let me collect my scattered thoughts! I will offer him unheard of sums—The
       police, I know, is immaculate—still pity for a human being—<hi>disinterested</hi>
        pity—<stage>(feels in his pockets)</stage> Where is my pocket-book! I must have left it in
       my bedroom. <stage>(rushes off, R. D.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Mrs. Floff, followed by Alfred MUTTON, L. D.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Here, my dear, is the—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>I beg pardon, you said—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(indignantly)</stage>
      <p>I was speaking to my husband, who, I thought was here.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="12"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Percival Floff.</speaker>
      <stage>(without)</stage>
      <p>Phemy, have you seen my pocket-book?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(going to R. D.)</stage>
      <p>Coming, dear! <stage>(to Alfred)</stage> Just take a chair, if you please, Mr. Floff will
       be with you in a moment. <stage>Exit R. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>This is a rum start. I wonder what they want with me? "Mr. Floff wishes particularly to see
       you—" what's his motive? I'll soon find out; I was not born yesterday, nor the day before—no,
       I was born at an early period of my existence—It's about my visiting Mary, I suppose—they
       object to my using their kitchen, that's it. Well, it's only swearing I was never there—but
       mum, I hear some one a coming.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter Floff, R. D.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(extraordinarily agitated, but endeavouring to conceal his emotion)</stage>
      <p>How dye do—o—o—you—you—I—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>He's very waxy—I'll manage him, though. <stage>(aloud)</stage> The lady said a gentleman
       wanted to see me—Mr. Floff, I believe. It's all right here, ain't it?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, ye—e—s, all right!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! I knowed it was!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>He knowed it was!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>I could not be mistaken in you—I've seed you too often for that.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Seed me too often! how he's looking at me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(eyeing him closely)</stage>
      <p>You don't seem quite the thing.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>No, not quite—a little faint!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Well, to be sure, it <hi>is</hi> trying weather.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>"Trying weather!" If that's not a plain hint—<stage>(aloud)</stage> The subject on which I
       desired to— <stage>Enter Mary with lunch, goes to table, L.</stage> Oh, here's the lunch!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <stage>(on seeing Alfred, she starts and gives a scream which, however, she half
       suppresses—Alfred winks and slaps his nose significantly with his finger as a sign for her
       not to recognise him)</stage>
      <p/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(with great affright, crossing to table, L.)</stage>
      <p>Mary, be quiet. What do you mean by screaming in that way! I insist on an explanation.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>Well, when—when—when, I seed a policeman in our parlour, I thought there must be something
       wrong.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>And a very natural thought, too, young woman,</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="13"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(to Mary)</stage>
      <p>There, arrange the things; put two glasses, and leave the room. <stage>(Mary does so) Exit
        L. D.</stage>
       <stage>(with a glance at Alfred)</stage> Pray take a chair! <stage>(Alfred sits L. of table,
        L.)</stage> Now I—the fact is <stage>(suddenly)</stage> An experienced officer like yourself
       must be aware I did not send to you for nothing!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Of course I were.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(R.)</stage>
      <p>I beg pardon.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(L.)</stage>
      <p>I say I were—I were aware—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, I see But suppose, before entering on business, we take a bit of something, and a glass
       of something else, eh?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>With all my heart! <stage>(aside)</stage> He's jolly civil! It's no go, though, I know his
       motive—he'll get nothing out of me. <stage>(Floff pours and hands him a glass of
        wine)</stage> Here's my duty to you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Can anything be more evident? "His duty to me!" he would imply, of course, that, if
       adequately remunerated, he is ready to sacrifice for me his duty. <stage>(aloud)</stage>
       Thank you—I see what you mean.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>I thought you would by the look of you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Now your duty is off your mind, let us come to the matter at once. I know why you are
       here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>So do I—because you sent for me. <stage>(aside)</stage> Take the change out of that, old
       boy, the ha'pence won't trouble you much.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Then let's come to the point.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Fire away!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Don't—I mean I suppose you would not mind waiting for twenty-four hours or so.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Where? what for?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Why, you know—I—I—remarked you from that window.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Did you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Yes!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Well, ain't I obliged to pass the house?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>But you are not obliged to stop and examine every brick in it, and then it is no use
       denying it—towards you personally I feel no animosity. As for your superiors, I pledge you my
       word they shall never hear anything about it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>He's a queer gent. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Well, it's no use making a fuss it's only a case
       of suspension, after all.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Don't—don't talk like that! <stage>(shouting)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>It would not be for long.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>If it were only for five minutes, it would be too much. Come, now, for a consideration
        <stage>(they get closer)</stage> for a good round sum—you wouldn't mind shutting your
       eyes—in fact, winking.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="14"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>He is a rum card—I begin to think a bit of his thatch is off. <stage>(aloud)</stage> You
       want me to wink! there! <stage>(shuts his eyes first—then opens them and winks)</stage> Will
       that do?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Don't trifle with my tenderest feelings! How much?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>For what?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Why this affected ignorance? the price of your silence for twenty-four hours.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Then it's nothing about me and Mary. But what is it about? <stage>(aloud)</stage> Well,
        I—<stage>(aside)</stage> I'll say five and sixpence—that won't hurt him.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Will twenty pounds do?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Now none of that! What do you take me for?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(eagerly)</stage>
      <p>Well, then, thirty—I'm not particular about a tenner.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>No more am I, so suppose we say forty. <stage>(aside)</stage> I see it all now—he wants a
       keeper.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(eagerly)</stage>
      <p>Very well—will that be enough?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(aloud)</stage>
      <p>Don't be in too great a hurry, Alfred. If he <hi>is</hi> mad, it ain't no fault o' your'n.
        <stage>(aloud)</stage> Well, you see, forty pounds—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Yes!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Is forty pounds—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Ah!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>I don't want to be hard on you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(embracing him)</stage>
      <p>Oh, thank you—thank you!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>But, if you'd make it a trifle more, I might retire from the Force and set up a private
       inquiry office of my own—I've a good nose for that sort of thing—and I don't mind telling
       you, at this very moment, I've a very nice little case on hand.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, a nice little case!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>This very morning at Mr. Gloss's—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>How delicately he shows me that he knows all, without compromising himself.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>The tailor.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, yes! <stage>(hysterically)</stage> I dare say it shocked you a good deal.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Not a bit of it—I'm used to such cases. We've lots on 'em. You don't see half in the
       papers—we keep 'em out. If we was to put 'em all in, there'd be no room for anything else. I
       see you are not so used to this game as I am!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I am not—I give you my word I am not. My dear sir, say no more, but name your sum.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>I must have half an hour to consider.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="15"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Half-an-hour—wouldn't ten minutes do?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Never you worrit yourself, I'm in no hurry—I ain't off duty till eight o'clock, and I'm
       very comfortable here. By the bye, just get some more of that wine. See, this is a dead man!
        <stage>(taking up bottle, which is empty—rises)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(rising and shuddering)</stage>
      <p>Ah, yes! I'll soon bring him to life again, though. <stage>(aside)</stage> I wish I could
       do the same in another case. <stage>(going towards, R. D.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>I say, just bring it in the garden, will you? and if you've a pipe, I should not mind doing
       a bit of smoke.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>All right! <stage>Exit, R. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>All right—I believe you it is all right. I shall make a tidy day's work on it—I shall. This
       comes of a man having his wits about him. I saw his motive in a jiffey—he's mad—mad as a
       march hare—and I'm the only person as has found it out. Ah, ah! trust me for seeing as far as
       most people into a brick wall.</p>
      <stage>Exit window, R.</stage>

     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Mrs. Floff, window, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking round)</stage>
      <p>Why, where is Percival? gone again!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Floff, R. D., with bottle of wine and long pipe in his hand..</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, Euphemia! the very person I wanted. Take this bottle of wine and pipe to the gentleman
       in the garden.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>What gentleman, my dear?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(pointing through window, L.)</stage>
      <p>The gentleman—the gentleman—with the bright buttons in blue.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>The policeman! <stage>(crosses R.—looking out of window, R.)</stage> Percival, what is the
       meaning of this? are you mad?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>No—yes—I can't say. Do as I bid you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! there's something I do not understand—some-thing horrid!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Who told you so ? no, no, it's only a little joke—a trifling wager of a thousand
       pounds.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>What, with a policeman?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>He– he's –not a policeman.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>What is he, then?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Why, he's—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Yes!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Gentlemen do such things sometimes. He's made a wager that he would be a policeman for a
       week, and have the run of ten kitchens, and five cooks in love with him, and he's nearly
       won—he's told me all—he's a lord.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="16"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>A lord!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Yes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>I thought there was something peculiar about him.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>So there is, my dear.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>I have been so mistaken in him! now I understand many things I formerly saw in the wrong
       light. Oh! tell me all!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I will, shortly—to-morrow or next year, or some other approximate period. But take him the
       wine, and oblige her poor, kind, gentle husband by being quick about it. <stage>Hurries her
        violently out through window.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>When will all this end? how will all this end? I am particularly anxious about the "how!"
       Why does not Consols forward the money? <stage>Enter Sidney Jubkins, L. D.</stage>
       <stage>(R.)</stage> What do you want? I thought you were in the garden!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(L.)</stage>
      <p>I was! I've had such a scene with Mrs. Jubkins. It ended by my going out by the garden gate
       at the back and coming round by the front.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Sneaking round, you mean—use the right expression.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Mrs. J. insisted on my taking her to the Palace, and sent me to call a cab.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Well, you don't expect to find a cab here, do you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>No, I wanted to know what I am to do.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Nothing, and do it at once. <stage>(pushing him towards L. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>So I will, but <stage>(hesitating)</stage> I think, perhaps, I had better get the cab
       first.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>You will do no such thing.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Come—I—I—won't be bullied by—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! do you forget you are my accomplice?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, but—but—Mrs. Jubkins—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Never mind her. <stage>(suddenly)</stage> When did you regulate your watch?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I don't know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>He don't know when he regulated his watch! Then it must want looking after. I want to know
       if mine is right, that I may be in time for the train to catch the American mail steamer.
       Just walk to the electric clock opposite Hungerford Market. Mind! walk! and, when you return,
       I'll tell you what to do next.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>But consider—</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="17"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Miscreant don't ruffle me! <stage>(seizes bottle, which he is about to hurl at Jubkins's
        head—Exit Jubkins quickly, L. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>How great is the power of calm reason!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Mrs. Floff, hurriedly, R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(R.)</stage>
      <p>Oh, Percival dear!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(L.)</stage>
      <p>What is it, Mrs. P. !</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>That policeman—your friend, I mean—is so strange—so free!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>He's a child of nature.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Then nature has neglected his education. I think he's rather the worse for wine—but—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Percival.</speaker>
      <p>But what?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, I don't like to tell you. Promise that you won't be angry—that you won't—won't fly
       out!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Not possessing wings, I promise I will not.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Well, then, he has been making love to me—there, don't storm.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(very calmly)</stage>
      <p>Reason tells me to despise such trifles. </p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>He actually put his arm round my waist. </p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>It's only his playfulness, in conjunction with the general custom of the aristocracy.
       There, go and—and—talk gently to him.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>But what is worse, he has been kissing Mrs. Jubkins.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>That's Jubkins's business.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>And I must say, since Mrs. Jubkins knows he's a nobleman she seems to like it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, you told her he was a swell? Why, it was a secret.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Was it ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, but it's always the same. When a woman is not strong enough to keep a secret herself,
       she fancies she may succeed better by getting a friend to help her. But don't stand talking
       here. Go immediately and rejoin my—my friend.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, Percival, I'm off! <stage>Exit through window, R. U. E.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Where can that idiot, Consols, be so long? Ah! I hear footsteps on the stairs. It is he
       with the money.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Jubkins, L. D.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>What! you here again? I thought I told you—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(L.)</stage>
      <p>Yes, I know, but I thought it might be better to do as Mrs. J. desired, and so, I got a
       cab. It's waiting outside.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="18"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(R.)</stage>
      <p>Let it wait.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, but it's two shillings an hour.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Pay it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, but I had better go and tell Polly. <stage>(crosses, going towards door,
       R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>You will do no such thing. <stage>(laying hold of the tail of his coat.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking off, R. window—he suddenly starts and exclaims)</stage>
      <p>Why, look there! that fellow, the policeman, is running after Mrs. Floff. Do you approve of
       such goings-on?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(seizing him by the throat, forces him in chair, R.)</stage>
      <p>How dare you ask such a question?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Then why do you allow it?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Unhappy wretch! that person in buttons is the bloodhead—no, I mean blue hound, on our
       track. I wish to divert his attention—to fill up his leisure till my broker sends the money,
       and then—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>But you might find some other means of filling up his leisure besides permitting him to
       behave thus to your wife.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, that's nothing!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Nothing!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>No, nothing, compared with what he's been doing with yours.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>With mine?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, with yours!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>This is infamous! I will bear it no longer! Why, <stage>(pointing through window,
        R.)</stage> just look there he's kissing her—why don't she scream?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Because she likes it!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(struggling)</stage>
      <p>Let me go—let me go!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(holding him)</stage>
      <p>Just leave them alone.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, nonsense! <stage>(struggles)</stage> I will go!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(holding him)</stage>
      <p>What do you mean? if I submit to see him run after Mrs. Floff, what right have you to
       complain of any little act of playfulness evinced towards Mrs. Jubkins!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(pointing)</stage>
      <p>Look there! why, now he's kissing her again—I can't bear to look at it!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Then turn your head the other way.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I—I—won't put up with it. <stage>(struggles, and suddenly breaking away from Floff rushes
        out window, R., Floff leans against the back of a chair, thoroughly exhausted.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>My strength can stand no more—I hear some one! it's the broker with my money.
       <pb n="19"/><stage>Enter Mary, L. D.</stage> No, it isn't. Ah, Mary, has anyone called? Has
       Mr. Consols sent?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>No, sir, he ain't.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>When he does—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>P'raps you'd better tell Susan what to do when he does, as I may not be here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Not be here! you appear agitated. What is the matter? Has—the—the—Governor of Newgate—no, I
       don't mean that!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, it's nothing, Mr. Floff, only I wanted to have a word with you, sir. I have come to
       give you warning to quit.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>There –be calm—be calm.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, sir, I will be calm. <stage>(growing more and more excited)</stage> Do you know, sir,
       what's a going on in that garden? <stage>(rattling on without stopping an instant)</stage>
       Because I am only a poor girl, as has got feelings, and—I—I—<stage>(sobbing)</stage>—can't
       stand it any longer—there's my Alfred Charles—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Your Alfred Charles?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>It's no use disguising on it; and now I know why missus has always been a watching him so
       closely whenever he came near here to see me, which I am free to confess—just like a cat a
       watching of a mouse—she ought to be ashamed of herself, she ought!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Mary—Mary, your emotion runs away with you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>I've seen her. He could not come near the place but what I was sure of seeing her head over
       the blind in the parlour. Oh, it <hi>was</hi> a blind. I know now why she liked to look at
       him—so she is fonder of Alfred Charles Mutton than she ought to be!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Nonsense! yet if it were true— She fond of Mutton! you don't mean to insinuate—but
       no—impossible! if you knew all—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>What! do you know any more, and take it so quietly?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>You misunderstand me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>I've been looking at 'em out of the staircase window—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Hush! your mistress may have had her reasons.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>Of course! she likes him!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, mind what you say!</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="20"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>And so does mother Jubkins, too.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Nonsense!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>It's a shame a horrid shame. What needs have you to make him come up here, a filling of him
       with wine, when he was quite contented with the kitchen, and the run of the beer barrel
        <stage>(stops suddenly)</stage> that is—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>That accounts for the rapid consumption of my Allsopp. But let me banish from my mind my
       weekly bills. <stage>(aside)</stage> Euphemia—my Euphemia—a—a—watching him like a cat!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking into garden)</stage>
      <p>Ah, look there! oh, the hussy! Give me my wages, sir, and let me go.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Mary, there is a mystery—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking round)</stage>
      <p>Where?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>In my breast—in the breast of your unfortunate master. Retract your resolution. Wait only
       for four-and-twenty hours.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>No!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>For twelve!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>Not an instant! I will go and tell them what I think—I will scratch their eyes out!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Defer the execution of your threat till—till— <stage>(aside)</stage> I have got off!
        <stage>(aloud)</stage> Mary, you are a good, respectable girl!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>I ain't!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Well, then, you ain't. <stage>(takes her hand)</stage> Mary! <stage>(looks imploringly in
        her face.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>What, are you beginning too?</p>
      <stage>Breaks from him, and rushes out, L. D.</stage>
     </sp>

     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I must stop her! Mary—Mary! If she insults that detective I am lost. <stage>Rushes out
        after her, L. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>

     <stage>Enter MUTTON, window, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(the worse for liquor though not drunk)</stage>
      <p>This is a rum place! I've left 'em in the garden having a nice row. Ain't the large one's
       husband a catchin' it neither? my eye ! <stage>(retires up.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Percival pulling in Mary, L. D.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>Don't, sir—let me go. <stage>(MUTTON turns round)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I won't—I won't! Let me beg—let me supplicate—let me beseech—I will even say, let me ask
       you to be quiet. <stage>(goes on his knees)</stage> Say nothing to Alfred Charles—and
       anything in my power to do for you I will.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="21"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(coming down, C., and pushing Floff away)</stage>
      <p>Halloa!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <stage>(L.—screams)</stage>
      <p>Ah!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(getting up)</stage>
      <p>My dear sir—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Don't talk to me! <stage>(aside)</stage> He ain't mad! I see his motive now—he's after my
       Mary—that's it, is it? <stage>(aloud)</stage> You're a nice party! What will your wife say
       when I tell her all?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Don't—lock it up in your own manly breast. <stage>(goes up, sits at table, R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(turning to Mary)</stage>
      <p>As for you, Mary, I blush for you!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>Blush for yourself, Mr. Mutton– and you'll have quite enough to do.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>What! talk to me like that, when I saw him at your feet?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>Suppose you did! what then? I saw <hi>you</hi> when I was a watching of you in the
       garden.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(with drunken solemnity)</stage>
      <p>Hush! respect his feelings. <stage>(pointing to Floff.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>But go on, I've done with you—I despise you. Don't imagine I am speaking in a passion. I've
       done with you for ever. I was never calmer in my life—never; so there now. <stage>Slaps his
        face and exit L. D., hurriedly.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>My eye! she's left her mark, at any rate. <stage>(goes towards L. D., rubbing his
        cheek.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Can it be? he after my wife, as well as me; but I will put an end to this! <stage>(aloud,
        coming down to Alfred)</stage> Mr. Mutton, a word with you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, that reminds me I—I—ain't going to stand this—I shall arrest you. <stage>(pulls out his
        staff)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>I must temporize. <stage>(aloud)</stage> You can't be serious!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Ain't I?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>But w—h—a—t for?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>You know well enongh—come along. <stage>(advances to capture him)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Wait! stop! <stage>(dodging him about)</stage> I—I can assure you it was done
       unintentionally.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Pooh!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>On my honour as a gentleman, it was—I—I was coming quietly home.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Coming quietly home! What's that to do with Mary?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Nothing!</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="22"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Well, then, if you think you can carry on these pranks with a young girl—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>It was a man.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(with drunken astonishment)</stage>
      <p>A man!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Yes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>That <hi>won't</hi> do.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Well, if it was a girl, she had on a coat and trousers.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>When?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Last night.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>He <hi>is</hi> mad! <stage>(aloud)</stage> Come, come, you're dangerous you ought to have
       been under lock and key long ago, it's my duty to take you, and I will! <stage>(pursues Floff
        round room, and at last collars him, ending Floff, L.—Alfred, R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>No, no—will a hundred do?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>A hundred pounds?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Yes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Money down?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Yes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Where is it?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(giving him notes)</stage>
      <p>There, count them?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>I mean to. <stage>(leaves go of Floff—goes to table, R., and counts notes)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking at him)</stage>
      <p>Reprobate! oh, Phemy, if ever I meet him in New York—which I never shall—he shall have
       cause to remember it!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Mrs. Floff, Mrs. Jubkins, and Jubkins, window, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Floff!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Floff! <stage>(very loud)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Percival!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Speak all at once, and then I shall hear you better.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>I have been insulted, sir, and Mr. Jubkins demands satisfaction. Mr. Jubkins, you demand
       satisfaction, don't you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, my dear, <stage>(looking imploringly at Floff)</stage> That is <stage>(to Mrs.
        Jubkins)</stage> Perhaps, my dear, that person, <stage>(points to Alfred)</stage> did not
       mean any harm, after all.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Was not I told he was a lord, and did not he keep up the imposition, kissing me and going
       on just like one, till your servant Mary came and told me, in very coarse language, the
       truth.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside, and with a bewildered air)</stage>
      <p>I'm in a fog! I a lord! What can be their motive? it is –it must be—this is a private
       madhouse, or an Agapemone.</p>
      <note type="ed">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agapemonites</note>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(weeping)</stage>
      <p>Oh, Percival!</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="23"/>
     <stage>Enter Mary, L. D., with her bonnet on, and a bundle in her hand.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>I'm going—I only want my wages.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. G.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Floff, that person—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>I'm no more a person than you are, mum.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Don't talk to me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>Why did you encourage Alfred Charles Mutton ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p><hi>I</hi> encourage him!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>He's as good as the guy you have got, and you seemed to think him <hi>rather</hi>
       better.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Is that the way in which you address a lady?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>No—I've got another way for a lady!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Jubkins, I—I order you to turn that creature ut of the room.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Jubkins.</speaker>
      <p>But, my dear—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Jubkins! <stage>(retires up)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Mary, go!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>I shan't!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Then I <stage>(mildly)</stage> shall turn you out!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p><hi>You</hi> turn her out! wait a moment! <stage>(brandishes his staff and crosses to
        Jubkins.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I can't bear this any longer—I will not bear it any longer. I—I—order you to leave the
       room. <stage>(to Mary)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>You! you did not talk so just now, when I found you alone with her, a kneeling at her
       feet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>What! my Percival at her feet! then this is why you sent me into the garden. Oh dear! oh
       dear! <stage>(falls in a chair, R., and faints—Mrs. Jubkins goes to her.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>See what you have done, you monster! and this, Mr. Jubkins, is the man you call your
       friend.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I, my dear—no, that is, yes. <stage>(aside)</stage> What shall I. do?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>This is the finishing blow—lead me to the scaffold, and have done with it. I will reveal
       the name of my accomplice.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside to him)</stage>
      <p>Floff!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Or rather of the principal.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside to him)</stage>
      <p>Percival, I am your friend.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>And, before I do so, I will have some little satisfaction—I'll fight you. <stage>(to
        Sidney)</stage> Come on. <stage>(dances up, sparingly to him)</stage> Come on!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>No, no—don't. <stage>(round to R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to Alfred)</stage>I give him in charge.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>No, no—let 'em have it out. <stage>(gets on chair)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>I will report you—I will. <stage>(to Sidney)</stage> Why don't
       <pb n="24"/>you vindicate your honour? Don't suffer this—hit him—hit him hard. <stage>(pushes
        Sidney forward—he spars Percival round to R.—Percival dances round Sidney, who feebly makes
        a show of self-defence)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <stage>(starting up, down L. of Percival)</stage>
      <p>My husband in danger! I will protect you. <stage>(throws herself round his
       neck)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Come away, ma'am. <stage>(tries to remove Mrs. Floff.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <stage>(crosses to Mrs. Jubkins)</stage>
      <p>You shan't touch my missus, whatever has happened.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Come, come! <stage>(goes and tries to pull away Mary)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Holloa! you leave her alone though she did smack my face, I loved her once.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I won't.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>You won't? Then I shall take you. <stage>(round him to R.)</stage> And you. <stage>(General
        mêlée—Mrs. Floff faints again, R. chair, and is imitated by MRS Jubkins, L. chair, and Mary
        C. chair—the MEN stand gazing at each other, and panting from exertion—street door bell
        rings—pause)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>There's the bell!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>We hear it! <stage>(going to window, L., and looking out)</stage> A man with a couple of
       rifles, and a large bag! Cook has let him in!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Oh!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Ah!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>It's all up with me! <stage>(catches hold of table)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>I'm not well. <stage>(supports himself on a chair)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking at them in amazement, and aside)</stage>
      <p>I think I see their motive. <stage>(all the WOMEN have got up)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Percival, my own, what is this?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(in a weak voice)</stage>
      <p>Brandy—brandy! <stage>(a loud single rap at the door, L.—Percival tries to get under the
        table, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>There is a knock at the door. Come in!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>No! <stage>(door opens)</stage> Ah, it's all over! <stage>Enter Pad, with two rifles, and a
        carpet bag, L. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>Good morning, ladies and gentlemen—I—<stage>(gazes round him in astonishment and all,
        except Percival and Sidney, look at him)</stage> I trust I don't intrude?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Oh, don't you!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>If you are engaged—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>No—merely a nice little family party.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="25"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <stage>(to Percival)</stage>
      <p>I think I had better say what I have to say to you alone. <stage>(goes up, and gets round
        to R. Puts rifles and bag on table, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Euphemia, retire.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>But, Percival—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(violently)</stage>
      <p>Retire. <stage>(she goes L.)</stage> Mrs. Jubkins, will you also oblige me?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F6">
      <speaker>Mrs. J.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Jubkins, do you permit this?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I don't care, ma'am, whether he does or no. <stage>(snatches staff from Alfred)</stage> Go!
        <stage>(brandishes staff)</stage> I am desperate, reckless—away! <stage>The WOMEN exeunt
        through L. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Come, I say. <stage>(snatches staff from Percival—aside)</stage> But I'll go after the
       women—it don't matter, we can hear it all through the keyhole, or gimlet a horifice through
       the door and look. <stage>Exit, L. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(catching hold of the tail of Sidney's coat, as Jubkins is sneaking after them,</stage>
      <p>No, you don't– we want you. Lock the door.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(going up to L. D.)</stage>
      <p>There's no key.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Lean against it then. If you let in a soul, I'll murder you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Don't go on like that! <stage>(leans against L. D.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I will—I—I—I'm a tiger. <stage>(to Pad—faintly)</stage> Now, sir, proceed.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <stage>(down, R.)</stage>
      <p>My name is Pad, sir—Pad! Mr. Gloss's foreman.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Oh!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>I have come from Mr. Gloss, who is prevented from coming himself—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>I should rather think so.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>Of course I need not refer to what took place last night? <stage>(Sidney, with his back
        against L. D., pushing very hard, but sliding continually, as if from the force exerted
        against it on the outside)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, they are pushing so!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Gloss was greatly hurt.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>I've no doubt of it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>He felt exceedingly warm about it at first.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>He's cold enough now.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>We found these rifles, Nos. 20 and 21, and 21 is discharged.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>That's my rifle. We are prepared for all! <stage>(pushing, L. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I am not. Speak for yourself.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>We need not let any one know a syllable about it.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="26"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(shoving against L. D.)</stage>
      <p>Oh, I can't keep them out much longer.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Well, but—the—the body! What will you do with that?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, that will do again.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Do again?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>Or we might burn it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Where?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>Anywhere—in the back kitchen; unless it would be of any use to you. Mr. Gloss said
       that—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Gloss said <stage>(bewildered, and speaking slowly)</stage> Wait—let me go through some
       abstruse mental calculation—twice two are four—three times four are twelve—twelve pence are
       one shilling—sixteen pence are one and sixpence. I am in possession of all my
       faculties—proceed.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>We have no wish to impose on you, and therefore, I have brought the head for your
       inspection.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_mult">
      <speaker>Sidney. | Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Whose head?</p>
     </sp>

     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>The head you put a ball in last night.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! <stage>(sliding from door, but recovering himself frantically)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>What, his—his—his head?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>Well, yes, it was his, but—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Was his! Ah, I understand. Why—why did you bring it here?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>He sent it for you to look at.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Who sent it to me to look at?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Gloss.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>If I ain't mad, you are the damndest liar that ever lived.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>Sir, my name is Pad! I am not a liar at least, not out of business I have brought the head
       in that bag, and I will show it you. <stage>(fetches bag, which he endeavours to open
        struggle between him and Percival)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(suddenly starting, and putting his hand behind him)</stage>
      <p>Ah. what's that? A gimlet!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Jubkins, you fool, why don't you come and help me? <stage>(Sidney leaves door, and rushes
        to Percival.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Door is immediately thrown open, and Mrs. Floff, Mrs. Jubkins, Mary, and Alfred, rush
      precipitately in.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(showing a gimlet</stage>That's what did it. <stage>(Percival and Sidney struggle
        with Pad, R.—in the midst of the contest, the head rolls on the floor)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="27"/>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! <stage>(starts off in the greatest horror to R. D., but rushes into the arms of Alfred,
        who pushes him back to his place)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Softly!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>I call this most ungentlemanly. I'm sure ten pounds is not such a large sum!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking up)</stage>
      <p>Ten pounds!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M4">
      <speaker>Pad.</speaker>
      <p>And considering it's the best wax—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>Wax! <stage>(looks at the head)</stage> Oh! <stage>(dives into his pockets, and pulls out
        the newspaper)</stage> Let me see. <stage>(reads)</stage> "Last night —dum—dum—dummy."
       Dummy! Huzza, Jubkins! It was a dummy, after all! <stage>(throws paper to Sidney)</stage>
       Huzza! <stage>(jumps about, and embraces Mrs. Floff, Mrs. Jubkins, and Mary—is about to
        embrace Alfred, but starts back)</stage> No, no—not you!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <p>Just as you like I shan't grieve! <stage>(aside)</stage> I knew it—dash my buttons, I knew
       it all along! I says to myself, says I "That's the chap as smashed the dummy." I was up to
       his motive, I was!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M2">
      <speaker>Sidney.</speaker>
      <stage>(having glanced over paper)</stage>
      <p>Thanks—thanks! We are not assassins! <stage>(kisses Mrs. Jubkins frantically)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M3">
      <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>He was in it too, was he? I knew it. Never mind, I'm all right—I know what he meant now.
       Well, I've a good capital for my private inquiry office!—a hundred pounds and a gimlet!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F7">
      <speaker>Mary.</speaker>
      <p>And a wife.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_F5">
      <speaker>Mrs. F.</speaker>
      <p>Let this be a lesson, Percival, dear—don't go shooting dummies any more.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0623_M1">
      <speaker>Perci.</speaker>
      <p>I won't promise—for we don't know what sort of dummies may come in our way—especially those
       that might try to effect a landing somewhere. To them we should be happy to give a lesson,
       and prove that Englishmen will very soon, thank goodness, know something about THE RIFLE, AND
       HOW TO USE IT.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>CURTAIN.</stage>
    </div>

    <trailer>Printed by T. Blower, 3, Black Horse Court, Fleet Street.</trailer>
   </div>
  </body>

 </text>
</TEI>
