<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L0664" xml:lang="en">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>PORK CHOPS, or A DREAM AT HOME : TEI edition</title>
    <author ref="lacyp:W0035"><persName>Blanchard, E.L.</persName><idno type="wikidata"
      >Q5344152</idno></author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>TEI conversion</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor>
    <idno type="LAE">L0664</idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives
      all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which it believes to be in the public
      domain. You may copy, modify, distribute, or perform this work freely. </licence>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="originalSource" n="45.4"><author>Blanchard, E.L.</author>
     <title type="main" n="porkchopsoradreamatho...">Pork Chops; or, A Dream at Home</title>
     <title type="sub">A Farcical Extravaganza furnished with a Dramatic Scene by Mr. W.R. Beverley
      and a Musical Sauce by Mr. Caulcott in one act</title>
     <extent>11 pp (UM copy: 106 - 117)<measure type="pp" quantity="10"/>
      <measure type="spCount" quantity="142"/>
      <measure type="spvCount" quantity="0"/>
      <measure type="txWords" quantity="3388"/>
      <measure type="spWords" quantity="2810"/>
      <measure type="stWords" quantity="578"/>
     </extent>
     <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 45, No. 0664</title><idno type="nic"
      >N00465</idno></bibl>
    <bibl type="surrogate"><ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/iau.31858024123287"
      >Hathi_Trust</ref></bibl>
    <bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref
      target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453541&amp;seq=106 ">UM from
      HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol45/L0664/L0664-um.pdf"/></bibl>
    <listEvent>
     <event type="firstPerf" when="1843-02-13" source="textNic" where="Olympic">
      <desc>Premiered at Royal Olympic Theatre 13 Feb. 1843</desc>
     </event>
    </listEvent>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <!--S 1 ExtravaganDramaMusic Ext. SPECTACLE-->
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#sizeS"/>
    <catRef target="#act1"/>
    <catRef target="nic:Ext."/>
    <keywords>
     <term>SPECTACLE</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
   <particDesc>
    <listPerson>
     <person xml:id="L0664_M1">
      <persName type="role">SEPTIMUS SNOOKS, a Gentleman connected with the
       Press—vulgo—Penny-a-liner—with the “Life of a Vagabond.”</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="64">Snooks.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0664_M2">
      <persName type="role">DARKEYE DABBS, a returned Convict, and Professor of
       Housebreaking</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="39">Dabbs.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0664_M3">
      <persName type="role">PHIL PILFER, (alias Paddington Phil) once a Conductor to a Paddington
       Omnibus and now a follower of Darkeye Dabbs</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="8">Phil.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0664_F4">
      <persName type="role">MISS CHIPPINGTON CHUBB, daughter to her mother, and heiress apparent to
       the house of her parent</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="26">Miss C.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="2">Miss Chubb.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0664_mult">
      <persName type="role">[Multiple speakers]</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">All.</persName>
     </person>
    </listPerson>
   </particDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2026-02-27">Add wikidata link to titleStmt where possible</change>
   <change when="2023-05-19">Header confected</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text>


  <front>
   <titlePage>
    <titlePart type="main">PORK CHOPS, or A DREAM AT HOME </titlePart>
    <titlePart>A Farcical Extravaganza </titlePart>
    <titlePart> furnished with a Dramatic Scene by Mr. W.R. Beverley and a Musical Sauce by Mr.
     Caulcott </titlePart>
    <titlePart>in one act</titlePart>
    <byline>by <docAuthor>E. L. Blanchard</docAuthor> Esq. author of <title>The Roads of Life
      —</title><title>The Artful Dodger—</title><title>Angels and Lucifers</title> &amp;c. &amp;c.
     &amp;c.</byline>
    <docImprint>London, Thomas Hailes Lacy, 89 Strand, W.C., (Opposite Southamlpton Street, Covent
     Gardeb Market)</docImprint>
   </titlePage>
   <pb n="2"/>
   <performance>
    <head>Pork Chops</head>
    <p>First performed at the Royal Olympic Theatre, February 13, 1843.</p>
    <castList>
     <head>Characters</head>
     <castItem><role gender="M">SEPTIMUS SNOOKS, a Gentleman connected with the
       Press—vulgo—Penny-a-liner—with the “Life of a Vagabond.”</role><actor>Mr. G.
      Wild.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">DARKEYE DABBS, a returned Convict, and Professor of
       Housebreaking</role><actor>Mr. Searle.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">PHIL PILFER, (alias Paddington Phil) once a Conductor to a
       Paddington Omnibus and now a follower of Darkeye Dabbs</role><actor>Mr.
      Rogers.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="F">MISS CHIPPINGTON CHUBB, daughter to her mother, and heiress apparent
       to the house of her parent</role><actor>Miss Hamilton.</actor></castItem>
    </castList>
   </performance>
   <div type="programme">
    <head>Startling incidents</head>
    <p>The Garret—The Supper—The Passage—The Staircase—The Murder— The Poisoning—the————The
     Denouement.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="costume">
    <list>
     <item>
      <label>Snooks.</label>—Shabby genteel modern dress—check trousers—white hat.
       <label>Dabbs</label>.—Picturesque melodramatic ruffian's dress of modern style.
       <label>Pilfer</label>.—Fancy sporting suit—very shabby. <label>Miss Chubb</label>.—Ordinary
      chambermaid's dress.</item>
    </list>
   </div>

   <pb n="3"/>
   <div type="liminal">
    <p>The Author of this little quiz upon the extravagances of the transpontine melodrama, is well
     aware how much he was indebted for its favourable reception to the talent displayed by the
     original performers who figured in the cast. The piece was one of his earliest contributions to
     the stage, and enjoyed the advantages of the scenic illusions provided by Mr. William Beverly,
     the genial humour of Mr. George Wild, the excellent acting of Mr. William Searle, and the
     admirable artistic, performance of Mr. James Rogers, who ingeniously expanded a small part into
     a very important one. It is with pleasure that he thus gratefully acknowledges their valuable
     assistance, and thanks them for the success which the farce attained on the boards of the Old
     Olympic Theatre.</p>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>

   <div type="scene">
    <head>SCENE FIRST. </head>
    <stage>—A Garret. Practicable window in flat, backed by tiles, with curtain drawn—bed, table,
     two chairs— carpet, fender—fireplace, L.—door, R.—wash stand, jug, basin —small cupboard in
     flat, with plate, knife and fork, mustard pot, bottle, and teacup in—two pork chops at the
     fire—coat over chair, white hat on nail—pipes and screw of tobacco on shelf—broken bit of
     looking glass—old candlestick and candle lighted—pen, ink, and newspapers, with letters
     manifold, &amp;c.</stage>
    <stage>Septimus Snooks discovered at table writing by the light of a small candle.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Fourteen lines, one and ninepence. Come, there's a breakfast for some day next week, at all
      events! Let me see how it reads. “Singular and Remarkable Accident. Yesterday afternoon,
      between the hours of one and six, as a gentleman, named Brown.” Brown! Thank goodness there
      are plenty of Browns! “was proceeding in his chaise along Oxford Street—” Capital street
      that—there's no knowing at which end things <hi>do</hi> occur! “the off wheel came, horrible
      to relate, against the birch broom of the street sweeper opposite, and such was the violence
      of the concussion, that the broom was immediately snapped in two, and the handle flying
      upwards, knocked the unfortunate gentleman off his seat into the window of a china shop next
      door—at the same instant, the horse and chaise took fright, in consequence of a little boy
      mischievously making faces, and dashed off at a rapid speed into the kitchen of—Smith, Esq.,
      to the astonishment of the cook, who was frying pancakes at the time, and whose alarm may be
      much better conceived than described. The horse and chaise were
      <pb n="4"/> extricated with great difficulty, and Mr. Brown resumed him journey with only the
      loss of his temper. The making-face nuisance we strongly recommend the police to look after.”
      So there's the result of my penny-a-lining for to-night, and now to send this romantic novel,
      in one paragraph, to the morning newspapers—I can't go myself for certain very peculiar
      reasons, and— <stage>(knock at door, R. 3 E.)</stage> That's somebody at the door. Now I
      shouldn't wonder if it is that persevering landlady of mine, who has the audacity to want some
      money! Come in!</p>
     <stage>Enter Miss Chubb, cautiously, L. D.</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Are you there, Mr. Snooks?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, it's you, my dear. Yes, I am here, and I wish I wasn't—you come, I believe, for your
      little account?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Why, my mother—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Ah, I know. Dutiful daughter—and couldn't refuse—wished to avoid the disagreeable
      task—obliged to undertake it! You look more pretty to-night than ever, Miss Chubb.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Thankye, sir—but if you'd be pleased to settle—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>So I do settle. I settle my affections upon you, and isn't that sufficient?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Why, sir, the bill has been so long standing—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>That you want it <hi>re-seated</hi>, eh? But if you will wait until to-morrow—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>My mother, Mr. Snooks, said I was not to go till a was properly balanced, and therefore, I
      can't wait.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Then tell your mother Mr. Snooks says it can't be properly <hi>balanced without
      waits</hi>.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>But this week's rent is also due, Mr. Snooks.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>I know it is—and being due it becomes nothing for <hi>dew</hi> is vapour, and vapour in air,
      and air is nothing—at least <hi>that air</hi>. However, here is that which will produce money.
       <stage>(takes paper from table)</stage> Send these round to the newspapers as directed, for
      me, and a grateful heart—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, Mr. Snooks, I can refuse you nothing—you will pay us to-morrow?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>To be sure I will. Good night, Miss Chubb.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Good night, Mr. Snooks!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Fare thee well, and if for ever—</p>
     <stage>(kisses her hand)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, what a nice young man he is to be sure!</p>
     <stage>                                        Exit at door, L.</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Making love's the cheapest thing, after all! Now for supper! Two pork chops, the remainder
      of to-day's dinner. Indigestible, very—but tempting exceedingly. If there is one
      <pb n="5"/> thing I have a partiality for more than another, it is a pork chop. One good turn
      deserves another. </p>
     <stage>(turns them)</stage>
     <p> Talking of turns, what turns, I've had to be sure! what a life I've led! </p>
    </sp>
    <spGrp>
     <head>SONG.—(Introduced)—“Life of a Vagabond.”</head>
     <sp who="#L0664_M1">
      <p><!-- song lyrics and associated patter missing from original --></p>
     </sp>
    </spGrp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <p> Now, then, to see about supper, and to lay the cloth. <stage>(lays newspaper on
       table)</stage> There, that's what I call blending the ornamental with the useful! I can read
      and inwardly digest together. <stage>(goes to cupboard, fetches plate, knife, fork, teacup,
       and bottle—gets chops)</stage> I have an appetite for two, but only a knife and fork for one,
      though no friend will pop into supper I expect, and as the old joke says, “If these chops are
      not ready, I know those that are.” <stage>(eating)</stage> Done to a nicety! rather fat, but
      if they were fat, fair, and <hi>forty</hi>, my “great revenge has stomach for them all.” What
      shifts we literary men are obliged   to put up with sometimes! There am I—generalissimo of
      inquests, and purveyor-general of accidents in ordinary to the whole of the newspaper press,
      compelled to reside in this classical abode, where they do say, one Dabbs, a burglar, was
      taken—capital chops these! By the way, my last robbery turned out very productive! fourteen
      shillings is no bad week! I must have a try at a murder next. Poor Dabbs! I wonder what became
      of him? I dare say the account of his capture made two columns at the least. I'll drink his
      health. <stage>(pours from bottle into teacup)</stage> Small beer two days old.
       <stage>(drinks)</stage> I suppose they call this <hi>small</hi> beer because you can't drink
      a <hi>large</hi> quantity of it. Well, I must do the honours of the table, at all events. Mr.
      Snooks, permit me to have the honour of drinking your good health. Thank you, sir—the same to
      you. There—I wonder what sort of night it is? <stage>(draws aside curtain, discovering tiles
       by moonlight)</stage> Poor Dabbs! I should like to know whether his ghost walks on the
      housetops! <stage>(a guitar and voice heard outside)</stage> Hark! there's a ballad singer in
      the court! Well, I'm amazingly fond of music, so I shall patronise native talent. There, old
      girl, it's the last. <stage>(throws penny)</stage> And, now then to enjoy my pipe, and listen
      to hers at the same time. <stage>(fetches pipe and screw off mantelpiece)</stage> Not much of
      the weed left, I declare. Well, it certainly can't be an ill weed, for it don't grow apace.
       <stage>(Female sings a verse of “Lovely Night”)</stage> How sleepy that small beer makes one!
      Poor Dabbs! I certainly   must get up a murder—they pay best! Miss Chubb—those pork
      chops—robbery—Dabbs, the housebreaker—oh! </p>
     <stage>(Music— gradually dozes off to sleep—knocks candle down)</stage>
    </sp>
   </div>
   <div type="scene">
    <head>SCENE SECOND. </head>
    <stage>—Another Apartment in the same House.</stage>
    <stage>Enter Miss Chubbs, with bed candle.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Bless my heart, how late it is getting to be sure!
      <pb n="6"/> I must go to the arms of Morpheus, as Mr. Snooks says. By the way, that Mr. Snooks
      is a very nice young man. I don't see why mother should be so cross with him, though he does
      owe five weeks' rent—four-and-sixpence a week, and find his own blacking brushes. When a
      single young man lodger occupies a place in your heart, though, it's high time to give him
      notice to quit! Well, I suppose I must get to bed, though I dare say I shall not close my eyes
      for dreaming about Mr. Septimus Snooks. Oh, dear! love is something like the pork chops Mr.
      Snooks talked about—very nice at the time, but very apt to keep you awake o' nights.</p>
     <stage>                                        Music—Exit.</stage>
    </sp>
   </div>
   <div type="scene">
    <head>SCENE THIRD. </head>
    <stage>—Garret, as before. Fire out—moon gone down—rain—thunder.</stage>
    <stage>Snooks discovered, sleeping—lights down.</stage>
    <stage>Dabbs appears at back, making his way along the tiles—enters through window with bag,
     dark lantern, &amp;c.—Music at the opening of scene.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>So far 'tis fortunate. The thirsty gang of peelers, who would fain my carcass have, are
      baulked in their career, and I am in safety. This my swag, for which I've robbed a shopkeeper,
      who robbed the world in turn, will make me rich, and bear me to a land far from the taxed and
      taxing soil of Britain. <stage>(Snooks snores)</stage> Ah, an intruder! Let me reconnoitre.
       <stage>(Music —He surveys, with his lantern, the apartment, and at last discovers
       Snooks)</stage> Ah, a stranger! <stage>(pulls Snooks to the front of the stage)</stage> How
      came you here?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>You pulled me!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>You are a traitor!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>No, I'm a penny-a-liner!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Ah, you know then—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>I do!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>And you are—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>I am.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Whilst your name is—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Snooks.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Enough—rise!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Thank you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>You deal in robberies?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Yes—I make them.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Did you ever commit a murder?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>No, but I mean to.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>On what?</p>
     <pb n="7"/>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>  Paper.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Psha! you behold this bag?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>I do.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Take it!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>I will.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>You have received stolen goods. My name is Dabbs —Darkeye Dabbs—Dabbs the Housebreaker. Ha,
      ha! do you tremble at the sound?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Not a bit of it!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>You have good spirits!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>It has dwindled to small beer lately.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Will you join me?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, as your historian. You shall commit robberies, and I'll write them. I will give you a
      last dying speech and confession with pleasure.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>You may stand yourself in need. Suppose I <hi>split</hi>!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Then you might keep your half.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>True; but you must be fatigued, and I have a tale to tell. Let us be seated. </p>
     <stage>(they sit)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>You'll excuse my furniture. I'm not accustomed to receive company.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Listen—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>I will!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Fourteen years ago I was a housebreaker.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>That <hi>was </hi>a go!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>  A regular housebreaker—a professor of the science of crib cracking, on the same plan as
      that pursued by the late Mr. John Sheppard! </p>
     <stage>(takes off his hat)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>You don't say so!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Whilst following my professional avocations, I was a tenant occupying this very room. I at
      last left for the army!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>I see—you were a <hi>left</hi>-tenant.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>I picked pockets at the Horse Guards!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>And became yourself one of the blackguards; but proceed!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>One night, whilst here, I was asked for my rent.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Insolent audacity!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>It was an insult that I never forgave—day and night I brooded over it, and swore to be
      revenged. Time flew past, and I was invited one morning to visit the Old Bailey, on account of
      a little legal affair at which my presence was desired. As I was about to leave, a gentleman
      begged me to go abroad at the expense of the Government, to aid in the colonisation of Botany
      Bay.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>And you—</p>
     <pb n="8"/>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Consented. I was always patriotic, even in my prejudices. So I remained fourteen long years
      engaged in advancing the mercantile interest of that country. Still I forgot not the insult,
      and here I am, returned for the purpose of   accomplishing the long cherished object of my
      thoughts— revenge! </p>
     <stage>(gets up)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Wonderful being! and the purport of your visit this night?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Is to fulfil my vow, and gratify my revenge! <hi>She</hi> sleeps in the second floor. From
      that slumber she must never— <stage>(three taps on the tiles)</stage> Hark!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Did you hear anything knock? </p>
     <stage>(rain)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>It is the signal—my comrade has arrived.</p>
     <stage>Music.—Phil slides down the tiles and enters through window.</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Well, this gentleman seems to be making himself quite at home.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Allow me the pleasure of introducing a friend—this is Mr.—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Snooks!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Mr. Snooks! and this my comrade, Phil Pilfer, better known to the world as Paddington Phil.
      Hope you may be better acquainted.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M3">
     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
     <p>Your servant, sir—and the public's to command.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <stage> (aside to Dabbs)</stage>
     <p>Is this one of the profession? <stage>(Dabbs nods mysteriously)</stage> I see how it is!
      this will be quite a house of call for them before long. What a situation for a gentleman
      connected with the press.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Now, then, to business. Is all prepared?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M3">
     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
     <p>All!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>One would imagine they were going to sit down to   supper, instead of its being the
      committal of—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <stage> (hurriedly turning round)</stage>
     <p>Who talks of a committal?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Why, you surely wouldn't—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M3">
     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
     <p>But we have sworn—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Several times!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Don't doubt it! </p>
     <stage>(clock strikes three)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>The hour has arrived. To the second floor! Lead on—my victim waits me. Follow!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>I will—to watch the result. It may end in—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M3">
     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
     <p>Murder!</p>
     <stage>Puts lantern up to Snooks's face. Music.—Exeunt at door —tableau formed.</stage>
    </sp>
   </div>
   <div type="scene">
    <pb n="9"/>
    <head>SCENE FOURTH. </head>
    <stage>—A Lobby.</stage>
    <stage>Music continued—stage dark. Snooks, Phil, and Dabbs cross the stage L. and exit, R. Enter
     Miss Chubb, L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Disturbed by the sound of footsteps, I have hastened hither, and if that light misled me
      not, saw three strangers cross the landing. What can this mean? Surely some vile plot is being
      carried on—the house entered by thieves, perhaps. Should Snooks be one—but oh no! the thought
      is unworthy of him. Ah, the light proceeds—stops—goes on —no—it pauses at the staircase; and
      now the extinguisher is popped upon it—a few more paces, and I can discern their
      object—gently, gently—let me observe.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>                                        Music.—Exit cautiously, R.</stage>
   </div>
   <div type="scene">
    <head>SCENE FIFTH. </head>
    <stage>—The Staircase to lower apartment. Windows over the stairs practicable, R.</stage>
    <stage>Dabbs, Snooks, and Phil discovered on stairs—they descend. Picture.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>So! we are on the second landing. This is the most singular affair in which I was ever
      engaged. Can't you put it off, to oblige me?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Psha! you grow chicken-hearted. Drink! <stage>(producing bottle)</stage> It's brandy! hark! </p>
     <stage>(starts and drops his hat)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M3">
     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
     <p>Phoo! it's only the cats!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>I heard mysterious sounds—the very tiles seem to start from the roof!</p>
     <stage>Miss Chubb appears on staircase.</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>That is the voice of Snooks! can he be a robber?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Come, I'm in no hurry. <stage>(takes cups from bag)</stage> I'll give you a toast, and you
      give us a song.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Consider the neighbours!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M3">
     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
     <p>Phoo! what have we to do with them. Let's enjoy ourselves!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Some dreadful deed is about to be committed. Could I but gain yonder cupboard—there is
      laudanum in it, and perhaps—</p>
     <stage>                                        (she descends, goes to cupboard, and gets the
      phial—Dabbs has poured out the brandy into cup, and holds it up, R. looking at Snooks—Miss
      Chubb pours the contents of phial into the cup.</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Now, then, here's to Jerry—</p>
     <pb n="10"/>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Psha!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>No, not Shaw, but Jerry Abershaw!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>That will frustrate their murderous design, at least. </p>
     <stage>(Dabbs gives Snooks the cup, who drinks)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Here's to Jerry Abershaw! </p>
     <stage>(gives same cup to Phil)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>He has taken the poisoned goblet by mistake. All   is lost!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M3">
     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
     <stage> (drinks)</stage>
     <p>Here's to Jerry Abershaw, and our enterprise!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_mult">
     <speaker>All.</speaker>
     <p>To our enterprise! </p>
     <stage>(Dabbs drinks out of another cup)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Now then, to complete my design! As you <stage>(crosses to Phil)</stage> were once an
      omnibus conductor behind, before, go in front. Here, take this lantern, and remember to strike
      home!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>This seems a striking situation altogether.</p>
     <stage>                                        Music.—Dabbs and Phil, in melodramatic action,
      signify that they are about to commit murder, telling Snooks to follow, and exeunt.</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <stage> (runs and stops Snooks)</stage>
     <p>Not a moment is to be lost. Fly, dear Snooks, if you value my love or your own life. You are
      poisoned, and by me! The shaft which I aimed at another, has recoiled upon your own head.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Poisoned! nonsense! yet now I think again, my brain is in a whirling world—the floor is
      walking up to the ceiling, and the walls are playing at leapfrog. Oh, fatal hour of ours, to
      be poisoned, and by you, Miss Chubb. Hark! know you that in yonder chamber a dreadful deed is
      being performed.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>Think not of me—the room is empty—we have removed down stairs.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Down stairs! parlours be praised! but those dreadful men—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>One of them is poisoned, too. But run to the doctor's.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>And leave you here! never! </p>
     <stage>(noise without, L.)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>  Hark! they return! behind this staircase we may observe their movements.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>True, we must take steps to conceal ourselves.</p>
     <stage>                                        (they retire, R.)</stage>
     <stage>Music.—Dabbs enters L.</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Confusion! our prey has escaped. Follow to the garret—to the garret!</p>
     <stage>                                        Exit up staircase.</stage>
     <stage>Enter Phil Pilfer, l.</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M3">
     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
     <p>I can go no further—thoughts of the time when I was
      <pb n="11"/> a happy cad to a Paddington 'bus comes rushing o'er my mind! My brain wanders!
      “Bank! city! bank!” I'm poisoned! I feel upon my temples an—“Elephant and Castle!” Look! see
      that shadowy form in the pepper and salt unmentionables! I know you well—it's a bad sixpence.
      Ah! ha, ha, ha! </p>
     <stage>(falls)</stage>
     <p> “Going down, sir?” “Is that an umbrella that I see before me! with its hook turned towards
      this way?” It is—ah! I see thee and yet I have thee not! Come, let me clutch thee! “Hold hard,
      Bill!” “This way, sir—Baker Street! Yorkshire Sting— oh! Full inside! Drive on!
       <stage>(Music—Dies)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Dabbs, and carries Phil off, L.—Miss Chubb and Snooks appear, R.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>It will be my turn next—I feel I'm on the same road—for— <stage>Re-enter Dabbs, l.</stage>
      Hold! you and I have yet accounts to reckon—so pay me now, for I will count blows upon that
      head till one of our two bodies prove it's settled!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M2">
     <speaker>Dabbs.</speaker>
     <p>Agreed! one dead, another shall be so. </p>
     <p>I've had one breeze, and do not fear your blow.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Then, traitor, turn, and Snooks will bravely fight, </p>
     <p>Till Darkeye Dabbs despairing dies downright.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>                                        (Music—they struggle—Dabbs throws Snooks off, who
     falls —Dabbs falls over him, and leaves the dagger stuck in the stage—Miss Chubb rushes down
     stage, obtains it—Dabbs retreats up stairs—Snooks follows—they struggle—Snooks throws Dabbs out
     of window—Miss Chubb kneels at bottom of stairs.—Tableau.</stage>
   </div>
   <div type="scene">
    <head>SCENE SIXTH. </head>
    <stage>Lobby as before.</stage>
    <stage>Music—Snooks rushing on L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>All is over—the poison works! the murders are done! the housebreaker is thrown over, and I'm
      overthrown! Oh, Chubb! Chubb! heroic girl! I have long had my eye upon you, and now you'll be
      in time to see me hook <hi>it!</hi> Farewell! a long farewell to all my greatness. I shall
      have an <hi>inquest</hi> held upon me—on me, who have gone <hi>in quest</hi> of so many
      myself! In half-an-hour the laudanum will have done its work—the remaining time I will employ
      to my own profit. I'll go to my garret and write the account of my own death for the morning
      papers—I go, and it is done—there will be a good report of my tragical ending, at all events.
      The pen—the ink—the paper! What ho! oh!</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>                                        Music—Exit, melo-dramatically, R.</stage>
   </div>
   <div type="scene">
    <head>SCENE SEVENTH. </head>
    <stage>—The Garret. Sunrise.</stage>
    <stage>Snooks discovered, asleep.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss Chubb.</speaker>
     <stage> (knocking at door without)</stage>
     <p>Mr. Snooks! Mr. Snooks! What can have possibly happened to him?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <stage> (awaking)</stage>
     <p>Who calls on Snooks?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss Chubb.</speaker>
     <p>Why, do you know what time it is? It's past ten! and here's a letter been waiting for you
      this hour and more!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>A letter! Why, surely—where am I? can I have been dreaming all this while? It must be so.
      I'll see if she knows anything about it! <stage>(opens door)</stage>
      <stage>Enter Miss Chubb, with letter.</stage> Why, bless my heart, Miss Chubb, you don't look
      as if you'd been up all night!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>La! why should I? You've been dreaming I am afraid, Mr. Snooks.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Dreaming! Oh, I see how it is! those cursed pork chops—fit of indigestion, caused the
      nightmare, and having my brain bewildered with murders and robberies during the day, I've been
      dreaming about robbers all night!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>And so you've really had the nightmare through eating pork chops!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>Yes; rather <hi>porkuliar</hi>, isn't it? But this letter! <stage>(takes it)</stage> Who can
      it be from? I haven't had a letter this twelvemonth. <stage>(reads)</stage> “Dear
      Septimus,—Uncle Bob has remembered you in his will, and left you an annuity of fifty pounds
      a-year, with his pork shop in the Borough. Can't write more, as the post is just leaving. Your
      affectionate   cousin, Angelica Snooks.” Fifty pounds a year and a pork shop in the Borough!
      I'm a made man! Your mother's rent shall be paid, and you shall be Mrs. Snooks!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>La, Septimus, you don't say so!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>It's a bargain! I'm so overjoyed that even the nightmare is forgotten, so we'll invite our
      friends, here, to come another night.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>At nine o'clock, to supper.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>But how to serve this novel dish of fun? </p>
     <p>Perhaps some may think our Pork Chops <hi>over done!</hi></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>To these kind friends you should refer the questions, </p>
     <p>And hope our jest—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <stage>                                        Will not cause indigestion!</stage>
     <p>Agreed; and though our dish is only plain—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>We trust you'll cut—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <stage>                                        To often come again.</stage>
     <p>As for your sanction here, the actor stops,</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_F4">
     <speaker>Miss C.</speaker>
     <p>And stakes his happiness—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0664_M1">
     <speaker>Snooks.</speaker>
     <p>                    On these Pork Chops.</p>
     <stage>CURTAIN.</stage>
    </sp>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
