<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L0802" xml:lang="en">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Orange Blossoms: TEI edition</title>
    <author ref="lacyp:W0337"><persName>J. P. Wooler</persName><idno type="wikidata"/></author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>TEI conversion</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor>
    <idno type="LAE">L0802</idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives
      all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which it believes to be in the public
      domain. You may copy, modify, distribute, or perform this work freely. </licence>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="originalSource" n="54.7"><author n="W0337">Wooler, J.P.</author>
     <title type="main">Orange Blossoms</title>
     <title type="sub">An Original Comedietta in one Act</title>
     <extent>25 pp (UM copy: 144 - 169)<measure type="pp" quantity="24"/>
      <measure type="spCount" quantity="505"/>
      <measure type="spvCount" quantity="1"/>
      <measure type="txWords" quantity="8837"/>
      <measure type="spWords" quantity="8164"/>
      <measure type="stWords" quantity="673"/>
     </extent>
     <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 54, No. 0802</title><idno type="nic">N20080</idno></bibl>
    <bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453822&amp;seq=144 ">UM from
      HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol54/L0802/L0802-um.pdf"/></bibl>
    <listEvent>
     <event type="LCP" when="1862-02-15" where="Strand">
      <desc>Licence sent 15 February 1862 for performance at the Strand. </desc>
      <bibl type="msSource">BL ms LCP_53011.P</bibl>
     </event>
     <event type="firstPerf" when="1862-02-20" source="textNic" where="Strand">
      <desc>Premiered at Royal Strand Theatre 20 Feb. 1862</desc>
     </event>
    </listEvent>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#sizeS"/>
    <catRef target="#act1"/>
    <catRef target="nic:Ca."/>
    <keywords>
     <term>COMEDIETTA</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
   <particDesc><listPerson>
  <person xml:id="L0802_M1">
   <persName type="role">Colonel Clarence</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="71">Colonel.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0802_M2">
   <persName type="role">Mr. Falcon Hope</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="100">Falcon.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0802_M3">
   <persName type="role">Mr. Septimus Symmetry</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="178">Sym.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0802_F4">
   <persName type="role">Violet Hope</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="49">Violet.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0802_F5">
   <persName type="role">Isabella Clarence</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="72">Isabel.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0802_F6">
   <persName type="role">Louisa</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="33">Louisa.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0802_mult">
   <persName type="role">[Multiple speakers]</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="2">All.</persName>
  </person>
</listPerson></particDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc><change when="2026-04-03">Rewrite all particDescs</change>
   <change when="2026-03-20">Add wikidata link to titleStmt where possible</change>
   <change when="2026-03-19">Hand checked against UM pdf</change>
   <change when="2026-03-19">TEI autotagging by Gemini Pro 2.5</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <titlePage>

    <titlePart type="main">Orange Blossoms</titlePart>
    <titlePart type="sub">An original Comedietta</titlePart>
    <titlePart type="sub">In One Act</titlePart>

    <byline>By <docAuthor>J. P. WOOLER, Esq.</docAuthor> Author of <title>Sisterly Service</title>
     <title>Plots for Petticoats</title>
     <title>Language of Flowers</title>
     <title>Allow me to Apologize</title>
     <title>Founded on Facts</title>
     <title>A Twice-told Tale</title>
     <title>Old Phil's Birthday</title>
     <title>A Model Husband</title>
     <title>I'll write to the Times</title>
     <title>Love in Livery</title> &amp;c. </byline>
    <docImprint> Thomas Hailes Lacy, 89, Strand, (Opposite Southampton Street, Covent Garden
     Market,) London. </docImprint>

   </titlePage>

   <performance>
    <head>Orange Blossoms</head>
    <p> First produced at the Royal Strand Theatre, (under the management of Mr. Swanborough, Sen.,)
     Thursday, February 20, 1862.</p>

    <castList>
     <head>Characters.</head>

     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Colonel Clarence</role>
      <actor>Mr. Ray</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Mr. Falcon Hope</role>
      <actor>Mr. Belford</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Mr. Septimus Symmetry</role>
      <actor>Mr. Clarke</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="F">Violet Hope</role>
      <roleDesc>(Wife to Hope)</roleDesc>
      <actor>Miss K. Carson</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="F">Isabella Clarence</role>
      <roleDesc>(Wife to the Colonel)</roleDesc>
      <actor>Miss Bufton</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="F">Louisa</role>
      <actor>Miss F. Josephs</actor>
     </castItem>
    </castList>
   </performance>
   <set>
    <p>SCENE—SYMMETRY'S GARDEN.</p>
    <p>TIME—THE PRESENT.</p>
    <p>Costumes—MODERN.</p>
   </set>
  </front>
  <pb n="3"/>
  <body>
   <note>[Mr. Lacy's List.]</note>
   <head>Orange Blossoms</head>
   <div type="scene">
    <head>Scene.–</head>
    <stage>Garden attached to Symmetry's House; Summer House, R. 2 E.; door and window practicable;
     Shrubbery, L. C.; Terrace, L. 2 E., practicable; garden chairs placed about stage. </stage>
    <stage>Symmetry discovered sitting on rail of garden chair, C., his feet in the seat, a letter
     in his hand.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>coming down</stage> Upon my word, credit, honour, and reputation! this is too bad!
      this perpetual and preposterous persecution of the free men of Great Britain by the unblushing
      women of those three kingdoms, passes all bearing and beggars all belief. Here's poor Falcon
      Hope fallen a victim to that designing coquette Violet Fane; not but that he brought the
      mischief on his own fool's head – he was always chevying the girls about –but it is positively
      a frightful state of things, and a stand must be made against it; these brigands in crinoline
      and bandoline must be put down, and I must go into Parliament to do it, or hang me if I shan't
      have some woman coming down to marry me next! Surely some law can be brought to work, to check
      this monstrous and merciless marauding, upon the hearths and hearts of helpless British
      bachelors; but laws generally are in a queer state, the laws of society are clearly out of
      joint, the laws of nations are simply preposterous, and it's not clear to me, that the laws of
      Nature don't want looking into. Still I've done my best to steer clear of the soft sex
      myself–soft! <hi>I</hi> never saw anything soft in the sex; precious clear-headed,
      sharp-sighted bandits I've found 'em all. Still, I left London, buried myself in the country,
      and picked my neighbours; there isn't a pretty girl in the village–in fact, all the women
      squint, except three, who're blind and can't, so I naturally thought I should be allowed to
      exist in a comparative state of safety; and yet this week has annihilated all my hopes, not
      only has that unutterable imbecile of a Clarence taken a house nearly next door, with that
      sky-larking cousin of mine, his wife, but now, by way of piling up the agony, I receive this
      impertinent and cold-blooded epistle. Let me see it once more. <stage>reads</stage> "Dear Sym,
      You are aware of my having
      <pb n="4"/> become the happiest dog in existence, by the fact of winning my darling Violet."
      Poor, devil! "We have just returned from Paris, and before settling down to work, I have
      determined to spend a few days with my old friend Symmetry, to whom I long to introduce my
      dear little wife. Expect us to-morrow. Yours always, Falcon Hope. P.S. I shall bring little
      Loo with me, as I know she will be as welcome as myself." Little Loo! who's little Loo? it
      can't be a –no, his calamity has not befallen him long enough for that! then who the deuce is
      little Loo? If I don't play my cards pretty cleverly, they'll <hi>loo</hi> me among 'em! Well,
      if things come to the worst I can emigrate; I should be safe in some Ojibbeway settlement, and
      that's what I shall have to do. –That villanous codicil! <stage>Ahem!</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Isabella Clarence, R. 1 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Well, here I am, cousin Septimus!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, here you are– <stage>aside</stage> as we said at school; "bella horrida bella,"
       <stage>aloud</stage> – and you're not the only misfortune that's to befal me to–day.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Gallant as ever; what now?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Just run your eye over my wretched face, and the other over that horrid dispatch.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>As that would involve an absolute squint, cousin, I shall devote both my eyes to the letter,
      with your permission. <stage>reads</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I wonder where all this is to end; however, it's rather premature to
      speculate upon that –it's only just begun.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Why this is absolutely delightful, Septimus.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Is it?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Poor Falcon Hope! how glad I shall be to see him again; you know he was somewhat smitten
      with me once.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Was he? I'm not surprised; he seems fool enough for anything.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Thank you. But whom did he marry? he calls her Violet; what was her other name?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Fane.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Indeed! why this is better and better; oh! what a delicious meeting; why you must know that
      my dear old Colonel proposed to her, before he saw me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>He seems rather partial to ladies, young enough to be his daughters; as some ladies I have
      heard of, take fancies to men old enough to be their grandfathers.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Very well aimed, cousin, but it misses the mark; bless you, you can't put me out of conceit
      with my dear old husband; not that he's an hour older than I approve of, for to tell you a
      very sober truth, Septimus, I admire gray hair, and were I free tomorrow, would rather marry a
      man of fifty, than one of twenty.</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="5"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I can only reply, that you're a woman, and there's no understanding any one of the
      sex; all I know is, the dear Colonel's a precious old ape.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Cousin!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>And tries to make love to every girl he meets.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>He is welcome to do so if it amuses him. It's no use, Septimus, you can't put me out of
      temper. Now do you know what I've made up my mind to do?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>That's good! No ma'am; what you've made up that very small parcel you call your mind for, I
      do not know.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I've made up my mind to marry you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>The deuce you have! are you going to assassinate your other husband?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Not yet.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, we can't have any bigamy, so how are you going to do it?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>You foolish fellow, you don't suppose I'm going to marry you myself; I mean I'll marry you
      to some one else.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Will you? You're very kind I'm sure.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Yes! depend upon it; I shall see you married before long.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>You may see me hanged; it's much more likely –in fact its not improbable that I shall hang
      myself, if this persecution is to go on.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>And pray in default of wife and family, may I take the liberty of asking, to whom you intend
      to leave all your money?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I shall endow a college for decayed bachelors–for those heroes who have fought the good
      fight and come off victorious. Stop a moment, there's one legacy I mean to leave, and that's
      to a lady.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>A lady! you leave a legacy to a lady?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes! to the only woman I really respect on earth.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>How complimentary you are, cousin.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Am I? I beg your pardon, I didn't intend it. But it is a debt of gratitude I am bound to
      discharge. I was once–I presume in a fit of temporary insanity–rash enough to propose to that
      lady.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Good gracious! and she?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>The blessings of a grateful heart upon her, she refused me! I feel the heavy amount of
      obligation I owe her, and shall feebly attempt to discharge it, by leaving her a thousand
      pounds.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, cousin! why didn't you ask me, I'd have refused you for five hundred?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Then you'd have done it very reasonably, that's all I have to say; but I say, are you not
      wasting your time here? you must have a great deal to do at home.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, bless you, no! Clarence and I intended spending
      <pb n="6"/> the day with you; <stage>Sym. groans</stage> but, of course, as you have ladies
      coming, you must have a lady to entertain them; therefore, while they remain, I shall oblige
      you by taking up my abode here altogether.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>gives a slight scream</stage> What! do you mean to tell me that I am to be shut up
      for a <hi>week</hi>, in the same house with two married women and one little Loo?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Exactly! unless we can induce them to stay a <hi>fortnight</hi>!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Then I had better send for a keeper and a straight waistcoat at once, that's all.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>By-the-bye, who <hi>is</hi> little Loo?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, what do I know or care about little Loo! I only hope they'll <hi>lose</hi> her on the
      road.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>You are full of wit and humanity, cousin; but here comes my lord and master, so I'll take
      myself off. <stage>crosses, L.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I can't blame him for coming, when he affects so pleasant a diversion in my favour; and when
      he has succeeded in the desirable manœuvre of taking <hi>you</hi> off, I trust that some
      providential interference will take <hi>him</hi> off too.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>I shall take the liberty, in return for that highly complimentary remark, of superintending
      the preparation of the best bed rooms in the house for your visitors– no thanks –and sans
      adieu!–for I shall see that agreeable face of yours again very shortly.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit up terrace, L. 2 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Shall you? I think it doubtful. Now to be bored by Clarence and his twaddle–for next to
      being talked to <hi>by</hi> a woman, the most objectionable thing is being talked to
       <hi>about</hi> women, and he can talk of nothing else–ha! an idea! Surely, from what Isabel
      told me about the previous attachments between these two couples, I can create some confusion
      among 'em, and punish these men for forcing their wives upon me. I shall be on the look
      out.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Colonel Clarence, R. 1 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>I say, Symmetry, I'll swear I saw the skirt of a petticoat vanish past the shrubbery. Are
      you stealing a march upon us after all, eh?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>You did see a petticoat, Colonel, and one you ought to know and tremble at. It was your
      wife.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, was it? <stage>aside</stage> And she ran away as I approached? I've often had my
      suspicions of this woman-hater. I must keep an eye on him. <stage>aloud</stage> Well, my boy,
      any news?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, as disastrous news as need be. I've got some women coming to see me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Women? Electric sound!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Galvanic shock!</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="7"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Are they young–pretty?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>You ought to be the best judge of that, as one of them was an old flame of yours.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Ah! <stage>aside</stage> This is exciting.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I'm told so–or perhaps it was her mother.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Sir!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, how can I tell? This, is a young woman, once known as Violet Fane.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Violet Fane! <stage>aside</stage> Meet her again? <stage>aloud</stage> Mr. Symmetry, you
      have broken the sealed tomb of the past.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Have I? Is there anything in it?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, sir–crushed affections, blighted hopes, and bitter memories. That young person, sir,
      once rejected this hand–declined this person–renounced this heart.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>No–did she, though?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Symmetry, I am not quite certain that I ought to meet that young person.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, luckily for you, it's optional whether you do or not. I wish <hi>I</hi> could say the
      same. I should certainly advise you to go home at once, and take your wife with you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>No–that would be cowardly, despicable. I will brave destiny and see her.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I say, just allow me to observe that I don't see what destiny you have to brave, in
      connexion with Mrs. Hope. I believe you have formed a matrimonial alliance with another lady,
      and I, sir, as the cousin of that lady, cannot permit – Pshaw! – What do I care about it? Do
      as you like–shoot the husband–marry the widow–get hanged for murder, or transported for
      bigamy. What the deuce is it to me?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>This is strange language, Mr. Symmetry.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, then, don't compel me to ruffle my serene temper about a woman. See! you've brought
      one upon us!</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Isabel from terrace, L. 2 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Oh! cousin, they are coming; I saw them drive up to the gate, and I saw little Loo, and
      she's the queerest looking thing! I told Charles to send them at once into the garden––isn't
      it delightful, my dear Clarence? Of course you know all about it?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, my dear, yes. <stage>aside to Sym.</stage> It will not be necessary, Mr. Symmetry, to
      mention any portion of our recent conversation to Mrs. Clarence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>to him</stage> Don't be alarmed. <stage>aside</stage> I'll set 'em all by the ears,
      if I can. <stage>aloud</stage> Why didn't you let 'em stay in the house: the ladies might like
      to go to bed perhaps.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Not they ––with such a fascinating host; see, here they come!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh! I'm not going to look fascinating; they shan't
      <pb n="8"/> be forming any idea of my personal attractions. <stage>tumbles his hair,
       &amp;c.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>For goodness sake, cousin!</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Falcon Hope, Violet, and Louisa, down terrace, L. 2 E., in travelling
     costumes.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Ah, Symmetry, my dear fellow!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I'm very glad to see you, <stage>aside to him</stage> but why the plague couldn't you come
      alone?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside to him</stage> The old perverted taste, eh? found no girl agreeable yet.
       <stage>aloud</stage> Allow me to introduce my wife to you–Violet, my love, Mr. Symmetry.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Symmetry itself! What a fright!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>I have another friend here, Symmetry, my cousin Loo; Louisa, come here and be introduced,
      will you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, if you like –it isn't of any great consequence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Sensible girl that!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>You have friends here too, Symmetry; pray make us acquainted? <stage>seeing Isabel,
       R.</stage> What, Miss Brandon!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p><stage>L. C.</stage> What, you know this lady, Falcon?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>No–yes–that is<stage>confused.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>This is not Miss Brandon, but the wife of that gentleman, Colonel Clarence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p><stage>starts, seeing the Colonel, R. C., for the first time</stage> Colonel Clarence!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>You know this gentleman, Violet?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p><stage>confused</stage> No–yes–that is–<stage>aside</stage> how exceedingly awkward!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>uneasily</stage> Ahem! <stage>gaily</stage> Oh, well; old friends–so much the better;
      make the visit the more agreeable for my part. I was once fortunate enough to be acquainted
      with Miss Brandon, but it was a mere flying acquaintance.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Which Mrs. Clarence will be delighted to extend, Mr. Hope. <stage>they shake
      hands</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Ahem! I once <stage>aloud</stage> also had the pleasure of a slight
      acquaintance with Miss Fane. <stage>crosses to her</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Which Mrs. Hope is charmed to renew, colonel.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Ahem! <stage>a general restraint is visible.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> It begins beautifully; the men are clearly out of temper, and the women
      seem disposed to keep them there.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I must take an opportunity of seeing Violet Hope alone.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I must manage to see Mrs. Clarence privately.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I'll be hanged if I can think of anything to say, but I must go in for
      something. <stage>aloud</stage> This isn't such an ugly den, is it?</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="9"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Delightful!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Delicious!</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>looking round</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p><stage>L.</stage> Much too nice a den for such a creature as a man.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Louisa!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>For shame!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> That's a most extraordinary young female–I begin to take quite an
      interest in her.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>You appear to be very fond of flowers, Mr. Symmetry.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, ma'am, of all but orange blossoms.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Never mind him, Violet–he's quite incurable; what with Symmetry's denunciations of women,
      and little Loo's onslaughts upon men, we may expect some fun. But come, Sym, show us round the
      grounds–the ladies will join us.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside to him, pulling his coat</stage> No, no; confound you, be quiet.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>I think you must excuse us at present–these ladies may have some change to make in their
      dress. What say you, madam? <stage>crosses to Violet</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>I would rather defer the pleasure until by-and-bye.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>to Falcon</stage> Come along at once; they'll change their minds in half a
      minute.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>We shall not be long, Falcon.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, pray don't hurry.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>This way, ladies.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exeunt Isabel, Violet, and Louisa, up terrace, L. 2 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>C.</stage> That's quite a relief, isn't it?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>L.</stage> Relief, you reprobate!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>R.</stage> The sun seems entirely extinguished!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, never mind the sun, so that the daughters are extinguished.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>I say Sym, you've hit upon a nice North American Indian style of dressing your hair.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, I may as well get into their ways at once; I shall be among 'em soon I fancy.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>What may you mean by that?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I may as well tell you all about it, altho' I don't much like telling secrets to
      married men; however, I'll risk it. You may have remarked that I have usually a good flow of
      spirits? <stage>sits, C.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Certainly. <stage>seated, L. C.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Always cheerful. <stage>seated, R.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>All assumed; there is a canker, gentlemen, at my heart's core.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>What?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Where?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Fact–tell you all about it. You know that old Guy Fawkes of an uncle of mine, who left me
      all his property ?</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="10"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Certainly; my father made the will.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>He did, and be hanged to him! Do you happen to know the fiendish codicil he attached to that
      will?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Perfectly. <stage>aloud</stage> My dear Sym, how should I?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, the human mind is scarcely capable of conceiving such cold-blooded inhumanity; he
      actually tacked this condition to his bequest–that if I did not marry before I was thirty-five
      years of age, nearly the whole of the property goes to another person.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Awkward.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aloud</stage> And who is the fortunate recipient, in case you don't marry?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Why, sir–to culminate his diabolical ingenuity–a woman, sir actually a woman–a certain Miss
      Dudley, whom I never saw!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>And is Miss Dudley aware of this state of things?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>No–she is to be kept in the dark till the time arrives.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>And how old are you now, pray?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Who–I–how old? Oh! rising thirty-four.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Will you swear you are <hi>not</hi> thirty-five next week?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Certainly not–I'll swear I <hi>am.</hi></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I know that. <stage>aloud</stage> And what do you purpose
      doing–marrying?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Mar–– Don't be offensive, sir!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Then, what the deuce do you mean to do?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Why, if there is any way of circumventing this female Dudley–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Don't imagine it; my father is too careful to have left any loophole, and depend upon it, he
      will see the matter properly carried out, for his own reputation's sake.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Then I shall go and join a tribe of Chocktaw Indians, get tattooed, and live comfortably;
      but don't let's talk any more about it we've got the week before us, and we'll amuse
      ourselves. <stage>aside</stage> I shall begin by making you two comfortable.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Marry my young friend–marry, by all means.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh!–you've always some sensible advice to give; but even if I were maniac enough to
      entertain the idea, how could I be sure of getting the right wife. Now here's a case in point.
      My friend Hope, here, you know, was desperately in love with Isabel–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>What, sir?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside to Sym.</stage> Hold your confounded tongue–do!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, dear yes, Colonel, didn't you know that? it was the merest chance in the world that you
      got her–I know she was extravagantly in love with Hope.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside to Symmetry</stage> Are you crazy?</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="11"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>This, I presume, sir, was the "flying acquaintance" you had with Miss Brandon?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>My dear Colonel, this is an egregious error on our friend's part. I certainly did meet Miss
      Brandon, and might have been dazzled for the moment–but only for the moment, believe me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>This is a delicate subject, and I hardly know how to treat it.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Treat it as it deserves, Colonel–it is mere nonsense, be assured. Any partiality I may have
      felt for Miss Brandon has long since been merged in my devotion to my wife.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>As a man of honour, sir, I am bound to believe you. <stage>aside</stage> I shall keep my eye
      upon you, notwithstanding.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, that's all very well, but there's another case in point–the Colonel, here, ought by
      right to have married Miss Fane.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Sir!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside to Symmetry</stage> Can't you keep your fool's tongue quiet?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Bless you, yes–didn't you know that, my dear Hope? they were mad after each other.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside to Symmetry</stage> Confound you! be still, will you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>This, I presume, Colonel, was the "slight acquaintance" you spoke of?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>The fact is, Mr. Hope–I once that is to say––</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Twice, perhaps–come, no shuffling–speak out.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside to Symmetry</stage> I'll assassinate you, you booby!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>laughingly</stage> Well, never mind–Symmetry has exposed us both, let it pass––we are
      matched to our liking at last, <stage>aside</stage> I'll not lose sight of you, my gay
      Colonel.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, now that I have put you on a friendly footing, and already demonstrated to you that
      you have each of you married the wrong woman, let us go and look round the property.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>By all means. <stage>aside</stage> I can't think what on earth could have possessed Violet
      to take any notice of that stick of a Colonel.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> What could Isabel have seen in that puppy, I wonder.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I haven't done amiss for a beginning–I see the makings of a very pretty
      disturbance–I'll keep the game alive –I'll wake 'em up again presently. <stage>aloud</stage>
      This way––you lively husbands!</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exeunt, R. U. E.</stage>
    <pb n="12"/>
    <stage>Re-enter Isabel and Violet down terrace, L. 2 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Believe me, my dear Mrs. Hope, I am delighted, as Mr. Symmetry's cousin, to receive you in
      his house, and shall do my best to entertain you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Believe me, my dear madam, I am equally delighted with the fact of becoming your guest.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>I intend that you and I shall be very intimate friends.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>An intention I shall only be too happy to second.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>And to show you how sincere I am, I am about to take the privilege of an old friend thus
      early, by asking you a favour.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Dear me, how remarkable––do you know, I was about to ask one of you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>No? <stage>aside</stage> What can she mean?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>No! <stage>aside</stage> What can she want?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>The fact is <stage>aside</stage> This is a ridiculous position –––it isn't likely she ever
      heard of her husband's attentions to me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>My object <stage>aside</stage> This is extremely embarrassing of course, she knows nothing
      of Clarence's attentions to me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>You said you wished to ask a favour –pray speak.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Pray let me have the pleasure of obliging you first.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>This will never do–let us be frank–I will set the example. I am perfectly aware that
      previous to my marriage, Clarence had the good taste to make proposals to you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>You knew it? <stage>aside</stage> What a relief!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, and I know something else, of which you may be probably ignorant, namely, that before
      your marriage, Mr. Hope had the bad taste to do me the same honour.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p><stage>coolly</stage> I was certainly quite ignorant of that, Mrs. Clarence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, be very easy, my dear–if I had liked him, I should have married him – as I didn't, I
      married somebody else. Now, we are both sensible women, and perfectly contented with the
      husbands we have –is it not so?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>On my side–undoubtedly.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>holding out her hand</stage> And no worse friends, for having changed partners in the
      fantastic dance of matrimony –eh?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p><stage>taking her hand</stage> Oh, no, no, my dear Mrs. Clarence, I was only a little fool
      for a moment––forgive me, it is a frequent occurrence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Now, that we understand each other, let us to the business, or rather pleasure of a mutual
      obligation–will you commence?</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="13"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>No–do you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Very well–you must promise not to be angry.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Gladly, for I shall have to exact the same promise from you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>That's agreed, then, on either side. Well, you must know that during the trifling
      intercourse between Mr. Hope and myself–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>That is exactly as I should begin–substituting Colonel Clarence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>I was indiscreet enough–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>The very word–our stories commence quite harmoniously.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Indiscreet enough to–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Enter into a correspondence; go on.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Not at all, I never wrote the man a line in my life.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Good gracious! then what were you indiscreet enough to do?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>I was miserably weak enough to give him my portrait.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Oh! <stage>aside</stage> and I daren't say anything about it!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Now, my dear Mrs. Hope, only get me back that stupid portrait, and I will do anything in the
      wide world for you, in return.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>I must be frank, also; I will take up your story at the word "indiscreet." I was indiscreet
      enough to</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>To give Clarence your likeness.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Never; not even a black profile.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Then, what in mercy's name were you indiscreet enough to do?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>To write him certain ridiculous, unmeaning letters. Oh! Mrs. Clarence, only get me back
      those letters–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Ha! ha! your letters for my portrait–a bargain! Now, it's just possible Mr. Hope may have
      that portrait with him.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, dear no, I am quite sure he couldn't do that.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Bless you, men do those things! Clarence carries one or two about with him wherever he goes;
      but he knows I am not jealous, so pray don't you be so.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Oh! bless you, not the least in the world. <stage>aside</stage> If he has!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Now, look here, I have the privilege of all my dear husband's desks, &amp;c. I'll tell you
      what we'll do–can you overlook Mr. Hope's dressing-case and trunks?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>I have the keys of everything,</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Good, then we'll not lose a moment, you go and search for my portrait, whilst, I run home
      and search for your letters.</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="14"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Agreed.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>And as we may have no other opportunity of a private conversation, we may as well fix upon
      some signal of success or failure in our search––I shall be in an agony till I know.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>And I, in absolute despair!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Let me see, I have it–a red rose shall be the signal of success, a white one of failure.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Agreed; but if I meet Falcon first, and he sees me with a flower, it's in his coat the next
      moment.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>I'm full of ideas this morning, I have another, we'll make my cousin Symmetry our signal
      post–we will each, when we meet him, present him with a rose, white or red, as it may be.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>But he will never receive a flower from a lady.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Bless you, he couldn't in common courtesy refuse one from you, and I'll make him take
      mine.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>So be it, then; had we not better proceed to work at once?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>The sooner the better; stay, to guard against contingencies, it will be as well if we
      succeed to deposit our spoil in the summer house, there no one ever enters it–you can put the
      picture in at that little window, as I will the letters; so we can take possession, without
      suspicion, at any time.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>I shall remember, and fortune grant us success!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Amen to that sweet prayer.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit, R. 1 E., Violet up terrace, L. 2 E.</stage>
    <stage>Re-enter Symmetry, R. U. E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Thank goodness I've made my escape from those married men! their conversation, to say the
      least of it, is of a highly objectionable character–in fact, it's hopeless twaddle; they talk
      nothing but nonsense, and they don't even talk that well. Hilloa! here comes little Loo, the
      "man-hater," as Falcon calls her, so much the better.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Louisa down terrace, L. 2 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>So, young lady, I've heard your character from the gentlemen.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>And I yours from the ladies; they were neither, I believe, worth hearing.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>And you hate men, do you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>As much as you hate women.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Then, of course, you hate me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Oh! I can just put up with you; there's not much of you, and what there is, is not of much
      account.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Upon my word, this little Loo's quite refreshing. <stage>aloud</stage>
      I suppose you never mean to be married?</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="15"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Not till a "hot January," as Beatrice says.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Ah! that would have been a magnificent play if Shakespeare had not spoiled it by making
      Benedict fool enough to marry Beatrice.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Reverse it, and say if he had not made Beatrice fool enough to marry Benedict.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Let us accommodate matters by setting them both down as fools together.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Just my opinion.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I can get on magnificently with little Loo. <stage>aloud</stage> Falcon
      and his wife agree tolerably well, eh?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Indifferently so at present–the orange blossoms haven't faded yet.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Orange blossoms! Bah! I'd as soon see a woman with spring onions in her bonnet!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Just my opinion.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>We really agree in a most surprising manner. I must know more of you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>You know enough; you'll like me less the more you know of me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>That's very possible; but do you know you're about the only woman whose visit I have ever
      approved of.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>I am an involuntary visitor–they brought me here. I had no wish to come, be assured.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I like you all the better for it–that is, mind, I don't mean that I like you at all.
       <stage>aside</stage> Sym, my fine fellow, you'd better pull up. <stage>aloud</stage> I
      mean–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>It's very immaterial what. Have you anything more to say?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Not at present, I think. Oh!–stop–yes–you adhere to that resolution of yours–never marry. If
      they would compel you, run away, and never be taken alive.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Let me return that invaluable advice; and be assured if ever I should marry, I should do so
      simply to be revenged on your whole sex, by the torture of that particular man I married.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Delightful candour!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>I'd thwart him–contradict him–plague him–worry him.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Little Loo's a little devil.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>In short, I'd drive him mad–there!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>You wouldn't have very far to drive him; he'd be half way there before he ventured upon
      you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>I'm afraid you'll think me very free and plain spoken, but its my nature; if you object to
      it, say so, and I'll go back to town.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Object? Bless you, no–you have such correct views
      <pb n="16"/> of things in general, and marriage in particular, it's quite delicious, and your
      sentiments again agree with mine, for if by any unforeseen, and impossible concatenation of
      diabolical circumstances I should be inveigled into marriage – You've heard of the wife
      beatings in that healthy and moral village of London?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>To my shame and sorrow, yes.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, they're all trifles to what the woman would get who married me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>I'm sure she would deserve all she received; and now, sir, good morning.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Good morning, miss; I think we quite understand each other, and we've had a very pleasant
      and intellectual conversation. <stage>Exit Louisa up terrace, L. 2 E.</stage> I've quite
      enjoyed it, upon my word; that little Loo is one of the most sensible girls I ever met with.
      If all women were like her now, and had the same opinion of mankind, how swimmingly we should
      all go on together. Now then, this won't do; here's another woman hunting me up–it's Mrs.
      Hope, and hang me, if she hasn't got one of my choicest white roses in her hand–just like
      'em–they can't keep their hands off anything.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Violet down terrace, L. 2 E., with a white rose.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I can't find it. I knew he would never carry that trumpery portrait
      about with him. <stage>aloud</stage> Oh, my dear Mr. Symmetry, I was looking for you. You must
      allow me to present you with this beautiful white rose; you can't refuse to wear it for my
      sake! <stage>fastens it to his coat</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> No, I don't see well how I can, or I would. <stage>aloud</stage> I'm
      sure I'm uncommonly flattered.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, pray don't mention it; and above all, pray don't think of thanking me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I should like to blow you up for picking my flowers.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>I'm sure you'll excuse my running away–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, certainly.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>As I have left little Loo in your pretty conservatory.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit up terrace, L. 2 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>And a pretty conservatory it will be when little Loo comes out of it, I expect. Now, what
      does this white rose mean? there's some design in it, I'll lay a wager. Eh? what? no! yes!
      why, damn it! here's another woman bearing down, with another rose. Its my free and easy
      cousin. Oh, I must get out of this!</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Isabella, R. 1 E., with red rose and packet of letters.</stage>
    <pb n="17"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I've found these precious documents, and I
      <pb n="17"/>dare say they were well worth looking for. <stage>aloud</stage> Ah, cous–What do I
      see, a white rose? <stage>aside</stage> Then she has failed.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>warmly</stage> Yes, and I see a red rose. Now, I tell you what it is, Cousin Isabel,
      I know I'm a mild man, I believe I am generally looked upon as a soft man, but if a pack of
      mischievous females go about my grounds damaging my plants you'll see me in one of the most
      stupendous passions––you will witness one of the most demoniac outbursts of fury–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Don't get excited, my dear Septimus, but just put this rose in your coat, and compose
      yourself you know how I love you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Am I to be stuck all over with roses ?–if I do, I'm–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Don't be a little ruffian! now just attend to me, if you don't put this rose in your coat
      directly, sir, I'll sit by your side, and talk to you all the evening.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>eagerly</stage> Give it to me! <stage>fastens rose in his coat</stage> Life is still
      sweet, even under this persecution.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Gracious! if I didn't leave Clarence's desk open. <stage>aloud</stage>
      I think you'll excuse my running away, cousin?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I'm sure I will–good bye!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Ta, ta, cousin! I declare you look quite handsome, <stage>he turns away, she slips letters
       in the window of summer house</stage> and so good humoured–he! he! he!</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit R. 1 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Confound these women! now what is the meaning of all this? first of all, the female Hope
      brings me a white rose–then the female Clarence brings me a red rose–I suppose little Loo'll
      bring me something presently––a moss rose, perhaps, or a wreath of orange blossoms, or a stick
      of rhubarb from the kitchen garden! It's quite clear I'm being victimized. I see no way for
      it, but to pack up a small portmanteau, steal out of the back door, and "wait for the waggon!"
      and I'll go and do it. Ah!–catch it, Symmetry, my boy–an idea! and what an idea! beautiful!
      Now, my rosy beauties, I'll spoil your little game, whatever it is. I'll just give–ah, here's
      Falcon, that'll do very nicely. I'll begin with him–I'll entangle 'em.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Falcon, R. U. E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Why, Symmetry, what the plague do you mean by running away from your friends in this manner?
      What have you been about?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, bless you, I've been making myself agreeable to the ladies.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>The deuce you have! Well, as you've been so laudably and unusually occupied, I cannot
      complain.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Had a chat with little Loo.</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="18"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Sensible girl that!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I believe you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Rather strong minded, perhaps.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, rather.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Now, she'd make you an excellent wife, Sym.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, I dare say she would, thank you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>I have always promised myself to get you a wife.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>You're very kind; when I want one, I'll drop you a line. Then I've been doing floricultural
      commissions for the other ladies.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>And I see they've not forgotten to reward you for your trouble.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Hush! You see this red rose?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Clearly; and a very fine one it is.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well–it's for you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>For me! From whom?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Never mind that; you take it, and ask no questions.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, nonsense! I must know who sent it.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I don't think the party who sent it ought to have sent it, and I ought not to have
      brought it; but then a woman can't do as she ought, and I'm such an obliging blockhead.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Well, but who is the sender?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, if I must tell you. Here–Isabella Clarence,</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>taking it, aside</stage> Isabella, then, has not forgotten me; but it is too late–my
      allegiance to Violet is not to be shaken. <stage>aloud</stage> I esteem the gift as from an
      old friend–tell her–no, I'll tell her that myself. <stage>puts rose in his coat</stage> Well,
      that other rose?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, that's a secret; – you want to know a great deal too much at once. Let me give you a
      piece of wholesome advice: never prick your fingers with the thorns of other people's
      roses.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, I see; little Loo gave it you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, she did give it me rather–in one sense–but she didn't give me this rose; the fact is,
      as you are so preciously inquisitive, I had it from Mrs. Hope.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Then why couldn't you say so at once? What harm is there in your wearing a rose given you by
      my wife?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I don't suppose there'd be any particular harm if I wore a wreath of roses; but it isn't for
      me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>No! For whom then?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, you will know. I told you you'd better not; but if you will, it's not my fault it's
      for Colonel Clarence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>What, sir!–impossible!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, you think it quite possible for Mrs. Clarence to send you a rose, but quite impossible
      for Mrs. Hope to send one to Colonel Clarence?</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="19"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>A different thing, sir, altogether! <stage>aside</stage> Can this be true?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I look upon it as a mere tit for tat arrangement, but you know best; if you say it is
      impossible, I dare say it is.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Pooh, Sym, you're only joking.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Now just look at me attentively, and tell me candidly, whether I have the appearance of a
      man who's given to joking.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>This is not to be borne, sir; if it be so, I know my course; if it be not so, lock to
      yourself.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit angrily up terrace, L. 2 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Number one settled. I'll teach 'em how to upset a quiet gentleman's establishment, with
      their wives, and little Loos, and roses, and orange blossoms, and–ha! here's Clarence.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Colonel Clarence, R. U. E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Have you seen Isabella, Symmetry?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Gone home, Colonel.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Oh! she'll soon be back, I suppose?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I'm afraid so.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>That's a very handsome white rose of yours.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>It's no rose of mine.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Indeed!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Don't make a noise–it's yours. <stage>gives it</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Mine! To what lovely creature am I indebted for this precious gift ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Why, to me, of course.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Psha! Oh, I see, it's from that pretty little girl they call Louisa!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Go along, you old peacock! that pretty little girl they call Louisa, would be more likely to
      send you a bunch of stinging nettles.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I must know who sent it, come.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh! very good, just as you please, only you'd better know nothing about it; why, you
      irresistible old warrior, it's from Violet Hope.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Is it possible! <stage>aside</stage> The charming Violet still holds me in her heart.
       <stage>puts rose in his coat</stage> Unhappy woman, her repentance comes too late!
       <stage>aloud</stage> Oh, Symmetry, you don't often find old friendships revived in this
      tender and graceful manner!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Not often, only occasionally. I know a very recent case––</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Ah!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, Isabel has just sent Falcon Hope a red rose.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Who? Sent what? Am I to understand–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Precisely what I said, you'll see it in his button hole.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>And if I do, sir, I'll pluck it out, and force it down
      <pb n="20"/> his throat; but, let me be calm–let me first ascertain the truth of this; you say
      my wife has gone home, if you have deceived me, beware!</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit passionately, R. 1 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Number two disposed of, and I think the quarrel a very pretty one as it stands; therefore, I
      shall interfere in it no further. I'll just place myself in a place of observation–Ah! that
      summer house is the very thing; I shall deposit myself in that private box, and enjoy an
      uninterrupted view of the entire entertainment. Hilloa! here comes one of the play actors!
      Walk up, ladies and gentlemen, just a going to begin. <stage>goes into summer house R., and
       looks from window</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Falcon highly excited, L. 2 E., down terrace.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>It was all true, I charged the perfidious woman with having had a white rose in her
      possession, and she could not deny it; but by no threats, or entreaties, or commands, could I
      make her confess for what purpose she procured it. Never mind, I have only now to blow out the
      brains of that rascally old Colonel, and my business here, is at an end. I'm not sure that I
      ought not to blow Symmetry's brains out too!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Hilloa! come I say!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>For daring to lend himself to such a piece of base disloyalty! However, first to find this
      man Clarence.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit, R. 2 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I think I've got him up to fever heat and a degree or two over–good! here comes another of
      the company, the heavy old man.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Colonel, R. 1 E., in a rage.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>True, true! every damned word of it true! The brazen hussey owned to the having a red rose,
      and when I threatened to annihilate her unless she told me why she gathered it, the baggage
      laughed in my face, and said it was a secret––A secret! my honour a secret, in the hands of
      that chattering little villain, Symmetry!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Now then!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>But where is this fellow Hope? I'll shoot him like a dog! and as for Symmetry, I'll
      horsewhip him within an inch of his life.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> The devil you will !</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Falcon, R. U. E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Nowhere to be seen–ha! so, sir, at last!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Well met, sir; I have to demand of you an account of that red rose you wear in your
      coat.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>You forestall me, sir; I was about to demand of you an account of that white rose you wear
      so ostentatiously.</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="21"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> Go it, York–go it, Lancaster!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>And suppose I refuse to render an account, sir.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>You are aware of the alternative, Colonel Clarence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>I wear Her Majesty's uniform, sir, which is a sufficient answer.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>aside</stage> I must stop this.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Louisa, L. U. E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Can you furnish the weapon ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>If you will use mine.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Unquestionably.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Be kind enough to accompany me then.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>about to call out, sees Louisa</stage> Confound it; here's little Lou, again!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Why, what on earth's the matter?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Nothing that concerns you, Louisa–go away.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Indeed I shall not, till I know the meaning of this strange conduct.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>My dear young lady, it will be sufficient for you to understand that I am dishonoured by the
      rose Mr. Hope now wears.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>And I equally so by that worn by Colonel Clarence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, if that's the only cause of quarrel, shake hands.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Bravo, little Lou!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>For you are quarrelling about things that don't concern you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>What!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>What!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>I myself saw both those roses given to Mr. Symmetry.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>I am perfectly aware of that, but they were not for him.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>I beg your pardon; I heard Mrs. Hope say, "My dear Mr. Symmetry, you cannot refuse to wear
      this rose, for my sake;" and Mrs. Clarence said, "Put this rose in your coat and compose
      yourself–you know how I love you."</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>(Colonel and Falcon stare at each other in amazement)</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> That little Lou 'll be the death of me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Now, gentlemen, you can of course do as you please; but if you must fight, you at least know
      who should be your antagonist.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit, L. 1 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> I'll strangle that little Lou, if I'm hanged for it.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>It appears we have been a trifle too hasty in this matter, Mr. Hope.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>We have, Colonel; and I, as the younger, frankly ask your pardon.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>You are an honourable young man, sir, and I ask yours with all my heart. <stage>(they shake
       hands)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="22"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>So this Mr. Symmetry, this woman-hater, has dared to tamper with us in this way.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>I have long suspected him; I believe his expressed antipathy to the sex to be sheer
      hypocrisy and assumed, merely to cloak the vilest enormities.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> O you do, do you, you scurrilous old imbecile!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Our views with regard to him are identical.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>I understand you–certainly.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> I don't.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>The only question is which shall have the first shot at him.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>I claim that, by virtue of seniority.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Oh, you stupid old fool!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>I think it is rather due to me as a guest.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Oh, settle it as you please, pray.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>I cannot consent to waive my right.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Perhaps you'd like to come on both at once.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Well, let us each go in search of him. Whichever is lucky enough to meet him first shall
      take precedence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Agreed; but we may as well change roses first. <stage>(they do so)</stage> I'll take this
      path.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit, R. 1 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>And I this.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit, L. 1 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <stage>(comes out with packet of letters in his hand, and sings very softly)</stage>
     <l>"Come open your gates, and let me gang free,</l>
     <l>For I darena stay longer in Bonny Dundee."</l>
     <p>Well, I think I've done it now; I've certainly put this handsome foot of mine pretty deeply
      into it. I must be off; I should like to tumble across little Loo, though, before I go.
      I'd–I'd I'd–what's this packet? "Letters from Violet." Why, I found 'em among the tools in the
      summer house; she must have been in correspondence with the gardener! She's a beauty! but I
      can't stop to overhaul 'em now, I shall have the Philistines upon me. <stage>(as he is going,
       L. 1 E. meets Falcon)</stage> Oh!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Stop, sir!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Can't–violent hurry! <stage>(as he is about to run off, R. 1 E., meets Colonel)</stage>
      Ah!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Stop, sir!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Don Juan!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Lovelace!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Faublas!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Go on!–anybody else?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Hypocrite!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Traitor!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Is this your friendship?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Is this your hospitality?</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="23"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>I wish to gracious you'd all of you go back to London.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>This rose was given to you, sir, by my wife.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>And this by mine.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes; and I wish both your wives would let my roses alone.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>He admits it!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Unblushingly!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Of course I do.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Roses are not given without a motive, sir.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, then, go and ask the women what the motive was.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>This bravado will not serve your turn, sir. You have been guilty of a gross violation of
      friendship and honour, and shall answer it.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, sir; gross violation–friendship–honour– answer it!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Now I tell you what it is, gentlemen, I'm not a going to be bullied on my own freehold
      property–if I only had a lease of the place I wouldn't stand it! What do you two maniacs
      want?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Satisfaction!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Satisfaction!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I like that–you bring your wives and your little Lou here; they scour my plantations,
      like female Cossacks– pilfer my roses, and thrust them into my button holes, and now you ask
      for satisfaction; damme, I'll go in for damages.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Well, after all this bluster, sir, I presume you are prepared to fight?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Just like your presumption, sir; I'm prepared for nothing of the sort.
       <stage>(aside)</stage> I'm prepared to run away, if I see an opening.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Come sir, enough of this.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Quite enough–rather too much; let's have no more of it.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>You don't escape me thus, sir.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Nor me, I promise you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Now I tell you what it is; if I work myself into a passion, if I give way to the stupendous
      and ungovernable frenzy of anger, if I open the floodgates of my temper, and set free the
      resistless torrent of my overwhelming fury, if in short, you put my all-round collar up, I
      shall pulverize the pair of you! <stage>(Falcon and Colonel laugh disdainfully)</stage> Oh,
      you will have it then, you've done it now; I'm only a little one I know, who cares; if I don't
      demolish–crush–spiflicate–annihilate, and sweep you both from the face of the earth, I–I wish
      I may be married; there. <stage>(takes off coat)</stage> It's no use your attempting to run
      away.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>If you've no objection, we'll fight like gentlemen, not like costermongers.</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="24"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, I've frightened you, have I? I thought I should stop your blustering; but as I am
      strong, I can be merciful.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>The man's mad!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Raving!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>What! my clemency disdained? then away with it, Colonel; in consequence of the excessive
      disproportion of your years–I mean nothing offensive–years, not ears, I may forgive you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Bah!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(to Falcon)</stage> But for you, sir, I defy you to mortal British combat; weapons,
      these! <stage>(holding out fists)</stage> time this, and mind what I say before hand, sir.
       <stage>(shaking packet of letters in his face)</stage> The polishing you will receive!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>What do I see? "Letters from Violet!"</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Mine! by heaven! The miscreant has broken open my desk!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Give up those letters, sir.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Never, with life.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Your life I'll have then, if I blow you into a thousand fragments! I will have those
      letters. Colonel, fetch the pistols.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Enter Isabella and Violet, L. 2 E., down terrace.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> I must shoot him, or–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Pistols! <stage>(Colonel and Falcon, turn away from their wives)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, ladies! you have succeeded in fulfilling the mission of women; you have brought with
      you confusion, mischief, discord, ruin and bloodshed! I am the victim of two wives, belonging
      to my friends; of two roses belonging to myself; and of one little Lou, belonging to no one in
      particular.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, nonsense! <stage>(to Violet)</stage> May I tell?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, yes, and I?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Certainly! <stage>(goes to Colonel)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(turns away)</stage> Hussey!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Come here, Clarence, come here I say, directly. <stage>(takes him up)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Falcon, dear.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Traitress!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>One word only. <stage>(takes him up)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> What are they up to now? the concoction of some other diabolical
      plot, I wager. I shan't stay here to be shot; a favourable opportunity now offers for a run,
      and so here goes. <stage>(running off, L. 1 E., meets Louisa)</stage> Oh, here's little Loo
      again!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Dear me, Mr. Symmetry, where are you going in such a hurry?</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="25"/>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside to Violet)</stage> Oh, is that all? Stop, sir, we haven't quite done with you
      yet. <stage>(whispers Colonel who makes signs of assent)</stage>
      <stage>(aloud to Sym.)</stage> Colonel, a word. These wretched women have made a full
      confession.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, have they?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>And there are two courses open to you; you will have either to exchange shots with Colonel
      Clarence and myself, or else–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M1">
     <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, sir, or else–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well, out with it, what else?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>You will marry.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>What! Perhaps you'll be good enough to go and fetch the pistols.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>You had better marry, sir.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>Consider, cousin, it's a painful thing to be shot.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Get away, both of you! shoot me and bury me in the stable–the women never go there.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Go and fetch the pistols, Colonel.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Exit Colonel, R. 1 E.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Well; but stop a minute, suppose, I say I'll mar–ry –I can't get the word out–who the deuce
       <hi>am</hi> I to marry?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>What do you say to little Loo?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, little Loo, again! <stage>(aside)</stage> An idea! I know she won't marry, so I can get
      out of it that way. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Now, if I'm refused, it's the same thing, of
      course?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Of course!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(c.)</stage> Very well. <stage>(to Louisa, L. C.)</stage> Now, miss, you see the fix
      I'm in, and if–– <stage>(turning away)</stage> No, I'll do it by post.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Won't do.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Won't it? well then, miss–<stage>(turns away)</stage> No, I'm hanged if I know how to go to
      work, and there's an end of it.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>You must kneel down.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F4">
     <speaker>Violet.</speaker>
     <p>Certainly.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F5">
     <speaker>Isabel.</speaker>
     <p>That's the position.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Go along with you, I shan't!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Very good, the pistols will soon be here.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> It's no use kicking, they're too many for me, so here goes.
       <stage>(kneels)</stage> Here's a position for the head of the house of Symmetry.
       <stage>(aloud)</stage> Now, miss, driven to desperation, and forced by an inconceivable
      species of persecution into this painful position. I say, let's go on to the grass, these
      stones are so precious sharp!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>It'll do very well, only be sharp yourself.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>You see before you, miss, an orphan, and a man of independent property; the victim of an act
      of ruffianism, from which there is no escape, but by the perpetration of this act of idiotcy;
      under these circumstances, miss, I have to make you an offer of my hand; either of 'em, right
      or left, I don't care which, what do you say? be quick please.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Well, sir, considering there's very little of you, and not fearing I shall ever love you too
      violently–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(rising)</stage> You see, she refuses.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>But more particularly, to save you from being shot, I consent.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Re–enter Colonel, R. 1. E. with pistols.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Eh! catch me somebody; <stage>(falls into Falcon's arms)</stage> but no–I won't have it,
      little Loo's gone crazy; I will not, I–<stage>(turning R., meets Colonel, who offers
       pistols)</stage> but you don't know what she'll do to me; she told me herself. <stage>(goes
       to Louisa, sternly)</stage> Woman! do you know what you're doing?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Perfectly; I am singular in my notions, and maybe overstepping the bounds of prudence and
      maidenly propriety; but it is to save a worthy man from an aimless and joyless existence, to
      which a false prejudice is condemning him.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>False prejudice?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, sir; the defamers of women are generally either fools or libertines; depend upon it,
      the highest honour of a man's home, the purest part of a man's possessions, the highest lustre
      of a man's life is, the love of a true and honest woman.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>And now permit me to observe, that this proceeding was a necessity on Mr. Symmetry's part,
      for in the event of his remaining unmarried beyond this week, all his property would be
      forfeited to–</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, never mind her name!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(taking Louisa's hand)</stage> To this lady, Miss Louisa Dudley.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_mult">
     <speaker>All.</speaker>
     <p>What!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>Little Loo, Miss Dudley!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M2">
     <speaker>Falcon.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, by his uncle's will. It was a bit of deception on my part, Sym, to bring her here, but
      you will understand and appreciate my intention.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, is it so? no man but a malicious or a foolish one would make such a will, therefore, Mr.
      Symmetry, I release you from your engagement.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_mult">
     <speaker>All.</speaker>
     <p>No, no, no!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_F6">
     <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
     <p>And rest assured you shall remain in full possession of your property.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0802_M3">
     <speaker>Sym.</speaker>
     <p>What, a woman, and so magnanimous! then I say no, no, no, too. <stage>(takes Louisa's hand
       and comes forward)</stage> Don't you think I'm right? <stage>(to audience)</stage> Never
      mind, don't answer– I'll risk it! and you'll shortly see or hear of me in the neighbourhood of
      Hanover Square, in company with "Little Loo," whose bonnet on that occasion, will be decorated
      with Orange Blossoms.</p>
    </sp>
    <stage>Colonel, Isabella. Symmetry. Louisa. Falcon. Violet. R.</stage>
    <stage>Curtain.</stage>
   </div>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>