<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L0871">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>The Ticket-of-Leave Man: TEI edition</title>
    <author>Taylor, Tom</author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>TEI conversion</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor>
    <idno type="LAE">L0871</idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives
      all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which is believed to be in the public
      domain. You may copy, modify, distribute and perform this work freely. </licence>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="origin" n="59.1"><author>Taylor, Tom</author><title type="main"
      n="theticketofleaveman">The Ticket-of-Leave Man</title><title type="sub">A Drama in four
      acts</title><title type="source" n="#FR">Founded on a French Dramatic Tale, “Le Retour de
      Melun”, included in “Les Drames de la Vie”, by MM. Brisebarre and Nuz</title><extent>85 pp (UM
      copy: 10 - 95)<measure type="pp" quantity="86"/>
      <measure type="spCount" quantity="1057"/>
      <measure type="spvCount" quantity="0"/>
      <measure type="txWords" quantity="25168"/>
      <measure type="spWords" quantity="20322"/>
      <measure type="stWords" quantity="4846"/>
     </extent>
     <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 59, No. 0871</title><idno type="nic"
      >N18977</idno><idno type="vpp">Vol59iTicket</idno></bibl>
    <bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref
      target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453657&amp;seq=10 ">UM from
      HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol59/L0871/L0871-um.pdf"/></bibl>
    <listEvent>
     <event type="LCP">
      <desc>No date of licence sent for May 1863 performance at the Olympic.</desc>
      <bibl type="msSource">BL ms LCP_53022.AA</bibl>
     </event>
     <event type="firstPerf" when="1863-05-27" source="textNic" where="Olympic">
      <desc>Premiered at Olympic Theatre 27 May 1863</desc>
     </event>
    </listEvent>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <!--L 4 DramaDrama D. DRAMA-->
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#sizeL"/>
    <catRef target="#act4"/>
    <catRef target="nic:D."/>
    <keywords>
     <term>DRAMA</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
   <particDesc>
    <listPerson>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M1">
      <persName type="role">ROBERT BRIERLY</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Briar.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="223">Brier.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="5">Brierly.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Crier.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M2">
      <persName type="role">JAMES DALTON</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="149">Dalton.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M3">
      <persName type="role">HAWKSHAW</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Hawk</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="79">Hawk.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Hawkshaw.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M4">
      <persName type="role">MELTER MOSS</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="86">Moss.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M5">
      <persName type="role">GREEN JONES</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="40">Green.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M6">
      <persName type="role">MR. GIBSON</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="4">Gibson.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="60">Mr. G.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="6">Mr. Gib.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M7">
      <persName type="role">SAM WILLOUGHBY</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="71">Sam.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M8">
      <persName type="role">MALTBY</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="2">Malt.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="38">Maltby.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M9">
      <persName type="role">BRUNTON</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Burton,</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Sharpe</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Sharpe.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_F10">
      <persName type="role">MAY EDWARDS</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">May</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="129">May.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_F11">
      <persName type="role">EMILY ST. EVREMOND</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="62">Emily.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_F12">
      <persName type="role">MRS. WILLOUGHBY</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Mr. W.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="57">Mrs. W.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_mult">
      <persName type="role">[Multiple speakers]</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="8">All.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">May | Mr. G.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="3">Navvies.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M13">
      <persName type="role">[Partys etc.]</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">1st Detective.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="3">1st Navvy.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="5">1st Party.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="3">2nd Party.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="2">3rd Party.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">4th Party.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L0871_M14">
      <persName type="role">[Waiter]</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="3">Waiter.</persName>
     </person>
    </listPerson>
   </particDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2026-01-14">Standardize header components</change>
   <change when="2025-12-07">Auto-tagged by Gemini 3.0 (Flash 2.5)</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <titlePage>
    <docTitle>
     <titlePart type="main">The Ticket-of-Leave Man</titlePart>
     <titlePart type="sub">A Drama in four acts</titlePart>
     <titlePart type="source">Founded on a French Dramatic Tale, "Le Retour de Melun," included in
      "Les Drames de la Vie," by MM. Brisebarre and Nuz,</titlePart>
    </docTitle>
    <byline>BY <docAuthor>TOM TAYLOR, Esq.</docAuthor>, (Member of the Dramatic Authors' Society,)
     AUTHOR OF <title>Our American Cousin, </title><title>Babes in the Wood, </title><title>The
      Fool's Revenge, </title><title>Nine Points of the Law, </title><title>The House or the Home?
      </title><title>The Contested Election, </title><title>An Unequal Match,
      </title><title>Victims, </title><title>Still Waters Run Deep, </title><title>Going to the Bad,
      </title><title>A Nice Firm, </title><title>A Blighted Being, </title><title>To Oblige Benson,
      </title><title>A Trip to Kissengen, </title><title>Diogenes and his Lantern,
      </title><title>The Philosopher's Stone, </title><title>The Vicar of Wakefield,
      </title><title>To Parents and Guardians, </title><title>Our Clerks, </title><title>Little Red
      Riding Hood, </title><title>Helping Hands, </title><title>Prince Dorus, </title><title>Payable
      on Demand</title>, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.; and one of the Authors of <title>Masks and Faces,
      </title><title>Plot and Passion, </title><title>Slave Life, </title><title>Two Loves and a
      Life, </title><title>The The King's Rival, </title><title>Retribution</title>, &amp;c.,
     &amp;c., &amp;c.</byline>
    <docImprint>THOMAS HAILES LACY, 89, STRAND, LONDON.</docImprint>
   </titlePage>
   <pb n="2"/>
   <div type="liminal">
    <head>INTRODUCTORY.</head>
    <p>I HAVE to thank Mr. EMDEN for his aid and superintendence as manager, and all the actors
     concerned in this drama for the large part of the success of the piece which is due to the
     excellent acting of every one engaged in it. I owe extra thanks to Mr. HORACE WIGAN for his
     intelligent labours as stage-manager. </p>
    <p>Mr. NEVILLE gives great force to the part of Brierly by his unstaginess, the general truth as
     well as force of his impersonation, and, in particular, by the excellence of his north-country
     dialect, which is essential to the proper representation of the part. </p>
    <p>Actors of this character should bear in mind that any staginess or stiltedness will be fatal
     to its effect. </p>
    <p>As much has been said apropos of this drama, on the subject of originality in play writing, I
     wish to submit here a few remarks on this matter. As regards the present play, all credit for
     the invention of the story belongs to MM. BRISEBARRE and Nuz, the authors both of <title>Les
      Drames de la Vie</title>, and of the drama of <title>Leonard</title>, founded, as well as
      <title>The Ticket-of-Leave Man</title>, on <title>Le Retour de Melun</title>, one of the
      <hi>drames</hi> in question. But here my obligation to the French authors ends. The dialogue
     is my own. I have made the personages in the play, its sentiments, and its action English, and
     I claim, on this ground, some, at least, of the rights of a creator. I have always conceived
     that the dramatist is at liberty to take his story where he pleases, whether from life, from
     history, or from fiction. Scarcely any subject treated, in the drama or in romance, but has
     roots in something besides the author's personal invention or observation. In this free
     appropriation of his subject-matter, if in nothing else, the puniest play-wright, who adapts a
     novel or a predecessor's piece, may claim fellowship with SHAKSPEARE. No one borrowed his
     subjects so freely and widely as the great master of all dramatists; he did not scruple to lay
     under contribution even the plays of earlier English writers, re-casting them, and giving the
     breath of his own life to their dead bones. I admit, at the same time, that it is perfectly
     fair that the sources from which an author derives his subject should be stated; and it is
     fair, also, that a dramatist who invents his own story, as well as the dramatic dress of it,
     <pb n="3"/> should receive the additional credit which his inventive faculty deserves. </p>
    <p>I have invented many of my subjects; I have borrowed several; in my printed plays, I have
     invariably mentioned the source to which I am indebted for my story. Of my longer comedies and
      dramas—<title>Victims, </title><title>The Unequal Match, </title><title>The Contested
      Election, </title><title>The Overland Route, </title><title>Payable on Demand,
      </title><title>Helping Hands, </title><title>The Babes in the Wood</title>, and <title>The
      American Cousin</title> are strictly of my own invention—subjects as well as treatment. In the
     case of other pieces, like <title>Plot and Passion, </title><title>Masks and Faces,
      </title><title>The King's Rival, </title><title>Two Loves and a Life</title>, I have worked in
     partnership, but may claim, at least, half the honours of invention, as well as dramatic
     treatment. In others, as <title>Still Waters Run Deep, </title><title>Retribution,
      </title><title>The House and the Home</title>, and <title>The Fool's Revenge</title>, I have
     worked on themes supplied by the plays or novels of others. But wherever I have done this, I
     maintain that comparison of my work with that on which it is founded will show that I have
     nowhere confined myself to the functions of a mere reproducer of other men's thoughts in
     another language, but that I have thought for myself, and engrafted dramatic shoots of my own
     growing upon the stocks which I have transplanted. </p>
    <p>Lastly, I may express my belief, however startling the avowal may be thought, that there has
     been no period, for the last two centuries, in which invention and activity have been more
     conspicuous in the dramatic field than during the thirty or forty years which include the epoch
     of such dramatists as Miss MITFORD, SHERIDAN KNOWLES, BULWER LYTTON, JAMES WHITE, JERROLD,
     BROWNING, G. DARLEY, SEARLE, MARSTON, HORNE, LOVELL, TROUGHTON, BELL, Mrs. GORE, SULLIVAN,
     PEAKE, POOLE, HOOK, PLANCHE, CHARLES and GEORGE DANCE, the MORTONS, MARK LEMON, BUCKSTONE,
     SELBY, FITZBALL (who, whatever may be the literary quality of his plays, has given evidence of
     genuine romantic invention). BERNARD, COYNE, OXENFORD, SHIRLEY BROOKS, WATTS PHILLIPS, and
     those peculiar products of our own time, the burlesque writers, like the Brothers BROUGH, and
     Messrs. BYRON and BURNAND. </p>
    <p>T. TAYLOR.LAVENDER SWEEP, Wandsworth, June, 1863.</p>
   </div>
   <performance>
    <p>First Performed at the Olympic Theatre, under the management of Messrs. Robson and Emden, On
     Wednesday, May 27th, 1863.</p>
    <p>The Scenery by and under the direction of Mr. TELBIN.</p>
    <p>The Ticket-of-Leave Man.</p>
    <castList>
     <head>Characters.</head>
     <castItem><role gender="M">ROBERT BRIERLY</role> (<roleDesc>a Lancashire Lad</roleDesc>) <actor
       sex="M">MR. H. NEVILLE.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">JAMES DALTON</role> (<roleDesc>alias Downey, alias The
       Tiger)</roleDesc>
      <actor sex="M">MR. ATKINS.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">HAWKSHAW</role> (<roleDesc>a Detective</roleDesc>) <actor sex="M"
       >MR. HORACE WIGAN.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">MELTER MOSS</role>
      <actor sex="M">MR. G. VINCENT.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">GREEN JONES</role>
      <actor sex="M">MR. R. SOUTAR.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">MR. GIBSON</role> (<roleDesc>a Bill Broker</roleDesc>). <actor
       sex="M">MR. MACLEAN.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">SAM WILLOUGHBY</role>
      <actor sex="F">MISS RAYNHAM.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">MALTBY</role>
      <actor sex="M">MR. H. COOPER.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">BRUNTON</role>
      <actor sex="M">MR. FRANKS.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="F">MAY EDWARDS</role>
      <actor sex="F">MISS KATE SAVILLE.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="F">EMILY ST. EVREMOND</role>
      <actor sex="F">MISS HUGHES.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="F">MRS. WILLOUGHBY</role>
      <actor sex="F">MRS. STEPHENS.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <roleDesc>Guests, Navvies, &amp;c.</roleDesc>
     </castItem>
    </castList>
   </performance>
   <set>
    <p>TIME—THE PRESENT DAY.</p>
    <p>An interval of three years and a half between the First and Second Acts, and intervals of six
     and four months between the Second and Third, and Third and Last Acts respectively.</p>
   </set>
   <pb n="5"/>
   <div type="programme">
    <head>Programme of Scenery and Incidents.</head>
    <list>
     <label>ACT I.—SEEING LIFE.</label>

     <item>The BELLEVUE GARDENS, in a South-Western Suburb. (SUMMER EVENING).</item>

     <label>ACT II.—BACK FROM PORTLAND.</label>
     <item>MAY EDWARDS'S LODGINGS.</item>

     <label>ACT III.—THE MESSENGER.</label>
     <item>A BILL BROKER'S OFFICE IN THE CITY.</item>

     <label>ACT IV.—HUNTED DOWN.</label>
     <item>
      <p>THE BRIDGEWATER ARMS, In which Miss Hughes will introduce "The Maniac's Tear," a Sensation
       Scena, composed expressly for her by J. H. Tully, Esq. </p>
      <p>A STREET IN THE CITY. AN OLD CITY CHURCHYARD.</p></item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <pb n="6"/>
   <div type="costume">
    <head>Costumes.</head>
    <list>
     <item><label>MELTER MOSS</label>—First Act: Rusty brown over coat, shabby black trousers, low
      crowned black hat. Third Act: Old-fashioned black coat and trowsers, black low crown hat.
      Fourth Act: Ditto and drab hat. </item>
     <item><label>JAMES DALTON</label>—First Act: Drab coat, check trousers and vest, drab hat.
      Third Act: Black frock coat and vest, grey trousers, black hat. Fourth Act: Brown cut off
      coat, tight-fitting trousers, light vest, wide-awake hat. </item>
     <item><label>BRIERLY</label>. First Act: Velveteen coat and vest, drab Kersey trousers, drab
      hat with black hatband. Second Act: Velveteen coat, grey vest and trousers, black hat. Third
      Act: Frock coat, dark vest and trousers, black hat. Fourth Act. Fustian suit, wide-awake hat.
       <label>HAWKSHAW</label>.—First Act: Tweed summer suit, trousers, and boots, wide-awake hat.
      Third Act: Suit of black (eccentric). Fourth Act: First Dress—Cord breeches, waistcoat with
      red sleeves, fur cap. Second Dress—Brown coat and overalls, wide-awake hat. </item>
     <item><label>GREEN JONES</label>. First Act: Full evening suit and light paletot. Second Act:
      Shabby morning gown, smoking cap, and check trousers. Third Act: Blue frock coat, white vest,
      drab trousers, black hat. Fourth Act: Blue (butcher's) coat and white sleeves, white apron,
      check trousers, greasy black hat. </item>
     <item><label>SAM WILLOUGHBY</label>—Second Act: Old paletot, check trousers and vest, highlows,
      cloth cap. Third Act: Tweed suit. Fourth Act: Green coat and vest, drab trousers, black hat. </item>
     <item><label>MR. GIBSON</label>. Second Act: Frock coat, light vest, dark trousers. Third Act:
      Ditto. Fourth Act: Ditto. </item>
     <item><label>MAUTBY</label>. First Act: Fancy summer suit. Fourth Act: Tweed coat, buff vest,
      light trousers, white apron. </item>
     <item><label>MAY EDWARDS</label>.—First Act: Light cotton gown, small shawl, black lace net
      tied over head. Second Act: Neat grey dress, white apron. Third Act: White muslin trimmed with
      mauve ribbons. Fourth Act: Drab stuff gown, dark shawl and bonnet, and apron. </item>
     <item><label>EMILY</label>. First Act: Rich silk dress, lace shawl, pink bonnet. Second Act:
      Showy muslin dress, hair à la Française. Third Act: Spotted muslin and hat. Fourth Act: Pink
      muslin, shawl, and bonnet. </item>
     <item><label>MRS. WILLOUGHBY</label>—Second Act: Red cotton gown, small shawl, white apron,
      white cap with black ribbons. Third Act: Green silk dress, showy shawl, and bonnet. Fourth
      Act: Merino dress, shawl, bonnet, cap.</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <pb n="6+"/>
   <div type="liminal">
    <head>MAY EDWARDS's Song in Act 1.—Page 15. </head>
    <head>[The Words translated from the German of Uhland, and the Music composed by Mrs. Tom
     Taylor.]</head>
    <lg>
     <l>Where daisies blow and waters glide,</l>
     <l>My lonely cottage stands beside</l>
     <l>The willowy brook that flows along</l>
     <l>Its rushy banks with murmuring song.</l>
     <l>And near the door there grows a tree,</l>
     <l>So thick that scarce the cot you see,</l>
     <l>And screens and shades my still retreat</l>
     <l>From Winter's cold and Summer's heat:</l>
     <l>And there, at eve, a nightingale</l>
     <l>Will sit concealed and tell its tale—</l>
     <l>So sweet, that all who wander by</l>
     <l>Are fain to stop, and listen nigh.</l>
     <l>Thou gentle child, with golden hair,</l>
     <l>Whom long I've watched with love and care,</l>
     <l>The wind is cold and rough for thee,</l>
     <l>Say wilt thou come and dwell with me?</l>
    </lg>
   </div>
   <div type="liminal">
    <head>Passages added since the first Representation.</head>
    <quote>
     <ref>(Page 78.)</ref>
     <ref>———Stand off, I say!</ref>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! Robert, Robert! This is the first time you ever thrust me from you. He is a good, kind
       husband, gentlemen; but we have had sore trouble lately, and it has almost driven him wild
       sometimes. But, oh, if you have wives of your own at home, think of them and spare me. Don't
       drive him to drink. He's never taken to that in all our troubles. Robert, come home with me
       —our hearth may be cold, but Love has always sat beside it—our cupboard may be bare, but we
       have never yet wanted bread, and, with heaven's help, we never will. Robert, come—come with
       the wife that loves you—come, come!</p>
     </sp></quote>
    <quote>
     <ref>———and don't sit up for me.</ref>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Robert!</p>
     </sp>
    </quote>
    <quote>
     <ref> ———not wanted here at all. </ref>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! Robert, Robert!</p>
     </sp></quote>

    <pb n="6++"/>
    <quote>
     <ref>Page 80.—SCENE SECOND. — Begin.</ref>
     <stage>Enter MAY EDWARDS, L., breathless and pale—her head uncovered—her hair
      dishevelled.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Thrust from <emph>his </emph>side—no, no—not <emph>his</emph>; but the fierce, hard man's,
       that drink and despair have changed him to! He told me to go home. <emph>Home</emph>!
        <stage>(shuddering)</stage> As if there was any home for me, but where he is, in his sorrow!
       I tried to watch but the pain in my heart blinded me, and I've wandered—wandered through the
       black night in these stony streets! Oh—if I had only died before this! If I could die now!
       Ha! the river can't be far off! there is rest there. <stage>(shrieks)</stage> No, no, no—What
       devilish tempting is this? Die and leave him alone with his despair. Heaven help him and
       forgive me! No; I will live—to bring him back to love and hope and faith. If I must die, it
       shall be with my hand in his our hearts against each other! If I could but find him! Oh,
       Robert! Husband! Love! Where are you? Come to me—come to me.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>She staggers off R., distractedly. </stage><stage>(omit her appearance in the subsequent
      part of the scene)</stage>
     <stage>Then enter MRS. WILLOUGHBY and SAM.</stage></quote>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <div type="act" n="1">
    <pb n="7"/>
    <head>ACT I.</head>
    <div type="scene" n="1">
     <head>SCENE. The Bellevue Tea Gardens, in the south-west Suburbs of London.—Summer
      evening.</head>
     <stage>Front of the Tavern with ornamental verandah, up L.; arbours along the stage, R. and L.,
      with tables and seats; trees, shrubs, statues, &amp;c. at the back, with ornamental orchestra
      and concert room.</stage>
     <stage> PARTIES, male and female, seated at the different tables, R. and L.; WAITERS serving
      refreshments. — Music heard off.—As the curtain rises the parties are heard giving their
      orders; MALTBY moving about with an eye to the GUESTS, WAITERS, &amp;c.; two DETECTIVES at
      table, up L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>1st Party.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Three hots with —</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M14">
      <speaker>Waiter.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(serving another table)</stage> Yes, sir.—Brandy and soda for you, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>2nd Party.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Tea for four—shrimps and a muffin.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M14">
      <speaker>Waiter.</speaker>
      <p>Coming! <stage>(serving another party)</stage> Pot of half-and-half for you, sir.
        <stage>(at DETECTIVE'S table)</stage> Two Sherry negus, two shillings. <stage>(takes
        money)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(moving about)</stage> Now, James, three teas and a muffin in 5. Jackson, money in
       6. <stage>(to a GUEST)</stage> Uncommon thirsty weather, sir—uncommon. <stage>(to another
        party)</stage> If I might recommend a cobbler for the lady, sir, delicious refreshment for
       July. Now, James, look after them brandies in 3.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Moves off, L. U. E.</stage>
     <stage>Enter HAWKSHAW, R. 1 E., he strolls carelessly to the DETECTIVES' table, then in an
      undertone and without looking at them.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawkshaw.</speaker>
      <p>Report.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>1st Detective.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(in same tone and without looking at HAWKSHAW)</stage> All right.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="8"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(same tone)</stage> Here's old Moss. Keep an eye on him. <stage>(strolls off,
        L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MOSS, R., sits at table, R. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to the WAITER)</stage> Good evening, James. Four penn'orth of brandy, if you
       please, James <stage>(sit chair, R.)</stage> and a little peppermint. <stage>(coughs, and
        looks around)</stage> Tiger not here yet. <stage>(bell rings)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> The concert bell, ladies and gentlemen —in the Rotunda.
        <stage>(pointing to concert room)</stage> The first talent—selections from the best
       classical music, and original nigger melodists. This way.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MALTBY, towards concert room, R.—most of the parties move off, leaving DETECTIVES,
      and a GUEST here and there.</stage>
     <stage>Enter DALTON, C., from L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(stirring and sipping his brandy and peppermint)</stage> Warm and comfortable. Tiger
       ought to be here before this. <stage>(as he stirs, his eye falls on the spoon, he takes it
        up; weighs it in his fingers)</stage> Uncommon neat article—might take in a good many
       people—plated, though, plated. <stage>(while Moss is looking at the spoon, DALTON takes his
        seat at Moss's table, unobserved by him)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. of table, to Moss)</stage> Not worth flimping, eh?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. of table, starting, but not recognising him)</stage> Eh, did you speak to me,
       sir?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>What? don't twig me? Then it is a good get up, <stage>(he lifts his hat, and gives him a
        peculiar look)</stage> Eh, Melter?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(recognising him)</stage> What, Tiger!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Stow that. There's no tigers here. My name's Downy; you mind that. John Downy, from
       Rotherham, jobber, and general dealer.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(coming down to DALTON)</stage> Now, sir, what can I have the pleasure of ordering
       you, sir?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>My good friend, Mr. Moss here, insists on standing a bottle of sherry.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(in alarm)</stage> No, no!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>What, you will make it champagne? very well, I'm not proud. <stage>(to MALTBY)</stage> I
       like it dry, mind, and
       <pb n="9"/> none of your home-brewed; I buy my rhubarb-juice at the greengrocer's.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MALTBY, L..</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Come, Ti— <stage>(DALTON gives him a look, which stops him)</stage> A joke's a joke. But a
       bottle of real champagne at ten and six—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>That's serious, eh? Well, I've taken a serious turn, always do when it's low tide here.
        <stage>(pointing to his pocket)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Down on your luck, eh?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(shrugs his shoulder)</stage> The Crushers are getting to know too much; then
       there's the Nailer's been after me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>What, Hawkshaw, the 'cutest detective in the force?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>He's taken his oath on the Bow Street Office testament to be square with me for that
       Peckham job— <stage>(hesitates)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Ah!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>When I spoiled his mate. <stage>(shrugs his shoulders)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(shaking his head)</stage> Ah, I always said that life preserver of yours would be
       doing somebody a mischief.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter MALTBY, L. U. E., with champagne and glasses.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Hush, here's the tipple.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(at back of table, uncorking and pouring out)</stage> And though I say it, there
       ain't a better bottle opened at Buckingham Palace. Ten and six, Mr. Moss—there's a
       colour—there's a bouquet!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(grumbling as he pays)</stage> There ought to be at the price.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(going up)</stage> Now, Jackson, take orders in the Rotunda.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MALTBY, L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(drinking)</stage> Ah, tidy swizzle!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>And so you're keeping dark, eh?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, pottering about on the sneak, flimping or smashing a little when I get the chance; but
       the Nailer's too hard on me. There's no picking up a gentlemanly livelihood. Hang me if I
       haven't often thought of turning respectable.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>No, no; it aint so bad as that yet. <stage>(looking around, and speaking
        cautiously)</stage> Now, I have the beautifullest lot of Bank of England flimsys that ever
       came
       <pb n="10"/> out of Birmingham. It's the safest paper to work, and you should have it cheap,
       dirt cheap, and credit till you'd planted it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>And how about lagging? If I'm nailed it's a lifer.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Bless you, I wouldn't have you chance it; but in the high society you keep, you could
       surely pick up a flat to put off the paper.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I've the very man. I gave him an appointment here, for this evening.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Did you, though? How pat things come about! Who is he?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>A Lancashire lad; an only son, he tells me. The old folks spoiled him as long as they
       lived, left him a few hundreds, and now he's got the collar over his head, and is kicking 'em
       down, seeing life. <stage>(laughs)</stage> And life in London ain't to be seen, without
       paying at the doors, eh, Melter?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Ha, ha, ha! and you're selling him the bill of the play.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I'm putting him up to a thing or two—cards, skittles, billiards, sporting houses, sparring
       houses, night houses, casinos—every short cut to the devil and the bottom of a flat's purse.
       He's as green as a leek and as soft as new cheese, no vice, steady to ride or drive, and runs
       in a snaffle. <stage>(rises)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(rising)</stage> Oh, beautiful, beautiful! <stage>(rubs his hands)</stage> It would
       be a sin to drop such a beautiful milch cow! Suppose we pumped him in partnership?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Thank you, I know your partnership articles, me all the kicks and you all the halfpence.
       But if I can work him to plant a lot of these flimsies of yours, I don't mind; remember,
       though, I won't go higher than fifteen bob for a fiver.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>What, only fifteen bob! and such beauties, too, they'd take in the Bank chairman—fifteen!
       I'd better chance it myself! Only fifteen—it's robbery.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Take it or leave it. <stage>(takes up the newspaper and sits at table, L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>I must take a turn and think it over. <stage>(going, returns)</stage> I'll bring you the
       flimsies. Come, you'll allow me a pound?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="11"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Bid me down again, and I stand on ten shillings —now you know. It's like it or lump it.
        <stage>(he returns to his paper)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(holding up his hands)</stage> Oh, dear! oh, dear! What it is to deal with people
       that have no consciences!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, R. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brierly.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(heard off, L. U. E.)</stage> A bottle of champagne, lad, and half a dozen
       Cabanas—and look sharp!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(looking up from paper)</stage> Here's my pigeon!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter BRIERLY, L. U. E., he looks feverish and dishevelled, and is dressed in an
      exaggerated sporting style.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(laying the paper down)</stage> Ah, Bob! up to time as usual!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brierly.</speaker>
      <p>Aye! nobody shall say Bob Brierly craned while he could keep't going. <stage>(waiter brings
        champagne and cigars)</stage> Here—yo—a clean glass for my friend. <stage>(crossing to L. of
        table, L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(pointing to Moss's bottle)</stage> I've had my whack already.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brierly.</speaker>
      <p>Nay, lad, you can find room for another glass.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>WAITER brings another glass—BRIERLY pours out wine.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brierly.</speaker>
      <p>It puts heart into a chap! <stage>(drinks eagerly)</stage> I've nearly lived on't this
       fortnight past.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. of table, L., stops his hand)</stage> Take care, Bob, or we shall have you in
       the doctor's hands.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Doctor? Nay; I'm as game as a pebble and as stell as a tree! <stage>(fills DALTON's glass
        with a shaking hand)</stage> Curse the glass! Here—drink, man, drink. I can't abear drinking
       single handed. I like company—always did. <stage>(looking round uneasily)</stage> And now, I
       don't know how it is <stage>(nervously looking down near the table)</stage> No, no, it's
       nothing! Here, have a weed. <stage>(offers cigar)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I'll take a light from you. <stage>(as DALTON lights his cigar at BRIERLY'S, the shaking of
        BRIERLY's hand becomes more apparent)</stage> Come, come, Master Bob, you're getting
       shaky—this won't do.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>It's that waking—waking. If I could only sleep. <stage>(earnestly)</stage> Oh, man—can't
       you help a chap to a good night's rest? I used to sleep like a top down at
       <pb n="12"/> Glossop. But in this great big place, since I've been enjoying myself, seeing
       life—I don't know <stage>(passing his hand across his eyes)</stage> I don't know, how it is—I
       get no rest—and when I do, it's worse than none—there's great black crawling things about me.
        <stage>(gulps down a glass of wine)</stage> I say, Downy; do you know how a chap feels when
       he's going mad?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I know the symptoms of del. trem. pretty well—sit down, sit down. First and foremost
        <stage>(puts him a chair)</stage> I prescribe a devilled biscuit I'll doctor one for you.
        <stage>(calling)</stage> Waiter! a plate of biscuits, toasted hot—butter and cayenne.
        <stage>(BRIEKLY buries his head in his hands—aside, looking at him contemptuously)</stage>
       The horrors! ah, he's seen too much of life lately—Bob, are you in cash?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Welly cleaned out I've written to the lawyer-chap, down at Glossop—him that's got all my
       property to manage, yo' know for more brass.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Now, if I'd a few of Moss's fivers— here's a chance. You must bank
       with me till the brass comes. Delighted to lend you a sovereign—five—ten— as much as you
       want.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MOSS, R. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Nay, will yo' though? That's friendly of you. Here's luck—and sink the expense! <stage>(he
        pours out wine, standing in front of table)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside to DALTON)</stage> I've got the flimsies—I'll do it at seven ten.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Fork over.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside, giving him a roll of notes)</stage> There's fifty to begin with—twenty, a
       tenner, and four fives. Plant the big 'un first.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter HAWKSHAW, C., meets Moss at back of chair— approaches the table where the
      DETECTIVES are one of them nods towards Moss and DALTON.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Good evening, gentlemen, <stage>(crosses in front to L.)</stage> you'll find my friend, Mr.
       Downy, excellent company, sir Very improving for a young man from the country.
        <stage>(aside)</stage> That's an honestly earned seven-pun-ten!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit Moss, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <pb n="13"/>
     <stage>WAITER brings biscuits and cayenne.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Now, for your devil, Master Bob. <stage>(as he prepares the biscuit, HAWKSHAW approaches
        the table, and takes up the paper which DALTON has put down— DALTON pushes the biscuit
        across to BRIERLY)</stage> Try that?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Beg pardon, sir, but if the paper's not in hand <stage>(sits at back of table,
       L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(rudely, and pocketing the note hastily)</stage> Eh—sir?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(sitting down coolly at the table and unfolding the paper)</stage> Papers very dull
       lately, don't you think so, sir?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(assuming a country dialect)</stage> I never trouble 'em much, sir, except for the
       Smithfield Market List, in the way of business.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, much my own case. They put a fellow up to the dodges of the town, though: for instance,
       these cases of bad notes offered at the Bank lately. <stage>(watching him close)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I never took a bad note in my life.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>You've been lucky—in the Smithfield line, too, I think you said. In the jobbing way, may I
       ask, sir, or in the breeding?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Sometimes one, and sometimes t'other—always ready to turn the nimble shilling.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>My own rule.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>May I ask your business?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>The fancy iron trade. My principle is, to get as much of my stock on other people's hands
       as I can. From the country, I think?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, Yorkshire.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! I'm Durham myself; and this young gent?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>What's that to you? <stage>(pushing away the biscuit)</stage> It's no use—I can't swallow a
       morsel.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>From Lancashire, I see; why, we are quite neighbours when we are at home—and neighbours
       ought to be neighbourly in this overgrown city, so I hope you'll allow me to stand treat—give
       it a name, gentlemen.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(roughly)</stage> Thank you, I never drink with strangers.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>They've a saying down in Glossop, where I come from, If you want a welcome, wait to be
       axed.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="14"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, quite right to be cautious about the company you keep, young man. Perhaps I could give
       you a bit of good advice—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Thank ye! I'm not in the way o' takin' good advice.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Well, don't take bad; and you won't easy find a worse adviser than your thieving companion
       here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(firing up)</stage> Eh? what do you mean by that?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Not you, sir. <stage>(tapping the champagne bottle)</stage> This gentleman here. He robs
       people of their brains— their digestions and their conscience to say nothing of their money.
       But since you won't allow me to stand anything—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>And wish to keep ourselves to ourselves.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>And think your room a deal better than your company—meanin' no offence you know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(rises and crosses to c.)</stage> Not in the least. If gentlemen can't please
       themselves in a public establishment! I'll wish you a very good evening.
        <stage>(aside)</stage> A plant, I'll keep an eye on 'em!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> I don't half like the look of that fellow. There's something about
       his eye—I must make out if Moss knows him—Bob, will you excuse me for five minutes?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Don't be long—I can't abear my own company.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I've only a word to say to a customer.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, L. 1 E. HAWKSHAW, re-appears, C., watches DALTON off and follows him, L. 2 E.
      after a moment's interval.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(goes to chair, R. of table, L.)</stage> And I'll try to sleep till he comes back.
       If I could only sleep without dreaming! I never close my eyes but I'm back at Glossop wi' the
       old folks at home—'t mother fettlin' about me, as she used when I was a brat—and father
       stroking my head and callin' me his bonny boy—noa, noa—I mustn't think o'them—not here— or I
       shall go mad. <stage>(sinking his head in his hands and sobbing)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music—other GUESTS come in, R. and L. and sit at the other tables.</stage>
     <pb n="15"/>
     <stage>Enter MALTBY, C., from L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Malt.</speaker>
      <p>Now then, James! Jackson take orders. Interval of ten minutes allowed for refreshment. Giv
       your orders, gents, give your orders. The nigger melodists will shortly commence their
       unrivalled entertainment. preliminary to the orchestral selection from <title>Beethoven's
        Pastoral Symphony</title>.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MAY EDWARDS with her guitar, R. U. E. the WAITERS move about bringing refreshments
      to tables— MAY goes down, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>If they'll only let me sing to-night. <stage>(tuning guitar)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Halloa, halloa! what's this? Oh, it's you, is it, Edwards? Come, I'm glad to see you're
       about again, but I can't have you cadging here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, Mr. Maltby, if you'll only allow me to try one song, and go round after it, I'll stop
       as soon as ever they ring up.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Well, well, you was always a well-behaved girl, so, for once in a way— <stage>(crosses to
        L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, thank you, thank you, and if you should have an opening for me in the room, sir, when
       I'm quite strong again—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>No chance of it, we're chuck full—a glut of talent; but if I should be able to find room
       for you in the chorus, and to double Miss Plantagenet when she's in the tantrums, ten
       shillings a week, and find your own wardrobe, you know—I'm not the man to shrink from a
       generous action. Now then, Jackson, money in 4.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MALTBY, L. U. E. <stage>(MAY sings; after her song she goes round the tables; all
       repulse her)</stage></stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>1st Party.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> The concert's quite enough without catterwauling between the acts.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>2nd Party.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> We've no small change, miss. Waiter! bottle pale sherry!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>3rd Party.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Be off!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>4th Party.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Now then, what's the girl gaping at? Can't you take an answer?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to BRIERLY)</stage> Please, sir—</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="16"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Be off with thee, lass, I'm in no mood for music.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(suppressing her tears)</stage> Not a penny!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Stop, lass; <stage>(feels in his pocket)</stage> not a farden. Where's Downy? Come here,
       what'st crying at?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I've not taken anything to-day, and I've not been well lately. <stage>(she turns faint and
        grasps a seat to support herself)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(rising)</stage> Poor thing! here, <stage>(places chair)</stage> sit thee down, why
       thee looks welly clemmed. Try and eat a bit. <stage>(he gives her a biscuit)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Thank you, sir, you're very kind. <stage>(she tries to swallow but cannot)</stage> If I had
       a drink of water.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Wather? <stage>(at back of table, L.)</stage> Nay, a sup o' this will hearten thee up.
        <stage>(tries to give her wine from his bottle)</stage> Not a drop! <stage>(he looks round
        and sees WAITER crossing from L. to R., bringing a decanter of sherry)</stage> Here, that'll
       do. <stage>(takes decanter)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M14">
      <speaker>Waiter.</speaker>
      <p>Beg pardon, sir, it's for No. 1.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I'se No. 1.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>1st Party.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Hollo, sir! that's my sherry.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No, it's mine.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>1st Party.</speaker>
      <p>I'll let you know, <stage>(he rises and turns up his cuffs, BRIERLY looks at
       him)—</stage>No, I'll see the landlord.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit 1ST PARTY, L. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>There, lass. <stage>(pours out a glass for MAY)</stage> Sup that.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(drinks)</stage> It's wine.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Sup it up.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>It makes me so warm.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>It'll put some heart i' thee. Sup again, thou'lt tune thy pipes like a mavis on that. Now
       try and eat a bit.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, sir, you're too good.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Good? me! nay—</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MALTBY, L. U. E., followed by 1ST PARTY.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c., soothingly)</stage> Merely a lark. depend upon it. The gentleman will
       apologize. <stage>(to BRIERLY)</stage> The gent who ordered that bottle of sherry.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Let him ordther another, I'll pay for it</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="17"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>The gent can't say fairer. <stage>(calls)</stage> Bottle sherry, Jackson; seven and six,
       sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Here. <stage>(feels in his pockets)</stage> Eh? score it down.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>We ain't in the habit of scoring, sir, not to strangers.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Then yo'd betther begin; my name's Bob Brierly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Malt.</speaker>
      <p>Your name may be Bob Brierly, sir, or Bob Anybody, sir, but when people take wine in this
       establishment, sir—especially other party's wine— they pay for it.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>DALTON re-appears behind C. from L. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>A tell yo— I'll pay as soon as my friend comes back.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, your friend! A regular case of bilk—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Now yo' take care. <stage>(firing up; the parties gather round from tables)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>frightened</stage> Oh, please, sir, please Mr. Maltby.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>1st Party.</speaker>
      <p>It's too bad.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>2nd Party.</speaker>
      <p>Why can't you pay the man?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>3rd Party.</speaker>
      <p>Police!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(coming forward, L.)</stage> Holloa! what's all this?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c., seizing him)</stage> Here, Downy, you lend me a sovereign to pay this chap.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Sorry I haven't change, but we'll manage it directly. <stage>(to MALTBY)</stage> It's all
       right. I'll be bail for my friend here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Your word's quite enough, sir. Any friend of Mr. Moss's</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Come, Bob, don't be a fool, take a turn and cool yourself. <stage>(drawing him off;
        aside)</stage> Now to plant the big'un. <stage>(draws him off, L. 1 E.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to GUESTS)</stage> Sorry for this disturbance, gents, quite out of keeping with the
       character of my establishment. <stage>(bell—Music, piano)</stage> But the concert is about to
       re-commence; that way, gents, to the Rotunda. <stage>(GUESTS go off, C. fiercely to
        MAY)</stage> This is all along of your cadging, Edwards, sitting down to drink with a
       promiscuous party.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Oh, I'm so sorry—he never thought it was all his kindness.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. sneeringly)</stage> Kindness! much kindness
       <pb n="18"/> he'd have showed you, if you'd been old and ugly. You ought to be ashamed of
       yourself.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(indignantly)</stage> You ought to be ashamed of yourself! it is cruel in you to
       insult a helpless and friendless girl like me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Insult! ho, ho, ha, here's a lark! A half-starved street-singer cheeking me in my own
       establishment! You'd better apply for an engagement, <emph>you</emph> had, on the first
       vacancy. <stage>(looking off)</stage> Hollo! what's that? carriage company! Heavy swells on
       the lark, white ties and pink bonnets! Show the ladies and gentlemen to the Rotunda,
       Jackson.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, R. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(sinks down at one of the tables, L.)</stage> I'm foolish to be angry, my bread
       depends on such as he. Oh, if I could only get away from this weary work! if some kind lady
       would take me in. I'm quick at my needle; but who'd take me, a vagabond, without a friend to
       speak for me? I'm all alone in the world now. It's strange how people's life is made for 'em.
       I see so many girls, nicely dressed, well off, with parents to love and care for 'em. I can't
       bear it sometimes, to see them, and then think what I am, and what's before me. <stage>(puts
        her hand to her face)</stage> I'm a silly girl: it's all because I'm so weak from the fever.
       There's nothing like keeping a good heart. How good he was to me; it was all through me he
       got into this trouble; but I mustn't think of him. Ah, <stage>(looking off, R. 1 E.)</stage>
       there's a pleasant looking party yonder. Come along, old friend, you've to earn my supper
       yet.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Takes her guitar and exit, R. 1 E.</stage>
     <stage>Enter GREEN JONES and EMILY ST. EVREMOND, R. U. E he wears evening costume, black, white
      tie, Gibus hat, &amp;c.;<note type="ed">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opera_hat</note> she is
      gaily dressed, pink bonnet, &amp;c.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(speaking as he comes down)</stage> Excuse me, Emily! Anything but the Rotunda; if
       your mama likes the music let her enjoy it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>I'm sure the music's very nice, Mr. Jones.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><emph>Mr. </emph>Jones, Miss St. Evremond! What have I done to be kept at arm's length by
       that chevaux de frise of a mister? was it for this that I thawed the thick-ribbed ice of Mrs.
       Traddles?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="19"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Thick-ribbed ain't a proper word to use to any lady, and I tell you my ma's name ain't
       Traddles, Mr. Jones, it's the same as mine—St. Evremond; she's changed it at my wish.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>I beg pardon of your stern parient, <stage>(sits, L.)</stage> Mrs. St. Evremond, late
       Traddles; but I repeat, was it to be called <emph>Mister</emph> Jones that I treated Mrs. St.
       E. and her chyild to the Star and Garter, and her chyild without Mrs. E. to the Trafalgar,
       where from the moonlit balcony that overhung the fragrant river, we watched together the
       sunset over the Isle of Dogs?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>And very wrong it was of me to go to that whitebait dinner without ma; and preciously she
       blew me up about it, though I told her you couldn't have treated me with more respect if I'd
       been a countess instead of a coryphée.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Emily, you only did me justice. My intentions are honorable. If you are
       in the ballet, that's no reason you shouldn't be a dear good girl. You've been a trump of a
       daughter; I don't see why you shouldn't turn out a trump of a wife. Emily, accept my
       hand.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Nonsense, Green, you don't mean it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>I'm perfectly serious. My hand and my heart, my fortune and my future. Don't stare, Emily.
       It's as true as that my name is Green. I'm quite in earnest—I am indeed.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! Green, dear, I'm in such agitation. <stage>(rises)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> We will spend a rosy existence. You like life, and I flatter myself I
       understand it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>And don't <emph>I</emph>? I call this life—the music and the company, and the singing and
       the trapèze. I thought the man must break his neck. It was beautiful!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, I like to associate with all classes. "Survey mankind," you know, Emily—" from
       China"—to earthenware. So when Charley Punter proposed a night at the tea gardens, I sank the
       swell; and here I am with my Emily and her mama. Charley didn't seem to see the parient; but,
       "Propriety, Charley my boy," I said, and he submitted with a sigh. And now what will you
       have?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="20"/>
     <stage>Re-enter MAY, down R. 1 E.—she begins to sing.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! anything but that. Now do oblige me by shutting up, that's a good girl.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>No, no, poor thing. Let her sing; she has a sweet voice.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Flat, decidedly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(contemptuously)</stage> You're another. Give me half a crown for her.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(gives one, she asks by gesture for another)</stage> Two? Such a bore. I shall have
       to change a note at the bar.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>You'll have to change a good many notes when we are married. <stage>(to MAY)</stage> Come
       along, you shall have both half crowns.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exeunt GREEN JONES and EMILY, L. U. E. as MAY is following.</stage>
     <stage>Enter BRIERLY, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Downy not here? He said I was to bring 't brass to our table.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(recognises him up, c.; comes down)</stage> 'Tis he! <stage>(joyously)</stage> Oh,
       sir, I'm so sorry—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Why, it's t' singin' lass. <stage>(crosses to her)</stage> I say, have you seen my
       friend?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>No, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>And where's t' landlord. Here's that'll make civil enough. <stage>(shews a number of
        sovereigns in his hand)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, what a lot of money!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Brass for a twenty pound note. I got it changed at t' cigar shop down t'road. He's a
       good'un is Downy—lends me whatever I want. Here yo' landlord. Hoy!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MALTBY, L. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Coming! Coming! <stage>(recognising BRIER)</stage> Oh it's you. <stage>(down,
       R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(flinging a half sovereign to MALTBY)</stage> There; seven and six is for t' wine,
       and t' other half crown's for t' thrashin' I owe you. <stage>(approaches him
        threateningly)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(pocketing the money and retreating)</stage> Take care—I'll teach you to insult a
       respectable licensed victualler, <stage>(to MAY, who trys to calm BRIERLY)</stage> and you
       <pb n="21"/> too, you tramp, I'll have you locked up for annoying my customers. How do I know
       my spoons are safe?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Thou cur! <stage>(he breaks away from MAY, and makes a rush at MALTBY, who escapes, L. U.
        E., crying "Police!")</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I can't bear you should trouble for me, indeed, sir. <stage>(concealing her
       tears)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Nay, never heed that muck-worm! come, dry thine eyes; thou's too soft
       for this life o' thine.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(apologetically)</stage> It's the fever, I think, sir—I usedn't to mind unkind looks
       and words much once.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Here, take this, <stage>(puts money into her hand)</stage> and stay thee quiet at home till
       thou'st i'fettle again.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Two sovereigns! oh, sir! <stage>(cries)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Nay, thou'lt make better use o't' brass than me—What, cryin' again! come, come, never heed
       that old brute, hard words br'ak no bones, yo know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>It's not<emph> his</emph> hard words I'm crying for now, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>What then?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><emph>Your</emph> kind ones—they're harder to bear—they sound so strange to me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Poor thing! heaven help thee—thou mindest me of a sister I lost, she'd eyes like thine, and
       hair, and much t' same voice, nobbut she favert redder i' t' face, and spoke broader. I'd be
       glad whiles to have a nice gradely lass like you to talk to.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>But where I live, sir, it's a very poor place, and I'm by myself, and</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(hesitates)</stage> No, no—you're right—I couldn't come there, but I'm loth to lose
       sight of yo too.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter DALTON hastily, from C. down R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Brierly!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Here'st' change—I've borrowed five o'the twenty.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>All right, now let's be off— I've a cab outside.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to MAY)</stage> Mind, if you want a friend, write to Bob Brierly, at the Lancashire
       Arms, Air-street, yo'll not forget.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Never, I'll set it down, <stage>(aside)</stage> in my heart I</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Come!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>And yo, tell me yo'r name—will yo?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>May Edwards.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Confound your billing and cooing—come!</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="22"/>
     <stage>As BRIERLY follows DALTON, C. HAWKSHAW and two of the DETECTIVES, appear, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>You're wanted.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> The crushers! Run, Bob!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>(Music—DALTON attempts to escape—DETECTIVES detain BRIERLY—HAWKSHAW seizes DALTON—in the
      scuffle, DALTON's hat and wig are knocked off)</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>I know you, James Dalton!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(starting)</stage> Ah!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Remember the Peckham job!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>The Nailer! Hit out, Bob! <stage>(BRIERLY has been wrestling with the two DETEC TIVES, as
        DALTON speaks he knocks one down)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I have! Some o' them garottin' chaps!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(cries)</stage> Help! help! <stage>(wringing her hands)</stage>
       <stage>(a fierce struggle—</stage>DALTON escapes from HAWKSHAW and throws him, he draws a
       pistol, DALTON strikes him down with a life preserver and makes his escape through the
       trees—BRIERLY is overpowered and handcuffed—GUESTS rush in and form Tableau)</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>GUESTS.</stage>
     <stage>GUESTS.</stage>
     <stage>HAWKSHAW. DETECTIVE. BRIERLY. DETECTIVE. MAY.</stage>
     <stage>R.</stage>
     <stage>L.</stage>
     <trailer>END OF THE FIRST ACT.</trailer>
    </div>
   </div>

   <div type="act" n="2">

    <head>ACT II.</head>
    <div type="scene" n="1">
     <head>SCENE. The Room occupied by May Edwards in Mrs. Willoughby's House, humbly but neatly
      furnished;</head>
     <stage>flowers in the window, R. flat; a work table; stool; door communicating with her bed
      room, R.; door leading to the staircase, L.; guitar hanging against wall; needlework on the
      table:</stage>
     <stage>MAY discovered with a birdcage on the table, arranging a piece of sugar and groundsel
      between the bars; sofa, R. chiffionier, L.; American clock, &amp;c.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>There, Goldie, I must give you your breakfast,
       <pb n="23"/> though I don't care a bit for my own. Ah! you find singing a better trade than I
       did, you little rogue. I'm sure I shall have a letter from Robert this morning I've all his
       letters here. <stage>(takes out a packet from her work box)</stage> How he <emph>has</emph>
       improved in his handwriting since the first. <stage>(opening letter)</stage> That's more than
       three years back. Oh! what an old woman I'm getting! It's no use denying it, Goldie.
        <stage>(to her bird)</stage> If you'll be quiet, like a good, well-bred canary, I'll read
       you Robert's last letter. <stage>(reads )</stage> "Portland, February 25th, 1860. My own
       dearest May, <stage>(kissing it)</stage> As the last year keeps slipping away, I think more
       and more of our happy meeting; but for your love and comfort, I think I should have broken
       down." There, Goldie, do you hear that? <stage>(she kisses the letter)</stage> "But now we
       both see how things are guided for the best. But for my being sent to prison, I should have
       died before this, a broken-down drunkard, if not worse; and you might still have been earning
       hard bread as a street singer, or carried from a hospital ward to a pauper's grave." Yes,
       yes, <stage>(shuddering)</stage> that's true. "This place has made a man of me, and you have
       found friends and the means of earning a livelihood. I count the days till we meet. Good-bye,
       and heaven bless you, prays your ever affectionate Robert Brierly." <stage>(kisses the letter
        frequently)</stage> And don't I count the days too? There! <stage>(makes a mark in her
        pocket almanack)</stage> Another gone! They seem so slow—when one looks forward—and yet they
       pass so quickly! <stage>(taking up birdcage)</stage> Come, Goldie, while I work you must sing
       me a nice song for letting you hear that nice letter! <stage>(hanging up birdcage—a knock at
        the door)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter EMILY, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(entering)</stage> May I come in?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, yes, Mrs. Jones. <stage>(sits to work, R. C.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>St. Evremond, please, Miss Edwards. Jones has changed his name. When people have come down
       in circumstances, the best they can do is to keep up their names. <stage>(sits, L.
        C.)</stage> I like St. Evremond, it looks well in the bill, and sounds foreign. That's
       always attractive— and I dress my hair á la Francaise, to keep up the effect.
       <pb n="24"/> I've brought back the shawl you were kind enough to lend me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I hope you got the engagement, dear?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(sighs)</stage> No the proprietor said my appearance was quite the thing—good stage
       face and figure, and all that you know how those creatures always flatter one; but they
       hadn't an opening just now in the comic duet and character-dance business.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I'm so sorry; your husband will be so disappointed.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! bless you, he doesn't know what I've been after. I couldn't bear to worrit him, poor
       fellow! He's had so many troubles. <emph>I</emph>'ve been used to rough it— before we came
       into our fortune. <stage>(noise heard overhead, L. —MAY starts)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>What noise is that? It's in your room.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Don't be alarmed—it's only Green; I left him to practice the clog-dance while I went out.
       He's so clumsy. He often comes down like that in the double shuffles. But he gets on very
       nicely in the comic duets.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>It's very fortunate he's so willing to turn his hand to anything.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, he's willing enough to turn his hand, only he is so slow in turning his legs. Ah, my
       dear, you're very lucky only having yourself to keep.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I find it hard enough work sometimes. But after the life I've passed through, it seems
       paradise.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! I couldn't a-bear it; such a want of excitement! And you that was brought up to a
       public life too. <stage>(rises)</stage> Every night about six, when they begin to light up
       the gas, I feel so fidgetty, you can't think—I want to be off to the theatre. I couldn't live
       away from the float, that is, not if I had to work for my living,— of course it was very
       different the three years we had our fortune. <stage>(sighs, and gives herself an air of
        martyrdom)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I'm afraid Mr. Jones ran through a great deal in a very short time.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Well, we were both fast, dear; and to do Jones justice, I don't think he was the fastest
       You see he
       <pb n="25"/> was used to spending, and I wasn't. It seemed so jolly at first to have
       everything one liked. <stage>(a knock)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Come in!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter GREEN JONES, much dilapidated; he wears a decayed dressing gown and a smoking cap,
      and carries a pair of clogs in his hand; he throws himself into chair, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Your wife's here, Mr. Jones.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>St. Evremond, please dear.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, Montague St. Evremond; that is to be in the paulo-poster-futurum. I thought you would
       be here, Milly. I saw you come in at the street door. <stage>(MAY takes her work)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, you were watching for me out of the window, I suppose, instead of practising your
       pas.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>I was allowing my shins an interval of refreshment. I hope, Miss Edwards, you may never be
       reduced to earn a subsistence by the clog hornpipe, or if you are, that you will be allowed
       to practise in your stockings. The way I've barked my intractable shins!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Poor dear fellow! There, there! He's a good boy, and he shall have a piece of sugar—he
       shall. <stage>(kissing him)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Sugar is all very well, Emily, but I'm satisfied I shall never electrify the British public
       in this style of pump. <stage>(shewing clog)</stage> The truth is, Miss Edwards, I'm not
       meant for a star of the ballet; as Emily says, I'm too fleshy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Stout was the word.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! was it? Anyway, you meant short winded. My vocation is in the more private walks of
       existence. If I'd a nice easy light porter's place, now—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! Montague, how can you be so mean spirited?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Or if there's nothing else open to us but the music halls, I always said we should do
       better with the performing dogs.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Performing dogs! Hadn't you better come to to monkeys at once?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>I've a turn for puppies. I'm at home with
       <pb n="26"/> them. It's the thing I've been always used to, since I was at college. But we're
       interrupting Miss Edwards. Come along, Emily; if you're at liberty to give your Montague a
       lesson in the poetry of motion under difficulties. <stage>(showing the clog)</stage> But, oh,
       remember your Montague has shins, and be as sparing as possible of the double shuffles.
        <stage>(rises, leaving his clogs)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>You poor dear soft-headed—soft hearted—soft-shinned creature! What <emph>would</emph> you
       do without me? <stage>(comes back)</stage> Oh, what a man it is, he has forgotten his dancing
       pumps, and I'm sure they're big enough.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit EMILY and GREEN JONES, L. door.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(folding up her shawl)</stage> How times are changed since she made him give me
       half-a-crown that dreadful night, when Robert—<stage>(sits)</stage> I can't bear to think of
       it, though all has turned out so well. <stage>Enter MRS. WILLOUGHBY, L.</stage> Ah, Mrs.
       Willoughby, I was expecting a visit from you. I've the week's rent all ready. <stage>(gives
        her a folded parcel from small box on table)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Which ready you always was, to the minit, that I will say, my dear. You'll excuse me if I
       take a chair, <stage>(sits, L.)</stage> these stairs is trying to an elderly woman —not that
       I am so old as many that looks younger, which when I'd my front tittivated only last week,
       Mr. Miggles, that's the hair dresser at 22, he says to me, "Mrs. Willoughby," he says, "forty
       is what I'd give you with that front," he says. "No, Mr. Miggles," I says, "forty it was
       once, but will never be again, which trouble is a sharp thorn, and losses is more than time,
       and a shortness of breath along of a shock three years was last July, "No, Mr. Miggles," I
       says, "fronts can't undo the work of years," I says, "nor yet wigs, Mr. Miggles—which
       skin-partings equal to years, I never did see, and that's the truth." <stage>(pauses for
        breath)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>At all events, Mrs. Willoughby, you're looking very, very well this morning.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, my dear, you are very good to say so, which, if it wasn't for rheumatics and the rates,
       one a top of another, and them dustmen, which their carts is a mockery,
       <pb n="27"/> unless you stand beer, and that boy, Sam, though which is the worst, I'm sure is
       hard to say, only a grandmother's feelings is not to be told, which opodeldoe can't be rubbed
       into the 'eart, as I said to Mrs. Molloy—her that has my first floor front—which she says to
       me, "Mrs. Willoughby," says she, "nine oils is the thing," she says, "rubbed in warm," says
       she. "Which it's all very well, Mrs. Molloy," says I, "but how is a lone woman to rub it in
       in the nape of the neck and the small of the back; and Sam that giddy, and distressing me to
       that degree, No, Mrs. Molloy," I says, "what's sent us we must bear it, and parties that's
       reduced to let lodgings, can't afford easy chairs," which well I know it, and the truth it
       is— and me with two beauties in chintz in the front parlor, which I got a bargain at the
       brokers when the parties was sold up at 24, and no more time to sit down in 'em than if I was
       a cherrybin.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I'm sure you ought to have one, so hard as you've worked all your life, and when Sam gets a
       situation—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Sam, ah, that boy—I came here about him; hasn't he been here this morning?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>No, not yet. I was expecting him—he promised to carry some things home for me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, Miss Edwards, if you would only talk to him; he don't mind anything I say, no more than
       if it was a flat-iron, which what that boy have cost me in distress of mind, and clothes, and
       caps, and breakages, never can be known—and his poor mother, which was the only one I brought
       up and had five, she says to me, "Mother," she says, "he's a big child," she says, "and he's
       a beautiful child, but he have a temper of his own;" which, "Mary," I says—she was called
       Mary, like you, my dear, after her aunt, from which we had expectations, but which was left
       to the Blind Asylum, and the Fishmongers' Alms Houses, and very like like you she was, only
       she had light hair and blue eyes—"Mary, my dear,' I says, "I hope you'll never live to see
       it," and took she was at twenty-three, sudden, and that boy I've had to mend and wash and do
       for ever since, and hard lines it is.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="28"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I'm sure he loves you very dearly, and has a excellent heart.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Heart, my dear—which I wish it had been his heart I found in his right-'and pocket as I was
       a-mending his best trowsers last night, which it was a short pipe, which it is nothing but
       the truth, and smoked to that degree as if it had been black-leaded, which many's the time
       when he've come in, I've said, "Sam," I've said, "I smell tobacco," I've said. "Grandmother,"
       he'd say to me, quite grave and innocent, "p'raps it's the chimbley" —and him a child of
       fifteen, and a short pipe in his right-hand pocket! I'm sure I could have broke my heart over
       it, I could; let alone the pipe—which I flung it into the fire—but a happy moment since is a
       thing I have not known. <stage>(pauses for breath)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! he'll get rid of all his bad habits in time. I've broken him in to carry my parcels
       already.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, indeed! and how you can trust him to carry parcels; but, oh! Miss Edwards, if you'd
       talk to him, and tell him short pipes is the thief of time, and tobacco's the root of all
       evil, which Dean Close he've proved it strong enough, I'm sure—and I cut it out of the
        <title>Weekly Pulpit</title>—and wherever that paper is now, <stage>(rummaging in her
        pocket—knock at door, L.)</stage> That's at your door—which, if you're expecting a caller or
       a customer <stage>(rises)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>No; I expect no one—unless its Sam. <stage>(knock repeated, timidly)</stage> Come in.
        <stage>(lays down her work)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>BRIERLY opens the door, timidly, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brierly.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(doubtfully)</stage> Miss Edwards, please?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. rushing into his arms)</stage> Robert! you here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> My own dear May! <stage>(rushes over to her)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. confused)</stage> I'm so glad! But, how is it that you're—how well you look!
        <stage>(fluttered)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Eh? well I'm sure!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! you mustn't mind, Mrs. Willoughby, it's Robert.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Oh—Robert! I suppose by the way he's a-goin' on, Robert's your brother—leastways, if he
       ain't your brother</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="29"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Her brother? yes, ma'am, I'm her brother! <stage>(kisses MAY)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Indeed! and if I might make bold to ask where you've come from—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I'm just discharged. <stage>(he pauses—MAY giving him a look)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Discharged! and where from—not your situation, I 'ope?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>From Her Majesty's Service, if you must know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses to c.)</stage> I've not seen him for three years and more. I didn't expect
       him so soon, Mrs. Willoughby, so it was quite natural the sight of him should startle me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Which well I know it—not 'avin' had brothers myself, but an uncle that
       ran away for a soldier, and came back on the parish with a wooden leg, and a shillin' a day
       pension, and always in arrears for liquor— which the way that man would drink beer!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> I should have written to prepare you, but I thought I might be here as
       soon as my letter, so I jumped into the train at Dorchester, and here I am.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> That was very thoughtless of you—no, it was very thoughtful and kind of
       you. But I don't understand—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>How I come to be here before the time I told you in my letter? You see, I had full marks
       and nothing against me, and the regulations <stage>(MAY gives him a look which interrupts
        him)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses c. to MRS. WILLOUGHBY)</stage> If Sam comes shall I tell him to go down
       stairs to you, Mrs. Willoughy?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>I shall be much obliged to you, my dear— which I know, when brothers and sisters meet
       they'll have a great deal to talk over, and two's company and three's none, is well
       beknown—and I never was one to stand listenin' when other folks is talkin' and one thing I
       may say, as I told Mrs. Molloy only last week, when the first floor had a little tiff with
       the second pair front about the water—"Mrs. Molloy," I says, "nobody ever heard me put in my
       oar when I wasn't asked," I says, "and idle chatterin' and gossip," I says, " is a thing that
       I never was given to, and I ain't a goin to begin now," I says, which good mornin' to you,
       young man, and a better girl, and a nicer girl, and a harder workin' girl than your sister,
       <pb n="30"/> I 'ope and trust may never darken my doors, <stage>(BRIERLY throws open
        door)</stage> which her rent was ever ready to the day. No my dear, it's the truth and you
       needn't blush. <stage>(during this last speech BRIERLY gets round to L. and urges her towards
        door, L.)</stage> Thank you, <stage>(going to door, L.)</stage> I can open the door for
       myself, young man. <stage>(turns to him)</stage> And a very nice looking head you have on
       your shoulders, though you have had your hair cut uncommon short, which I must say—good
       mornin', my dear, and anything I can do for you, <stage>(exit, L., but heard still talking
        till the door below is heard to shut loudly)</stage> I'm sure, which nobody can say but I
       was always ready to obligė, if reduced to let lodgings owing to a sudden shock.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Phew! <stage>(giving a sigh of relief)</stage> One would think she'd
       been on the silent system for a twelvemonth! Now, we're alone at last, May. Let me have a
       good look at you. I gave you a bit of a squeeze, but I hadn't a good look. <stage>(he takes
        her by the hand)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Well—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Prettier than ever—you couldn't look better or kinder.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Now sit down, and don't talk nonsense.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Sit down! not I—I've had a good look at you —and I must have a good look at the place. How
       snug it is! as neat as the cell I've just left. But it wasn't hard to keep <emph>that</emph>
       in order—I had only a stool, a basin, and a hammock. Didn't I polish the hammock-hooks
       neither. One must have a pride in something you know. But here you've no end of things a
       sofa—and a carpet—and chairs—and—<stage>(going round as he speaks)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Isn't it a nice clock, Robert? and look at the cheffonier! I picked that up a bargain and
       all out of my own earnings!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>It's the cosiest little nest for my bird—you were a singing bird once, you
        know—<stage>(sees the guitar)</stage>—And there's the old bread-winner—I'm glad you've not
       parted with <emph>that</emph>.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I should be the most ungrateful creature if I did! How many a dinner it's earned for
       me!—how many a week's rent it's paid! But for it I never should
       <pb n="31"/> have known you—my friend—my brother. Yes, Robert, I wanted to explain to Mrs.
       Willoughby, when she called you my brother.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>So did I. But I felt it was true— <stage>(sits, R. C.)</stage> If I'm not your brother born
       and bred, May, you've been a true sister to me—ever since that night</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Oh, Robert—a kind word was never lost yet. No wonder I clung to
       you—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Aye, when all stood aloof. In the prison—in the dock—to the van-door. But for you, May, I
       should have been a desperate man. I might have become all they thought me a felon, in the
       company of felons.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, do not look back to that misery—but tell me how you are out so long before your
       time?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Here's my ticket-of-leave—they've given me every week of my nine months—they hadn't a mark
       against me—I didn't want to look forward to my discharge —I was afraid to—I worked away; in
       school, in the quarry-gang first, and in the office afterwards, as if I had to stay there for
       ever—I wasn't unhappy either—all were good to me. And then I had your letters to comfort me.
       But when I was sent for to the governor's room yesterday, and told I was a free man,
       everything swam round and round—I staggered—they had to give me water, or I think I should
       have fainted like a girl.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, as I felt that night when you gave me the wine.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Poor dear, I remember it, as if it was yesterday. But when I passed out at the gate, not
       for gang labour, in my prison dress, with my prison mates, under the warder's eye, and the
       sentry's musket, as I had done so many a weary week—but in my own clothes—unwatched —a free
       man—free to go were I liked—to do what I liked—speak to whom I liked, <stage>(rises)</stage>
       I thought I should have gone crazy—I danced, I sang, I kicked up the pebbles of the Chizzle
       beach—the boatmen laid hands on me for an escaped lunatic, till I told 'em I was a discharged
       prisoner, and then they let me pass—but they drew back from me; there was the convict's
       'taint about me—you can't fling that off with the convict's jacket.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>But here, no one knows you—you'll get a fresh start now.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="32"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I hope so, but it's awfully up hill work, May; I've heard enough down yonder of all that
       stands between a poor fellow who has been in trouble, and an honest life. But just let me get
       a chance.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh—if only Mr. Gibson would give you one.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Who's he?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>The husband of the lady who was my first and best friend. <stage>(BRIERLY looks
        uneasy)</stage> After you, of course, you jealous thing. It was she gave me work—
       recommended me to her friends and now I've quite a nice little business. I pay my way—I'm as
       happy as the day is long—and I'm thinking of taking an apprentice.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> How I wish I was a lass. <stage>(taking her hand)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> I think I see those great clumsy hands spoiling my work.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>You don't want a light porter—eh, May?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>No—I've not quite business enough for that yet. If Mr. Gibson would only give you
       employment. He's something in the City.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No chance of that, May. I must begin lower down, and when I've got a character, then I may
       reach a step higher, and so creep back little by little to the level of honest men.
        <stage>(gloomily)</stage> There's no help for it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(putting her hands upon his shoulder)</stage> At all events you can wait and look
       about you a little—you've money coming in, you know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Me, May?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Yes. You forget those two sovereigns you lent me—I've put away a shilling every week out of
       my savings and then there's the interest, you know—ever so much. It's all here. <stage>(goes
        to table, and coming down on his L., puts a saving-sbox into his hand)</stage> You needn't
       count it. There'd have been more if you hadn't come so soon.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>My good, kind May, do you think I'd touch a farthing of your savings?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, do take it, Robert, or I shall be so unhappy —I've had more pleasure out of that money
       than any I ever earned, because I thought it would go to help you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Bless your kind heart! To think of those little fingers working for me—a lusty, big-boned
       chap like me!
       <pb n="33"/> Why, May, lass—I've a matter of twenty pounds in brass of my own earnings at
       Pentonville and Portland—overtime and allowances. The Governor paid it over to me, like a
       man, before I started yesterday—aye, and shook hands with me. God bless him for that.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Twenty pounds! Oh, how small my poor little earnings will look! I was so proud of them,
        too—<stage>(ruefully)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Briar.</speaker>
      <p>Well, keep 'em, May—keep 'em to buy your wedding-gown, <stage>(takes her in his arms and
        kisses her)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter SAM, L.—he gives a significant cough.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! <stage>(startled)</stage> Sam!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(hastily)</stage> Sam! is it? Confound him! I'll teach him <stage>(crosses to L. C.,
        sees it is a boy, and pauses)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Now will you, though? Granny will be uncommon obliged to you. She says
       I want teaching —don't she? <stage>(to May)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> How dare you come in like that, Sam, without so much as knocking?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>How was I to know you had company? Of course I'd have knocked if I'd been aware you'd your
       young man.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> I'll tell you what, young un, if you don't make yourself scarce—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Well, what? <stage>(retreating)</stage> If I don't make myself scarce, you'll pitch into
       me. Just you try it <stage>(squaring)</stage> Lanky?—Yah! Hit one of your own size
        <stage>(squaring)</stage> do!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Go it, Master Sam! Ha, ha, ha!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>My name's not Sam. It's Samivel Willoughby, Esquire, most respectable references given and
       required, <stage>(pulls collar up)</stage> as Granny says when she advertises the first
       floor.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Now be off, like a good little chap.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Come—cheeky! Don't you use bad language. I'm rising fifteen, stand five feet five in my
       bluchers, and I'm sprouting agin' the summer, if I ain't six foot of greens already like
        <emph>you</emph>.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses to c.)</stage> Hold your tongue! you're a naughty, impudent little boy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Come—I'm bigger than you are, I'll bet a bob. <stage>(stands on his toes)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="34"/>
     <stage>Enter MRS. WILLOUGHBY, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, here's that boy at last! which upstairs and down stairs, and all along the street, have
       I been a seekin' of him, <stage>(throws him over to L.)</stage> which, if you'd believe me,
       Miss Edwards, I left a fourpenny-bit in the chany dog-kennel on the mantel-piece down stairs,
       only yesterday mornin' as ever was, which if ever there was a real bit of Dresden, and cost
       me fourteen-and-six at Hanway Yard in 'appier days, with a black and white spaniel in a
       wreath of roses, and a Shepherdess to match, and the trouble I've 'ad to keep that boy's
       'ands off it since he was in long clothes—where's that fourpenny-piece—<stage>(seizes
        him)</stage> you young villain which you know you took it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Well, then, I did to buy bird's-eye with.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Bird's-eye! and him not fifteen—and the only one left of three.
        <stage>(falls in chair, L. C.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>If you will nobble a fellow's bacca, you must take the consequences; and just you mind it
       ain't no use a tryin' it on breaking my pipes, Granny. I've given up Broselys and started a
       briar-root. <stage>(pulls it out)</stage> It's a stunner.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Oh dear, oh dear! if it ain't enough to melt an'eart of stone—no! fronts I may wear to 'ide
       my suffering, but my grey 'airs that boy have determined to bring with sorrow to the
       grave.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>What? Cos I smoke? Why there's Jem Miggles smokes, and he's a year younger than me, and
       he's allowed all the lux'ries of the season—his father's going to take him to see the badger
       drawn at Jemmy Shaw's one of these days—and his mother don't go into hysterics.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Sam, I'm surprised you should take pleasure in making your grandmother unhappy!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>I don't take pleasure—she won't let me; she's always a knaggin' and aggravatin' me. Here,
       dry your eyes, granny—<stage>(goes to her)</stage>—and I'll be a good boy, and I won't go
       after the rats, and I won't aggravate old Miggles's bullfinches.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>And you'll give up that nasty tobacco, and you'll keep your clothes tidy, and not get
       sliddin' down
       <pb n="35"/> ladders in your Sunday trowsers—which moleskins won't stand it, let alone mixed
       woollens.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Best put me in charity leathers at once with a muffin cap and a badge, wouldn't I look
       stunnin'? Oh my! <stage>(goes L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>There! that's just him—always some of his imperent audacious chaff—I know he gets it from
       that young Miggles—ready to stop his poor granny's mouth with.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>No. <stage>(kisses her)</stage> that's the only way to stop it. Come, I'm goin' to take
       myself up short, like a jibbin cab oss! and be a real swell, granny, in white kids! only I'm
       a waiting till I come into my fortune—you know, that twenty pounds you was robbed of, three
       years ago.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Which robbery is too good a word for it. It was forgery, aye, and a'most as good as murder—
       which it might ha' been my death! Yes, my dears, as nice looking, civil spoken a young man as
       you would wish to see—in a white 'at, which I never can forget, and a broad way of
       speaking—and, "Would you change me a twenty pound note, ma'am," he says;" "And it aint very
       often," I says, "you could have come into this shop"— which I was in the cigar and periodical
       line at that time.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Where was your shop?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>In the Fulham-road, three doors outside the Bell-vue Gardens— "And a note is all the same
       to me," I sez—"if all correct," I sez—and when I looked in that young man's face, I had no
       more suspicion than I should of either of yours, my dears; so he gave me the note, and he
       took the sovereigns. And the next thing I saw was a gent, which his name he told me was
       Hawkshaw, and he were in the police, on'y in plain clothes, and asked to look at the note,
       and told me it was a bad un; and if that man left me on the sofa, in the back shop, or behind
       the counter, with my feet in a jar of brown rappee, and my head among the ginger beer
       bottles, is more than I can tell for fits it was for days and days, and when I worked out of
       'em, then I was short of my rent, and the stock sold up and me ruined. <stage>(BRIERLY shews
        signs of agitation while she is speaking)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Crier.</speaker>
      <p>And you never recovered your money?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="36"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Not a penny, my dear, and if it hadn't been for a kind friend that set me up in my own
       furniture, in the Fulham Workhouse I might have been at this moment, leastways St. George's,
       which that's my legal settlement and that blessed boy <stage>(goes L., she cries)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(gaily)</stage> In a suit of grey dittoes, a stepping out with another chap, a big
       'un and a little 'un together like a job lot at an auction, to church of a Sunday, to such a
       jolly long sermon! shouldn't I like it! <stage>(consolingly and changing his tone)</stage> I
       say, don't cry, granny, we ain't come to skilly yet. <stage>(gets to c.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Which if that young man knew the mischief he'd done.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Perhaps he does, and is sorry for it. <stage>(they rise he goes to
        back)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses to R. with SAM)</stage> Not he, the wretch! What do the likes o' them care
       for the poor creatures they robs—hangin's too good for 'em, the villains.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses at back to L.—taking his hat and going)</stage> Good bye, May.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>You're not going?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I've a little bit of business that can't wait— some money to pay.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>You'll not be long?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No; I'll be back directly. <stage>(aside)</stage> Thank heaven, can I make it up to
       her!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit BRIERLY, L. door.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Poor fellow! he can't bear it! she little thinks—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>You'll excuse me, it's not often I talks about it, Miss Edwards, which it's no use a cryin'
       over spilt milk, and there's them as tempers the wind to the shorn lamb—and if it wasn't for
       that boy—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> There, she's at me again.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Which if I'd only the means to put him to school and keep him out of the streets, and clear
       of that Jim Miggles and them rats</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R., half crying)</stage> Bother the rats!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses to SAM)</stage> You see, Sam, how unhappy you make your grandmother.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>And don't you see how unhappy she makes me, talkin' of sendin' me to school.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="37"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(forcing him to MRS. WILLOUGHBY)</stage> Come, kiss her, and promise to be a good
       boy. Ah, Sam, you don't understand the blessing of having one who loves you as she does.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Then, what does she break my pipes for?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, them pipes! <stage>(a knock)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>More visitors! What a busy morning this is! Come in !</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MRS. GIBSON, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Miss Edwards—eh?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Glad I'm right—I thought it was the third floor front a woman told me downstairs. I'm
       afraid I pulled the wrong bell. <stage>(looks about him, takes off his hat, gloves,
        &amp;c.—MAY sets him a chair, L. C., he sits)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>And a nice way Mrs. Molloy would be in if you brought her down to another party's bell,
       which, asking your pardon, sir, but was it the first floor as opened the street door? It was
       a lady in a very broad cap border and still broader brogue.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>I don't know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Which that is the party, sir, as I was a speakin' of; and I do 'ope she didn't fly out,
       sir, which Mrs. Molloy of a morning—after her tea—she says it's the tea—is that
       rampageous—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. Gib.</speaker>
      <p>No, no; she was civil enough when I said I wanted Miss Edwards.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Which I do believe, my dear, you've bewitched every soul in the 'ouse, from the kitchens to
       the attics.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. Gib.</speaker>
      <p>Miss Edwards don't confine her witchcraft to your lodgers, my good lady. She's bewitched my
       wife. My name's Gibson.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, sir; I've never been able to say what I felt to your good, kind lady; but I hope you
       will tell her I am grateful.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. Gib.</speaker>
      <p>She knows it by the return you have made. You've showed you deserved her kindness. For
       fifty people ready to help, there's not one worth helping— that's my conclusion. I was
       telling my wife so this morning, and she insisted that I should come and satisfy myself that
       she had helped one person at any rate who
       <pb n="38"/> was able and willing to help herself, <stage>(looks at her)</stage> and a very
       tidy, nice looking girl you are, <stage>(goes up round table and comes down)</stage> and a
       very neat, comfortable room you have, I must say.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Which you can tell your good lady, sir, from me, Miss Edwards' rent
       were always ready to the days and minits—as I was telling her brother just now.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. Gib.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Brother? My wife said you were alone in the world.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I was alone, sir, when she found me. He was <stage>(she hesitates)</stage> away.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. Gib.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(pointing to SAM, who has put down a chair and is balancing himself
        acrobatically)</stage> Is this the young gentleman? <stage>(SAM pitches over with chair, and
        MRS. WILLOUGHBY lugs him up)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, dear no, sir, begging your pardon, which that is my grandson, Samuel Willoughby, the
       only one of three, and will be fifteen the twenty-first of next April at eight o'clock in the
       morning, and a growing boy—which take your cap out of your mouth, Samuel, and stand straight,
       and let the gentleman see you. <stage>(MR. GIBSON, sits L. of table)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(sulkily)</stage> The old gent can see well enough—it don't want a telescope.
        <stage>(slinks across at back to L.)</stage> I ain't a-going to be inspected. I'll mizzle.
        <stage>(takes a flying leap over chair)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit SAM, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Which Miss Edwards' brother is grown up, and only come back this
       blessed mornin' as ever was, discharged from Her Majesty's Service, and five foot nine in his
       shoes, by the name of Robert—which, well he may, for a sweeter complexion—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>With a good character, I hope.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, yes! <stage>(eagerly)</stage> the very best, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter BRIERLY, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> I've done it! I can face her now.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>So—<stage>(rises)</stage> I suppose this is Robert, a likely young fellow.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> This is Mr. Gibson, Robert, the husband of the lady who was so good
       to me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> Heaven bless her and you too, sir, for
       <pb n="39"/> your kindness to this poor girl, while I was unable to help her.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>But now you've got your discharge, she'll have a protector.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I hope so, sir—as long as I live, and can earn a crust—I suppose I shall be able to do
       that.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. Gib.</speaker>
      <p>What do you mean to do?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, there it is; I wish I knew what I could get to do, sir. There are not many things in
       the way of work that would frighten me, I think.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>That's the spirit I like your sister speaks well of you, but I shouldn't mind that. It's
       enough for me that you've come out of <stage>(BRIERLY looks startled)</stage> Her Majesty's
       Service with a good character. <stage>(BRIERLY gives a sigh of relief)</stage> You write a
       good hand? <stage>(MAY goes up and round table—gets letters from box—comes down L.
        c.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Tolerably good, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Beautiful, sir: here are some of his letters—look, sir. <stage>(going to shew him, but
        pauses, seeing date of letter)</stage> Portland ! not this, sir. <stage>(turns page)</stage>
       This side is better written.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>A capital hand. Can you keep accounts?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, sir, I helped to kept the books—yonder.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter SAM, L. door, comes over rapidly at back, to MRS. WILLOUGHBY.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Holloa, Granny, here's a parcel I found for you in the letter box ain't it heavy,
       neither.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> For me? <stage>(takes it)</stage> Whatever is it? Eh! money? Oh! Sam,
       you han't been and gone and done anything wrong?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Bother! Do you think if I had I'd a come to you with the swag?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(who has opened the packet, screams, and lets a paper fall from the packet)</stage>
      </p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>What's the matter, Mrs. Willoughby?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Sovereigns! real, golden sovereigns!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>May | Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Sovereigns!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, crikey! <stage>(goes up and down in exultation, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(picks up the paper MRS. WILLOUGHBY has let
        <pb n="40"/> fall)</stage> Here's a note "For Mrs. Willoughby—£20 in payment of an old
       debt."</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(who has seated himself and begun to write, rises and comes down)</stage> Yes, and
       no signature. Come, don't faint, old lady! Here, give her a glass of water. <stage>(to
        MAY)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(recovering)</stage> Sovereigns! for me? Oh, sir, let me look at 'em—the
       beauties—eight, nine, ten, twelve, fifteen, eighteen, twenty! Just the money I lost.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>There, Granny—I always said we was comin' into our fortune.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(with a sudden flash of doubt)</stage> I shouldn't wonder if it was some nasty
       ring-dropper. Oh! are they Bank of Elegance, or only gilt washed? Which I've seen 'em at
       London Bridge a sellin' sovereigns at a penny a-piece.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Oh, no! they're the real thing.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Perhaps it's somebody that's wronged you of the money and wants you to
       clear his conscience.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(C.)</stage> Ah! eccentric people will do that sort of thing—even with income-tax.
       Take my advice, old lady, keep the cash.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Which in course a gentleman like you knows best, and I'm sure whoever
       sent the money, all I wish is, much good may it do him, and may he never know the want of
       it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Amen!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Which, first and foremost—there's my silver tea pot, I'll have out of pawn this blessed
       day, and I'll ask Mrs. Molloy to a cup of tea in my best blue chaney, and then this blessed
       boy shall have a year of finishin' school.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>I wish the party had kept his money, I do! <stage>(MRS. WILLOUGHBY is counting the
        sovereigns over and over)</stage> I say, Granny, you couldn't spare a young chap a couple of
       them, could you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Drat the boy's imperence! Him askin' for sovereigns as natural— Ah! they'll all be for you,
       Sam, one of these days.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>I should like a little in advance. <stage>(SAM makes a grab at the sovereigns playfully,
        and runs at back to L., followed by MRS. WILLOUGHBY whom he dodges behind a chair—MR. GIBSON
        writes at table)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="41"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(half-hysterically, throwing herself into a chair)</stage> Oh! Sam, which that boy
       will be the death of his poor grandmother, he will.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(jumping over chair back on which he perches on, gives back money and kisses
        her)</stage> There, granny, it was only a lark.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(admiringly and affectionately)</stage> Oh! what a boy you are!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exeunt MRS. WILLOUGHBY and SAM, L. door.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(gives note to BRIERLY)</stage> Here, young man,. bring this note to my office, 25,
       St. Nicholas-lane, at ten o'clock to-morrow. I've discharged my messenger—we'll see if you
       are fit for the place.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, sir!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>There there, don't thank me. <stage>(crosses to L.)</stage> I like gratitude that shews
       itself in acts like yours to my wife. Let's hope your brother will repay me in the same
       coin.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, R. door.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Robert, the money has brought us a blessing already. <stage>(he takes her in his arms
        exultingly—Music, piano)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>R. MAY. BRIERLY. L.</stage>
     <trailer>END OF ACT THE SECOND.</trailer>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div type="act" n="3">
    <pb n="41"/>
    <head>ACT III.</head>
    <div type="scene" n="1">
     <head>SCENE. Mr. Gibson's Bill-broking Office in Nicholas-lane, City</head>
     <stage>—a mahogany railing runs up the stage, separating compartment, L. (in which stand across
      the stage two large mahogany desks set round with wire, and a brass rail at the top to support
      books) from the compartment, R., at the side of which, in side flat, R. 2 E., is the door
      leading to Mr. Gibson's private office— in front of the compartment, L., runs a mahogany
      counter with a place for writing at, divided off, L.—a large iron safe for books in R.
      flat—another safe, R., near door—door communicating with passage and street, in c. flat—a
      small desk down stage, R. 1 E.—two windows, L. As the curtain rises, SAM is discovered
      carrying the ledgers out of safe, R., through an entrance in the railing to compartment, L.,
      and arranging them on the desks— BRIERLY is discovered at the counter numbering cheques in a
      cheque-book, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> There they are, all ship-shape. I say, Bob,
       <pb n="42"/> if granny could see these big chaps, <stage>(whilst carrying ledgers)</stage>
       all full of £ s. d., and me as much at home with them as old Miggles with his toy terriers.
        <stage>(puts books on desk and returns to c.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Only the outsides, Sam—fifty—fifty-one—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Everything must have a beginning. I'm only under messenger now, at six bob a week, but it's
       the small end of the wedge. I don't mean to stay running errands and dusting books long, I
       can tell you. I intend to speculate—I'm in two tips already.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Tips?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Yes. <stage>(takes out betting book)</stage> I stand to win a fiver on Pollux for the
       Derby, and a good thing on the Count for the Ascot Cup—they were at Pollux last week, but
       he's all right again, and the Count's in splendid form, and the stable uncommon sweet on
       him.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Bring me those pens. <stage>(as SAM comes to him with the pens he comes to c. and catches
        him by the collar and shakes him)</stage> You young rascal! Now, you mark me, Master Sam. If
       ever I hear of you putting into a tip again I'll thrash you within an inch of your life, and
       then I'll split on you to Mr. Gibson, and he'll discharge you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Now I call that mean. One City gent interfering with another City gent's amusements.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(bitterly)</stage> Amusements! When you've seen as much as I have, you'll know what
       comes of such amusements, lad.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>As if I didn't know well enough already. Lark, lush, and a latch-key—a swell rig out, and
       lots of ready in the pockets—a drag at Epsom, and a champagne lunch on the hill! Oh my—ain't
       it stunning!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, Sam, that's the fancy picture—mine is the true one. Excitement first, then idleness and
       drink, and then bad companions—sin—shame—and a prison.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Come, I don't want to be preached to in office hours: granny gives me quite enough of that
       at home, ain't it a bore, just!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, my lad, take my advice, do! Be steady— stick to work and home. It's an awful look out
       for a young chap adrift in this place, without them sheet anchors. <stage>(returns to
        counter, L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="43"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, I ain't afraid. I cut my eye teeth early. Tips ain't worse than time bargains—and
       they're business. <stage>(crosses at back to his L.)</stage> But don't look glum, Bob, you're
       the right sort, you are, and sooner than rile you I'll cut tips, burn "Bell's Life, and take
       to Capel Court and the "Share List," and that's respectable, you know. <stage>(sits on
        counter)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(looking over cheque book)</stage> You young rascal! you've made me misnumber my
       cheques.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Serves you jolly well right, for coming to business on your wedding day.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! I've two hours good before I'm wanted for that.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>I say, Bob, you don't mean to say you've been to the Bank for the petty cash this
       morning?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Yes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>And didn't leave the notes on the counter?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>And didn't have your pocket picked?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Well, you are a cool hand. I've often wondered how the poor chaps in Newgate managed to eat
       a good breakfast before they're turned off. But a fellow coming to office the morning he's
       going to be spliced and when the Governor has given him a holiday too—by Jove, it beats the
       Old Bailey by lengths. I hope I shall be as cool when I'm married.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>You you young cock-sparrow.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Yes. I've ordered the young woman I want down at Birmingham. Miss Edwards ain't my
       style.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No—isn't she though? I'm sorry it's too late to have her altered.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>She's too quiet—wants go. I like high action. Now I call Mrs. Jones a splendid woman. Sam
       Willoughby, Esquire, must have a real tip-top lady. I don't mean to marry till I can go to
       church with my own brougham.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I suppose that means when you've set up as a crossing sweeper. And now, Sam, till your
       brougham comes round for you, just trot off to the stationer's and see if Mr. Gibson's new
       bill-case is ready.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="44"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(vaulting over the counter, sees MAY through the glass door, L., off L. 1
        E.)</stage> All right. Here's Miss Edwards a coming in full tog. I twig—I ain't wanted.
       Quite correct—Samivel is fly.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Puts his finger to his nose and Exit c.</stage>
     <stage>Enter MAY, L., in wedding dress.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, May darling! <stage>(takes her by the hand and kisses her)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(looking in)</stage> I saw you!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, C. L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Hang that boy! But never mind his impudence, my own little wife.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Not yet, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>In two hours.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>There's many a slip between the cup and the lip, you know. But as the clerks aren't come
       yet, I thought I might just look in and shew you <stage>(displays her dress)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Your wedding gown!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Yes. It's Mrs. Gibson's present, with such a kind note—and she insists on providing the
       wedding breakfast and she's sent in the most beautiful cake, and flowers from their own
       conservatory. My little room looks so pretty.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>It always looks pretty when thou art in it. I shall never miss the sun, even in Nicholas
       Lane, after we are married, darling.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! Robert, won't it be delightful? Me, house-keeper here, and you, messenger, and such a
       favorite too! And to think we owe all, to these good kind generous —There's only one thing I
       can't get off my mind.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>What's that?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Gibson doesn't know the truth about you. We should have told him before this.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>It's hard for a poor chap that's fought clear of the mud, to let go the rope he's holding
       to and slide back again. I'll tell him when I've been long enough here to try me, only wait a
       bit.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Perhaps you are right, dear. Sometimes the thought comes like a cloud across me. But you've
       never said how you like my dress. <stage>(displaying it)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="45"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I couldn't see it for looking at thy bonny face— but it's a grand gown. <stage>(get round
        at back to L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>And my own making! I forgot—Mrs. Jones is come, and Mrs. Willoughby. They're going to
       church with us you know — Emily looks so nice—she would so like to see the office, she says,
       if I might bring her in?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, yes! the place is free to the petticoats till business hours.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses L. and calls at door, L.)</stage> Come in, Emily.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MRS. GREEN JONES, L</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! Mr. Brierly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>While Robert does the honours of the office, I'll go and help Mrs. Willoughby to set out
       the breakfast. The white service looks so lovely, Robert, and my canary sings as I haven't
       heard him since I left the old lodgings. He knows there's joy in the wind.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(calling without, L.)</stage> Miss Edwards!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>There! I'm wanted. I'm coming, Mrs. Willoughby. Oh, dear! If I'd known the trouble it was
       to be married, I don't think I should have ventured. I'm coming.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(who has been looking about her)</stage> I did so want to see an office—a real one,
       you know. I've seen'em set on the stage often, but they ain't a bit like the real thing.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>They are but dull places. Not this one, though, since May's been housekeeper.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, they are dull, but so respectable—look so like money, you know. I suppose, now,
       there's no end of money passes here?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>A hundred thousand pounds a day, sometimes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Gracious goodness! All in sovereigns?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Not a farthing—all in cheques and bills. We've a few thousands, that a queer old fashioned
       depositor insists on Mr. Gibson keeping here, but except that, and the petty cash, there's no
       hard money in the place.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Dear me! I thought you City people sat on stools all day shovelling sovereigns about. Not
       that I could bear to think of Jones sitting on a stool all day, even to shovel about
       sovereigns, though he always says
       <pb n="46"/> something in the City would suit him better than the comic duet business. But he
       doesn't know what's good for him—never did, poor fellow.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Except when he married you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Well, I don't know about that, but I suppose he would have got through the property without
       me he's so much the gentleman, you know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>He's coming to church with us?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, yes! You know he's to give away the bride. But he was obliged to keep an appointment in
       the City first, so queer for Jones, wasn't it? He wouldn't tell me what it was.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(heard without, L. C.,)</stage> Two and six, my man. Very good, wait.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Here's your husband!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(looking through door, c.)</stage> In a cab—and a new coat and waistcoat, and
       trousers! Oh, Jones! Well, I shan't pay for them.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter GREEN JONES, L. C., in a gorgeous new suit.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(speaking off)</stage> Now, hand me out those parcels—yah, stupid, give me hold.
        <stage>(hands in parcels one by one)</stage> Here, bear a hand. <stage>(he pitches parcels
        to BRIERLY, who pitches them on to MRS. GREEN JONES, who deposits them on the counter,
        L.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(as first bonnet box comes in)</stage> Jones! <stage>(as second bonnet box comes
        in)</stage> Green! <stage>(as case of Eau-de-Cologne comes in)</stage> Green Jones!
        <stage>(glove box comes in)</stage> Oh! <stage>(two bouquets in paper are given in)</stage>
       Gracious goodness!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>There all out. Let's see—bonnets, Eau-de-Cologne, gloves, bouquets—seven ten; Two and six
       the cab—my own togs, five ten—that's thirteen two and six in all.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Jones, are you mad?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Is your principal here, Brierly?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>The governor? No, it's not his time yet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><hi>En attendant,</hi> you couldn't advance me thirteen two six, could you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>What! lend you the money?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(reproachfully)</stage> Oh, Jones! I'm afraid——
       <pb n="47"/> you're as great a fool as ever.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Emily, be calm. It's not the least consequence. They can wait—the shopman, I mean —that is—
       the two shopmen and cabby.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, he's gone crazy!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>The fact is, I've had a windfall. Choker Black has turned up trumps. He was put in the hole
       in California's year, had to bolt to Australia--struck an awfully full pocket at the
       diggings, and is paying off his old ticks like an emperor. He let me in for two thousand, and
       he has sent me bills for five hundred, as a first instalment.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Five hundred! And you've got the money?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>I've got the bills on his agent. Here they are. Emily, embrace your husband! <stage>(he
        kisses her)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> I wish you joy—both of you. Mr. Gibson will discount the bills for you
       as soon as he comes in.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> But, I say, cash, you know, no curious sherry--no old masters, or
       patent filters—I've had rather too much of that sort of thing in my time.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. who has been peeping into bonnet box)</stage> What a duck of a bonnet!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No, you're not among your old sixty per cent. friends here. We only do good bills at the
       market rate.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(who has opened glove box)</stage> And what loves of gloves!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>That's your sort. I feel now the full value of the commercial principle.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, Green! But you'll be careful of the money?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Careful! I'm an altered man. I swear—you'll allow me to register a vow in your office? —to
       devote myself to the virtuous pursuit of money-making. I'm worth five hundred pounds, I've
       fifteen hundred more coming in; — Not one farthing of that money shall go in foolish
       extravagance.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>But how about these things, Jones?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Trifles; —a <hi>cadeau de noce</hi> for the ladies, and a case of Eau-de-Cologne for
       myself. I've been running to seed so long, and want watering so much. <stage>(sprinkles
        himself with Eau-de-Cologne)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh dear, Green! I'm afraid you're as great a fool as ever.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="48"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Nay, nay, Mrs. Jones—no man's a fool with £500 in his pocket. But here come the
       clerks;—band-boxes and bouquets ain't business-like. You must carry these down to May.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(loading EMILY with the parcels)</stage> Beg her acceptance of a bonnet, a bouquet,
       and a box of Piver's seven and a quarter's; and accept the same yourself, from yours ever
       affectionately, G. J. <stage>(tries to kiss her over the parcels but cannot)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(from over the parcels)</stage> Oh, go along with your nonsense! I'll give you one
       down stairs.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit L. 1 E.</stage>
     <stage>Enter MR. BURTON and MR. SHARPE, clerks, L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M9">
      <speaker>Sharpe.</speaker>
      <p>Good morning. Governor come yet?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Not yet, Mr. Sharpe; it's getting near his time, though.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>
      <stage>(CLERKS hang up their hats, coats, &amp;c., and seat themselves at desks, L.)</stage>
     </stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M9">
      <speaker>Sharpe</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to MR. GREEN JONES)</stage> Can we do anything for you, sir?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(indicating GREEN JONES)</stage> This gentleman's waiting to see Mr. Gibson. Here he
       is.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MR. GIBSON, L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(rubbing his feet on the mat)</stage> Good morning, morning, Mr. Sharpe—good
       morning, Burton. Well, Robert—didn't expect to find you at the office this morning.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Here's a gentleman waiting for you, sir, on business.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>If you'll walk into my room, sir?</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit GREEN JONES into MR. GIBSON's room, R. 2 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> I thought I might as well number the cheques, sir, and go for the petty
       cash. Somehow, I felt I shouldn't like anything to go wrong to-day.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> Well, that's a very proper feeling. I hope May likes my wife's present.
       She is a first-rate house-keeper; though she <emph>did</emph> call <emph>you</emph> her
       brother, the little rogue—and I've every reason to be satisfied with you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I'm right proud of that, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>You won't mind my giving you a word of advice on your wedding-day? Go on as you've begun—
       keep a bright eye and an enquiring tongue in your head
       <pb n="49"/> —learn how business is done—watch the market—and from what I've seen of you the
       six months you've been here, I shouldn't wonder if I found a better berth than messenger for
       you one of these days.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Gibson—sir—I can't thank you—but a look-out like that—it takes a man's breath away.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>In the City there's no gap between the first round of the ladder and the top of the tree.
       But that gentleman's waiting. <stage>(pauses—goes to door, R.)</stage> By-the-way! I expect a
       call from a Mr. Hawkshaw.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(starting)</stage> Hawkshaw!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, the famous detective. Shew him in when he comes. I've a particular appointment with
       him.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MR. GIBSON into his own room, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Hawkshaw coming here! The principal witness against me at my trial. Perhaps he won't know
       me—I'm much changed. But they say, at Portland, he never forgets a face. If he knows me, and
       tells Mr. Gibson, he'll discharge me—and, to-day, just when we looked to be so happy! It
       would break May's heart. But why should I stay? I'm free for the day—I will not wait to meet
       my ruin. <stage>(going up, c.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter HAWKSHAW, L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Mr. Gibson within?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Yes, sir, but he has a gentleman with him.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Take in my name. <stage>(writes on card with pencil and gives it to BRIERLY)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(takes card and crossing to R. sees name on it— aside)</stage> Hawkshaw! It is too
       late! Would you like to look at the paper, sir? <stage>(offers him one from desk)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(as he takes it, gives a keen look of recognition at BRIERLY, who shrinks under his
        eye, but represses his agitation by an effort)</stage> I've seen you before, I think?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I don't recollect you, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(carelessly)</stage> Perhaps I'm wrong—though I've a good memory for faces. Take in
       my card. <stage>BRIERLY goes off, R., with card.</stage>
       <stage>(sits, L.)</stage> It's Dalton's pal—the youngster who got four years for passing
       forged Bank of England paper, at the Belle Vue Tea Gardens. I owe Master Dalton one for
       <pb n="50"/> that night yet. Back from Portland, eh? Looks all the better for his schooling.
       But Portland's an odd shop to take an office messenger from. I wonder if his employer got his
       character from his last place.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter BRIERLY, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Gibson will see you in a moment, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Very well. <stage>(gives him a look)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter GREEN JONES, from Mr. Gibson's room, R., with cheque.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to BRIELY)</stage> All right! Market rate—and no old masters. I'll drive to the
       bank—cash this—settle with those counter-skippers, and rattle back in time to see you turned
       off. I say you must allow me to order a little dinner at the "Star and Garter," and drive you
       down—all right, you know. Mail phæton and pair —your wife and my wife. I want to show you the
       style G. J. <emph>used</emph> to do it in. <stage>(goes up)</stage> Now, cabby, pull round.
        <stage>(speaking loud)</stage> London Joint Stock Bank! Best pace.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit GREEN JONES, L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> He little thinks what may be hanging over me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(appearing at the door of his room, R.)</stage> Now, Mr. Hawkshaw, I'm at your
       service.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses to R., then returning BRIERLY the paper)</stage> Cool case of note-passing
       that at Bow-street, yesterday. <stage>(BRIERLY winces—aside)</stage> It's my man, sure
       enough!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit into MR. GIBSON's room, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>He knows me —I can read it in his face—his voice. He'll tell Mr. Gibson! Perhaps he's
       telling him now! I wish I'd spoken to him—but they have no mercy. Oh, if I'd only made a
       clean breast of it to Mr. Gibson before this!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter GIBSON and HAWKSHAW from MR. GIBSON's room, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to first clerk)</stage> Mr. Sharpe; will you go round to the banks and see what's
       doing? <stage>SHARPE takes his hat and exit, L. C.</stage> Mr. Burton, you'll be just in time
       for morning's clearance.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="51"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M9">
      <speaker>Burton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(getting his hat—aside)</stage> By Jove, the governor wants to make a morning's
       clearance of us, I think. I'm half an hour too soon for the clearing house. —Time for a
       tip-top game at billiards.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Robert! <stage>(writing at desk, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Before you leave just step round to Glynn's and get me cash for this. You'll have time
       enough before you're wanted downstairs, you rascal.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> He knows nothing. <stage>(aloud)</stage> I'll be back in five
       minutes, sir. <stage>(as GIBSON is about to give him the cheque HAWKSHAW who is standing
        between GIBSON and BRIERLY, interposes and takes cheque carelessly)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Your messenger, eh?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Yes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Had him long?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Six months.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Good character?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Never had a steadier, soberer, better behaved lad in the office.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Had you references with him?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Why I think I took him mainly on the strength of his own good looks and his sweetheart's.
       An honest face is the best testimonial after all.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>H'm—neither is always to be relied on.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>You detectives would suspect your own fathers. Why how you look at the lad. Come, you've
       never had him through your hands. <stage>(a pause)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> No, he's quite a stranger to me. <stage>(turns away)</stage> Here's
       the cheque, young man. Take care you make no mistake about it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside, going, c.)</stage> Saved! saved! Heaven bless him for those words.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Poor devil, he's paid his debt at Portland. <stage>(aloud)</stage>
       Now to our business. You say a bill drawn by Vanzeller and Co. of Penang, on the London
       Joint-Stock Bank, was presented for discount here last night, which you know to be a
       forgery?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Yes. As it was after hours the clerk told the presenter to call this morning.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="52"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Bill forging is tip-top work. The man who did this job knows what he's about. We mustn't
       alarm him. What time did the clerk tell him to call?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>At eleven.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>It's within five minutes. You go to your room. I'll take my place at one of these desks as
       a clerk and send the customers in to you. When the forged bill is presented, you come to the
       door and say, loud enough for me to hear—"Vanzeller and Co., Penang," and leave the rest to
       me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(nervously)</stage> Hadn't I better have assistance within call?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Oh dear no—I like to work single handed— but don't be excited. Take it coolly, or you may
       frighten the bird. <stage>(goes to desk, L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Easy to say take it coolly! I haven't been thief catching all my life.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit GIBSON into his room, R.</stage>
     <stage>Enter MOSS, C., and down, C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(at the counter, getting out his bills)</stage> Let me see —Spelter and Wayne.
       Fifty, ten, three—thirty days after sight. That's commercial. <stage>(examining another
        bill)</stage> For two hundred at two months—drawn by Captain Crabos—accepted the Honourable
       Augustus Greenway: that's a thirty per center. Better try that at another shop. <stage>(takes
        out another)</stage> Mossop and Mills—good paper —ninety-nine, eight, two—at sixty days.
       That'll do here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(at door of his room, R.)</stage> Mr. Hawkshaw!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>H-sh! <stage>(crosses to R., warns him against using name, but obeys his call, and goes
        in)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(on hearing name)</stage> Hawkshaw! <stage>(with a quick glance as HAWKSHAW passes
        into MR. GIBSON's room)</stage> A detective here! Ware —hawk! <stage>(alarmed, but
        recovering)</stage> Well, it ain't for me— I'm all on the square, now. If bills will go
       missing—it ain't me that steals 'em—Tiger does that —I'm always a <hi>bonâ fide</hi> holder
       for value—I can face any examination, I can. But I should like to know Hawkshaw's little
       game, and I shouldn't mind spoiling it. <stage>Re-enter HAWKSHAW, R.</stage> Mr. Gibson, if
       you please?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="53"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>He's in his office, sir. <stage>(as MOSS passes in he recognizes him—Exit MOSS, R.)</stage>
       Melter Moss here! Can he be the forger? He heard my name. Dear, dear, to think that a
       business-man like Mr. Gibson should be green enough to call a man like me by his name.
        <stage>Re-enter MOSS, R.</stage> Here he comes, now for the signal. <stage>(goes to desk,
        L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(coming down with cheques and bill book)</stage> All right! Beautiful paper, most of
       it. Only two of 'em fishy. Well, I'll try them three doors down—they ain't so particular.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> No signal!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(in front of counter, L.)</stage> If you'll allow me, I'll take a dip of your ink,
       young man—I've an entry to make in my bill book. <stage>(HAWKSHAW pitches him a pen)</stage>
       Thank you. <stage>(MOSS writes)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter DALTON, L. C., dressed as a respectable elderly commercial man, in as complete
      contrast as possible with his appearance in first Act—comes down, C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Gibson? <stage>(takes out his bill case)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(at desk, L.)</stage> You'll find him in his office, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> That's not the young man I saw here yesterday afternoon.
        <stage>(aloud)</stage> Let me see first that I've got the bill. <stage>(rummages for
        bill)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(recognizing DALTON)</stage> Tiger here, in his City get up. Oh, oh! If this should
       be Hawkshaw's little game? I'll drop him a line. <stage>(writes, crosses to c., and passes
        paper secretly to DALTON, with a significant look, and taking care to keep behind the
        railing of the counter)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(recognizing him)</stage> Moss! <stage>(taking paper, reads)</stage> "Hawkshaw's at
       that desk." Forewarned, forearmed! <stage>(goes up)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(goes up, c.)</stage> There, I hope I've spoiled Hawkshaw's little game.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MOSS.</stage>
     <stage>MR. GIBSON appears at door of office, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(about to address HAWKSHAW again)</stage> Mr.—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(hastily interrupting him)</stage> H'sh! a party wants to see you, sir, if you could
       step this way, for a moment.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Would you oblige me, Mr. Gibson, by looking
       <pb n="54"/> very particularly at this bill. <stage>(gives it to GIBSON, who comes
        down)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> "Vanzeller and Co., Penang." <stage>(glances at HAWKSHAW, aside, who
        crosses and seats himself at desk, R.)</stage> He don't stir! "Vanzeller and Co., Penang."
        <stage>(aside)</stage> Confound it, I haven't made a blunder, have I! "Vanzeller and Co.,
       Penang." <stage>(HAWKSHAW prepares handcuffs under the desk)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, a most respectable firm. But all's not gold that glitters; I thought the paper as safe
       as you do; but, unluckily, I burnt my fingers with it once before. You may or may not
       remember my presenting a bill drawn by the same firm for discount two months ago.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, particularly well.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Well, sir, I have now discovered that was a forgery.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>So have I.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>And I'm sadly afraid, between you and me.— By the way, I hope I may speak safely before
       your clerk?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, quite.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I'm almost satisfied that this bill is a forgery too. The other has been impounded, I hear.
       My object in coming here yesterday was, first to verify, if possible, the forgery in the case
       of this second bill; and next, to ask your assistance, as you had given value for the first
       as well as myself, in bringing the forger to justice. <stage>(HAWKSHAW looks up as in
        doubt)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Really sir,—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, my dear sir! If we City men don't stand by each other in these rascally cases! But
       before taking any other step, there is one thing I owe to myself, as well as to you, and that
       is, to repay you the amount of the first forged bill.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>But you said you had given value for it?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>The more fool I! But if I am to pay twice, that is no reason you should be a loser. I've a
       memorandum of the amount here. <stage>(looks at his bill-book)</stage> Two hundred and
       twenty-seven—five. Here are notes—two hundreds a ten—and two fives—seven—and one—two —three.
        <stage>(counting out copper)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! pray, sir, don't trouble yourself about the coppers.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="55"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I'm particular in these matters. Excuse me It's a little peculiarity of mine
        <stage>(counting out coppers)</stage>— three—four—five. There! that's off my conscience! But
       you've not examined the notes. <stage>(HAWKSHAW pockets the handcuffs)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, my dear sir! <stage>(putting them up)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! careless, careless! <stage>(shakes his head)</stage> Luckily, I had endorsed 'em.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Really, sir, I had marked that two hundred and twenty off to bad debt a month ago. By the
       way, I have not the pleasure of knowing your name?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Wake, sir—Theophilus Wake, of the firm of Wake, Brothers, shippers and wharfingers,
       Limehouse, and Dock-street Liverpool. We have a branch establishment at Liverpool. Here's our
       card. <stage>(gives card)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>So far from expecting you to repay the money, I thought you were coming to bleed me afresh
       with forged bill No. 2—for a forgery it is, most certainly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Quite natural, my dear sir, quite natural—I've no right to feel the least hurt.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>And what's more, I had a detective at that desk ready to pounce upon you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>No, really!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>You can drop the clerk, now, Mr. Hawkshaw. <stage>(HAWKSHAW comes down, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Hawkshaw! Have I the honour to address Mr. Hawkshaw, the detective, the hero of the great
       gold dust robberies, and the famous Trunk-line-transfer forgeries? <stage>(crosses to
        c.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk</speaker>
      <p>I'm the man, sir. I believe —<stage>(modestly)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Sir, the whole commercial world owes you a debt of gratitude it can never repay. I shall
       have to ask your valuable assistance in discovering the author of these audacious
       forgeries.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Have you any clue?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> I believe they are the work of a late clerk of ours—who got into gay
       company, poor lad, and has gone to the bad. He knew the Vanzellers' signature, as they were
       old correspondents of ours.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Is the lad in London?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>He was within a week.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Can you give me a description of him? Age—
       <pb n="56"/> height—hair—eyes—complexion—last address—haunts —habits—associates,
        <stage>(significantly)</stage> any female connexion?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Unluckily I know very little or him personally. My partner, Walker Wake, can supply all the
       information you want.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Where shall I find him?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Here's our card. We'll take a cab and question him at our office. Or <stage>(as if struck
        by a sudden thought)</stage> suppose you bring him here—so that we may all lay our heads
       together.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>You'll not leave this office till I come back?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>If Mr. Gibson will permit me to wait.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> I shall feel extremely obliged to you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>You may expect me back in half an hour at farthest <stage>(going up c., returns)</stage>
       egad, sir, you've had a narrow escape. I had the darbies open under the desk. <stage>(shewing
        handcuffs)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Ha, ha, ha! how very pleasant. <stage>(takes and examines handcuffs curiously)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>But I'll soon be down on this youngster.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>If only he hasn't left London.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Bless you—they can't leave London. Like the moths, they turn and turn about the candle till
       they burn their wings.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! thanks to men like you. How little society is aware of what it owes its detective
       benefactors?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>There's the satisfaction of doing one's duty— and something else, now and then.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! a good round reward.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>That's not bad; but there's something better than that.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Indeed!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Paying off old scores. Now, if I could only clinch the darbies on Jem Dalton's wrists.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Dalton! What's your grudge against him in particular?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>He was the death of my pal, the best mate I ever had, poor Joe Skirrit. <stage>(draws his
        hand across his eyes)</stage> I shall never work with such another.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Did he murder him?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Not to say murder him right out. But he spoiled him—gave him a clip on the head with a
       neddy—
       <pb n="57"/> a life-preserver. He was never his own man afterwards. He left the force on a
       pension, but he grew sort of paralysed, and then got queer in his head. I was sitting with
       him the week before he died—"Jack," he says, it was Joe and Jack with us, "Jack," he says, "I
       lay my death at the Tiger's door"—that was the name we had for Dalton in the force. "You'll
       look after him, Jack," he says, "for the sake of your old mate." By— no, I won't say what I
       said, but I promised him to be even with Jem Dalton, and I'll keep my word.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> You know this Dalton?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Know him! He has as many outsides as he has aliases. You may identify
       him for a felon to-day, and pull your hat off to him for a parson to-morrow. But I'll hunt
       him out of all his skins;—and my best night's sleep will be the day I've brought Jem Dalton
       to the dock!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Hawkshaw, I wish you every success!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>But I've other fish to fry now. <stage>(going up, looks at card)</stage> Wake, brothers,
       Buckle's Wharf, Limehouse.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit HAWKSHAW, C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Ask anybody for our office! <stage>(aside)</stage> And if any body can tell you I
        <emph>shall</emph> be astonished <stage>(following him up then returning.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>I'm really ashamed to keep you waiting, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, I can write my letters here. <stage>(pointing to the counter)</stage> If you don't mind
       trusting me all alone in your office.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>My dear sir, if you were Dalton himself—the redoubtable Tiger—you couldn't steal ledgers
       and day-books, and there's nothing more valuable here—except, by the way, my queer old
       depositor, Miss Faddle's, five thousand, that she insists on Mr. Gibson keeping here in the
       office in gold, as she believes neither in banks nor bank-notes. And, talking of notes, I may
       as well lock up these you so handsomely paid me. <stage>(goes to safe, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Not believe in notes! Infatuated woman! <stage>(aside)</stage> I hope he'll like mine.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(locks safe)</stage> I'll leave you to write your letters.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MR. GIBSON into his office, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Phew! <stage>(whistles low)</stage> That's the narrowest shave I ever had! So, Jack
       Hawkshaw, you'll be even with Jem Dalton yet will you? You may add this day's
       <pb n="58"/> work to the score against him. How the old boy swallowed my soft sawder and
       Brummagem notes! They're beauties! It would be a pity to leave them in his hands —and five
       thousand shiners p'raps alongside of 'em. Come—I've my wax handy—never travel without my
       tools. Here goes for a squeeze at the lock of this safe. <stage>(goes to safe, R., and by
        means of a pick-lock applies wax to the wards of the lock by the key-hole—Music,
        piano)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter BRIERLY, C. from L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(hangs up hat, L.)</stage> Clerks not returned. Hawkshaw gone? <stage>(sees DALTON
        at safe)</stage> Holloa! who's this? Tampering with the safe? Hold hard there! <stage>(he
        seizes DALTON, who turns)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside, R.)</stage> Brierly! Hands off, young'un. Don't you know a locksmith when
       you see him ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Gammon! Who are you? How came you here? What are you doing with that
       safe?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>You ask a great deal too many questions.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I'll trouble you to answer 'em.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>By what right?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I'm messenger in this office, and I've a right to know who touches a lock here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>You messenger here? Indeed! and suppose I took to asking questions you mightn't be so keen
       of answering yourself—Robert Brierly!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>You know me!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Yes. And your character from your last place—Port—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(terrified)</stage> Hush!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Your hair hasn't grown so fast but I can see traces of the prison-crop.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>For mercy's sake!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Silence for silence. Ask me no questions and I'll press for no answers.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>You must explain your business here to Mr. Gibson. I suspected you for a thief.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>And I know you for a jail-bird. Let's see whose information will go the farthest. There,
       I'll make you a fair offer, Robert Brierly. Let me pass, and [ leave this place without
       breathing a word to your employer that you're fresh from a sentence of penal
       <pb n="59"/> servitude for four years. Detain me, and I denounce you —for the convict you
       are! <stage>(a knock at the door, L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(without)</stage> Mr. Brierly!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Hush! Coming, Mrs. Willoughby.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Is it a bargain?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Go—go—anything to escape this exposure. <stage>(giving him his hat, &amp;c. from counter,
        L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(at door)</stage> There's Aby Moss, waiting for me outside. He shall blow the lad to
       Gibson. He may be useful to us, and I owe him one for spoiling my squeeze.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit DALTON, L. C.</stage>
     <stage>Enter MRS. WILLOUGHBY, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Which, I've to ask pardon for intruding, not bein' used to an office, and knowing my place
       I 'ope. But it's gettin' on for a quarter past eleven, Mr. Robert, and twelve's the latest
       they will do it, and the breakfast all set out beautiful and some parties is a gettin'
       impatient, which it's no more than natural, bless her, and Sam that rampagious — But
       whatever's the matter? You look struck all of a heap like?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, nothing, nothing. It's natural, you know, a man should look queer on his wedding
       morning. There, go and tell May I'll be with her directly.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter SAM, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Come along, Bob, we're all tired of waiting, especially this child. <stage>(sings nigger
        song)</stage> Come along!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(admiringly)</stage> Oh, that boy! If it ain't enough to make any grandmother's
       'eart proud.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Go—go—I'll follow you—I've some business matters to attend to.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>A nice state for business you're in—I don't think— There, granny. <stage>(looks at
        him)</stage> This is what comes of getting married! If it ain't an awful warning to a young
       fellow like me!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Drat your imperence.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>But the party's waiting down stairs, and we're wanted to keep 'em in spirits, so come
       along, granny.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Polks out with MRS. WILLOUGHBY, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Known! Threatened! Spared by Hawkshaw— only to be denounced by this man</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="60"/>
     <stage>Enter MOSS, L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Gibson, if you please?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>He's in his office, sir—that way. <stage>(points to open door, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>I remember the young man now. A convict get himself into a respectable situation. It is a
       duty one owes to society to put his employer on his guard. <stage>(Exit, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Yes—he's gone — I can draw my breath again— I was wrong to let him go. But to have the cup
       at one's lip, and see it struck away—I couldn't—I couldn't—even the detective had mercy. When
       we're married, I'll tell Mr. Gibson all.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter MOSS and MR. GIBSON from his office, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>You can question him, sir, if you don't believe me: any way I've done my duty, and that's
       what I look to.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MOSS, L. C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Here's the money for the cheque, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>GIBSON takes money—BRIERLY is going, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Robert.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Where are you going?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>To dress for church, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Stay here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Sir!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>You have deceived me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Gibson—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>I know all—your crime—your conviction— your punishment!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Mercy! Mercy!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>Unhappy young man.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! unhappy you may well call me. I was sentenced, sir, but I was not guilty. It's true,
       sir, but I don't expect you to believe it—I've worked out my sentence, sir—they hadn't a mark
       against me at Portland —you may ask 'em—here's my ticket-of-leave, sir. You own I've been
       steady and industrious since I came here. By heaven's help I mean to be so still, indeed I
       do.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Mr. G.</speaker>
      <p>I dare say, but I must think of my own credit and character. If it was buzzed about that I
       kept a ticket-of-leave man in my employment—</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="61"/>
     <stage>Enter GREEN JONES, C. down R., and MAY, EMILY, MRS. WILLOUGHBY, and SAM, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Which, axin' your pardon, Mr. Gibson, we're all ready, and the cab is a
       waitin'</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> And the parson getting cold.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Robert, why are you not dressed? What is the matter?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Heaven help thee, my poor lass.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>You are pale you tremble—you are ill! Oh, speak, what is it?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Bear up, May. But our marriage—cannot— be—yet—awhile.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p>The wedding put off! <stage>(MAY stands aghast)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>No bonnets!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>And no breakfasts!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>By Jove!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Here's a-go!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>(together)</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Am I dreaming! Robert—what does this mean?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>It's hard to bear. Keep up your heart— I'm discharged. He knows all.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to MR. GIBSON)</stage> Oh, sir, you couldn't have the heart—say it is not true.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Gibson.</speaker>
      <p>Sorry for it. You have both deceived me— you must both leave the place.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>You hear—Come, May.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I'll go, sir. It was I deceived you, not he. Only give him a chance—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Never heed her, sir. <stage>(music—piano till end)</stage> She'd have told you long ago,
       but I hadn't the heart—My poor lass! Let her bide here sir—I'll not trouble you I'll leave
       the country— I'll list.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Hush, hush, Robert! We were wrong to hide the truth; we are sorely punished but if
        <emph>you've</emph> courage to face what's before us, <emph>I</emph> have.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>My brave wench! Thank you for all your kindness, sir. Good bye, friends. Come, May, we'll
       go together.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>GREEN. GIBSON. BRIER. MAY. MRS. W. SAM. EMILY.</stage>
     <stage>R.</stage>
     <stage>L.</stage>
     <trailer>END OF ACT THIRD.</trailer>
    </div>
   </div>




   <div type="act" n="4">
    <pb n="62"/>
    <head>ACT IV.</head>
    <div type="scene" n="1">
     <head>SCENE FIRST.— The Bridgewater Arms</head>
     <stage>—A large gaily decorated Coffee Room, set out with tables and benches, a bar crosses the
      corner of room, up L., with gaily painted hogsheads ranged above it; beer engine, &amp;c., at
      the head of bar, L. C.; door to street in flat, R.; door to parlour, R. 2 E.; curtained
      windows in flat; a piano L.; a trap leading to cellar, practicable, up stage, C., near the end
      of the bar; table and three chairs in front, R.; table and benches, up L.; table and benches
      at back, R. MOSS with bags of silver, and DALTON seated at table, R. —MALTBY waiting upon
      them.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(at back of table, R.)</stage> Pint of sherry. <stage>(putting it down)</stage> Very
       curious! — Yes, Mr. Moss, it's a pleasure to see you, sir, at the Bridgewater Arms; though it
       aint the Belle Vue Gardens! worse luck!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. of table)</stage> Ah! ups and downs is this lot of life, Mr. Maltby. You'll let
       me know when Mr. Tottie comes?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, the subcontractor for the main sewer in the next street. Such a nuisance! stops all
       traffic—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>But sends you all the navvies. It's here they're taken on, and paid you know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Connexion not aristocratic, but beery; we do four butts a-week at the bar, to say nothing
       of the concert room up stairs.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. of table, R.)</stage> What, the navvies like music to their malt, do they?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, yes, sir! I introduced the arts from the West End. The roughs adore music, especially
       selections from the Italian Opera, and as for sentiment and sensation, if you could hear Miss
       St. Evremond touch them up with the "Maniac's Tear," the new sensation ballad, by a gifted
       composer, attached to the establishment, and sold at the bar, price one shilling: why we've
       disposed of three dozen "Maniac's Tears" on a pay night —astonishing how it goes down!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>With the beer?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="63"/>
     <stage>Enter MRS. GREEN JONES, door in flat, and comes down, L. —she wears a handsome evening
      dress under her shawl.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c. coming forward to her)</stage> Here comes Mrs Jones—gentlemen, this is the great
       and gifted creature I was alluding to.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Go along with your nonsense!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Miss St. Evremond, the great sensation balladist, formerly of the Nobility's Concerts, and
       her Majesty's Theatre—<stage>(aside)</stage>—in the ballet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Proud to make the acquaintance of so gifted an artiste.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>You're very obliging, I'm sure. <stage>(taking off her bonnet and shawl, and smoothing her
        hair, to MALTBY)</stage> How's the room to night?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Tidy, but nothing to what it will be. It's the navvies pay-night you know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Navvies! oh lord! <stage>(sighs)</stage> to think of Emily St. Evremond wasting her
       sweetness upon an audience of navigators!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>They are not aristocratic, but they are appreciative.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Yes! poor creatures! they do know a good thing when they hear it! <stage>(to
        MALTBY)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>If Miss St. Evremond will oblige us with a ballad—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>The Maniac's Tear.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>If these gentlemen wouldn't mind.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>On the contrary—we like music; don't we, Moss?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>I doat upon it; especially Handel!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>But where's the accompanist?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>I regret to say the signor is disgracefully screwed!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, never mind, Jones can accompany me! <stage>(going up)</stage> Come in, Green Jones;
       you're wanted!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>
      <stage>(MALTBY opens piano)</stage>
     </stage>
     <stage>Enter GREEN JONES with a basket of trotters, door in flat— they both come down,
      L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>In the trotter line, or the tuneful?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="64"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>To accompany me on the piano! <stage>(she arranges her hair)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Till you're ready, these gentlemen wouldn't like to try a trotter would they? A penny a
       set, and of this morning's boiling—if I might tempt you? They're delicious with a soupçon of
       pepper.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>No, no, Mr. Jones, these are not your style of customers.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Excuse me, Mr. Maltby, I'm aware trotters are not known in good society; but they go down
       as a relish, even with people accustomed to entreés! I liked 'em as a swell before I was
       reduced to them as a salesman.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c. to MRS. GREEN JONES)</stage> Perhaps you'd give us the Maniac's Tear?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> I can't do it without letting down my back hair!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Oh, down with the back hair, by all means!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>You're very kind. Jones! Where's the glass?</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>(JONES produces hand-glass from basket—EMILY arranges her hair by glass)</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.—seating himself at the piano)</stage> One word of preface, gentlemen! It's a
       sensation ballad! scene— Criminal Ward, Bedlam! Miss St. Evremond is an interesting
       lunatic—with lucid intervals. She has murdered her husband— <stage>(finds basket in his
        way)</stage> Emmy! if you'd just shift those trotters —and her three children, and is
       supposed to be remonstrating with one of the lunacy commissioners on the cruelty of her
       confinement!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage><stage>(Music—</stage>EMILY sings a sensation ballad, "The Maniac's Tear," accompanied
      by her husband—all applaud)</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(going off)</stage> Now—look sharp, Miss St. Evremond. The Wisconsin Warblers are at
       their last chorus.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MALTBY, L. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to her husband)</stage> Bye-bye, dear, till after the oncert—you know I can't be
       seen speaking to you while you carry that basket.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>True—in the humble trotter-man who would suspect the husband of the brilliant St. Evremond!
       There's
       <pb n="65"/> something romantic in it—I hover round the room—I hear you universally
       admired—visibly applauded—audibly adored. Oh, agony!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Now, Jones—you are going to be jealous again! I do believe jealousy's at the bottom of
       those trotters!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MRS. and MR. GREEN JONES, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Now's our time while the fools upstairs are having their ears tickled. You've the tools
       ready for jumping that crib in St. Nicholas Lane?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, but tools ain't enough—I must have a clear stage, and a pal who knows the
       premises.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>I've managed that nobody sleeps in the place but the old housekeeper and her precious
       grandson.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>He's as sharp as a terrier dog—and can bite too a young varmint. If I come across him.
        <stage>(threateningly)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>No occasion for that— you're so violent. I've made the young man's acquaintance. I've asked
       him to meet me here to-night for a quiet little game—his revenge, I called it. I'll dose the
       lad till he's past leaving the place. You drop a hint to the old lady—she'll come to take
       care of him. The coast will be clear yonder.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>And the five thousand shiners will be nailed in the turning of a jemmy. If we had that
       young Brierly in the job—he knows the way about the place blindfold. But he's on the square,
       he is —bent on earning an honest livelihood.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>But I've blown him wherever he's got work. He must dance to our tune at last!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! if you've got him in hand! Work him into the job, and I'll jump the crib to-night.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>He's applied to be taken on at the contract works near here. This is the pay night—Tottie,
       the sub-contractor, is a friend of mine—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>He's lucky!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Yes. I find him the cash at twenty per cent, till his certificates are allowed by the
       engineer. 'Taint heavy interest, but there's no risk--a word from me, and he'd discharge
       every navvie in his gang. But I've only
       <pb n="66"/> to breathe jail-bird, and there's no need of a discharge. The men themselves
       would work the lad off the job. They are sad roughs, but they've a horror of jail-birds.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Ah! nobody likes the Portland mark. I know that I've tried the honest dodge, too.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>It don't answer.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>It didn't with me. I had a friend, like you, always after me. Whatever I tried, I was blown
       as a convict, and hunted out from honest men.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>And then you met me and I was good to you —wasn't I?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Yes. You were very kind.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Always allowed you handsome for the swag you brought, and put you up to no end of good
       things! and I'll stick by you, my dear—I never drop a friend.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>No, till the hangman takes your place at his side. <stage>(presses his elbows to his side
        in the attitude of a man pinioned)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Don't be disagreeable, my dear—you give me a cold shiver. Hush! here come the navvies.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter the NAVIGATORS noisily, through door in flat R. C. They seat themselves at their
      tables, R. and L., calling, some for pots of beer, some for quarterns of gin. POTMAN and
      WAITERS bustle about, with MALTBY superintending and taking money. BRIERLY follows. Enter
      HAWKSHAW, door in flat, R. C., disguised as a navvy. He appears flustered with drink—goes to
      one of the tables, L., and assuming a country dialect, calls swaggeringly.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Gallon 'o beer! measter.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>A gallon?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Aye, and another when that's done—I'm in brass to night, and I stand treat. Here, mates,
       who'll drink? <stage>(NAVVIES crowd, with loud acclamations to his table, beer is
        brought—HAWKSHAW to BRIERLY, who is seated L. of table)</stage> Come, won't thou drink, my
       little flannel back.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No, thank you; I've a poor head for liquor, and I've not had my supper yet.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="67"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Thou'st sure it's not pride?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Pride? I've no call for pride—I've come to try and get taken on at the works.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Well, thou looks a tough 'un. There's cast-iron Jack was smashed in the tunnel this
       morning. There'll be room for thee, if thou canst swing the old anchor.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>The old anchor?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Ha, ha! It's easy to see thou's no banker. Why, the pick to be sure —the groundsman's
       bread- winner. Halloa, mates, keep a drop for Ginger. <stage>(goes back to table)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>Navvies.</speaker>
      <p>Aye, aye!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Here's the old anchor, boys, and long may we live to swing it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p>The pick for ever! Hip, hip, hurrah!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(coming down, R.)</stage> Mr. Tottie's in the parlour, and wishes particularly to
       see you, Mr. Moss.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>I should think he did —say I'm coming.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MALTBY, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside to Moss)</stage> You look after the Lancashire lad—yonder he sits and I'll
       drop a hint to the old woman. Stay, we'd better work from the old church yard of St.
       Nicholas—there's a door opens into it from the crib. I'll hide the tools behind one of the
       tombstones.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Beautiful! Sacred to the memory of Jem Dalton's jack-in-the-box! Ha, ha, ha!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exeunt, MOSS into parlour, R., DALTON by the street door, R. in flat.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Here, landlord, take your change out of that. <stage>(flings a sovereign on table)</stage>
       Call for more beer, mates, till I come back.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, staggering like a drunken man after DALTON.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>1st Navvy.</speaker>
      <p>Thou'llt come back, mate?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(at door)</stage> Aye, aye, boys, directly. Contractor's in 't parlour wi' the
       week's pay.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>1st Navvy.</speaker>
      <p>Here's thy health!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(sing)</stage> "For he's a jolly good fellow," &amp;c.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter GREEN JONES, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Emily is bringing down the house in the
       <pb n="68"/> Maniac; I can't stand it; my feelings as a husband are trampled on! But she's a
       trump, too, and what a talent! By heaven, if ever I get my head above water again, I won't
       fool away my money as I've done; no, I'll take a theatre at the west end, and bring out my
       wife in everything. It will be an immense success; meanwhile, 'till the pounds present
       themselves, let me look after the pence. Trotters, gents, trotters, penny the set, and this
       morning's boiling. <stage>(he goes up among tables)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M13">
      <speaker>1st Navvy.</speaker>
      <p>Stop till we get brass, we'll clear out thy basket.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit NAVVIES, R. door, followed by GREEN JONES.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, the old anchor is my last chance—I've tried every road to an honest livelihood, and,
       one after another, they are barred in my face. Everywhere that dreadful word, jail-bird,
       seems to be breathed in the air about me—sometimes in a letter, sometimes in a hint,
       sometimes a copy of the newspaper with my trial, and then it is the same story, sorry to part
       with me, no complaint to make, but can't keep a ticket-of-leave man. Who can it be that hunts
       me down in this way? Hawkshaw spared me; I've done no man a wrong—poor fellows like me should
       have no enemies. I wouldn't care for myself, but my poor lass, my brave true-hearted May; I'm
       dragging her down along with me. Ah! here she is.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MAY EDWARDS, poorly dressed—she has a can and some food in a bundle, door in flat,
      and comes down, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(cheerfully)</stage> Well, Robert, dear, I said I shouldn't be long; I've brought
       your supper.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Thank thee, darling—I'm not hungry— thou'st been out after work all
       day—eat thyself—thou need'st strength most.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(on his L.)</stage> Nay, dear, what will become of me if you lose heart? But if
       you'll be a good boy, and take your tea, <stage>(gets round in front to R., opens tin, and
        takes bread from bundle)</stage> I'll tell you a piece of good news— for you —for both of
       us.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>That will be something new.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I've got a promise of work from the Sailor's Ready Made Clothing Warehouse near here. It
       won't
       <pb n="69"/> be much, but it will keep the wolf from the door till you get another situation.
       Have you tried if the contractor here will take you on?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Not yet. He's in yonder paying the men. He'll send for me; but I scarcely dare to ask him.
       Oh! May, lass, I've held on hard to hope, but it feels as if it was slipping out of my hand
       at last.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Robert, dear Robert, grasp it hard; so long as we do what is right, all will come clear at
       last; we're in kind hands, dear—you know we are.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I begin to doubt it, lass—I do, indeed.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>No, no; never doubt that, or my heart will give way too—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>And thou that has had courage for both of us. Every blow that has fallen, every door that
       has been shut between me and an honest livlihood, every time that clean hands have been drawn
       away from mine, and respectable faces turned aside as I came near them, I've come to thee for
       comfort, and love, and hope, and I've found them till now.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, yes! what's the good of a sunshine wife? It's hard weather tries us women best, dear,
       you men ain't half so stout-hearted.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I'd not mind the misery so much for myself, 'tis for thee.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>I don't complain—do I?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Never! But, nevertheless, I've brought thee to sorrow, and want, and shame. Till I came
       back to thee thou hadst friends, work, and comforts. But since Mr. Gibson discharged us off,
       the blight that has followed me, has reached thee too, the bravest, honestest, brightest lass
       that ever doubled a man's joys, and halved his burdens. Oh! it's too bad;
        <stage>(rises)</stage> it kills the heart out of me—it makes me mad! <stage>(crosses to
        R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(following him)</stage> I tell you, 'twill all come clear at last, if we are only
       true to ourselves —to each other. I've work promised, and perhaps you may be taken on here. I
       spy bright days before us still.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Bright days! I can't see them through the prison cloud that stands like a dark wall between
       me and honest labour. May, lass, I sometimes think I had
       <pb n="70"/> better let it all go—run—'list—make a hole in the water, anything that would rid
       thee of me; thou could'st make thy way alone.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, Robert, that is cruel! nothing others could do to us could hurt me like those words
       from you; we are man and wife, and we'll take life as man and wife should, hand-in-hand:
       where you go. I will go; where you suffer, I will be be there to comfort; and when better
       times come, as come they will—we will thank God for them together.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I'll try to hope.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>And you won't heed the black thoughts that come over you when you're alone?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I'll do my best to fight 'em off.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>That's a brave dear; I'm only going to the warehouse, I shall be back soon. Good-bye,
       dearest. Remember, when the clouds are thickest, the sun still shines behind them.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, door in flat.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Bless that brave bright heart; she puts strength into me, in spite of the devilish doubts
       that have got their claws about my throat. Yes, I will try once more. <stage>(the NAVIGATORS
        come noisily out of parlour, R., and re-seat themselves at the tables, R. and
       L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MOSS, from parlour, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(speaking off)</stage> So, all paid at last?</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter DALTON, door in flat, and HAWKSHAW, after him.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(down, R., to MOSS)</stage> All right, the lad's coming. I've tipped the old woman
       the office, and planted the tools. <stage>(at table, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses to L., then tapping BRIERLY on the shoulder)</stage> All the gang ha'
       gotten their brass—Tottie's takin' on men now, my little flannel-back. Thou go in, and put on
       a bold face—Tottie likes chaps as speaks up to him. <stage>(HAWKSHAW returns to his
        MATES)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>If this chance fail—God, help us both!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit into parlour, R. 1 E. (NAVVIES at the table, clamour and fight, and shout over
      their drink, MOSS glances at BRIERLY as he passes)</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>There he goes! <stage>(NAVVIES clamour)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="71"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>It would be a pity to let a ticket-of-leave man in among all those nice, sober,
       well-behaved young men. <stage>(clamour)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>I must blow him again; he ought to be near the end of his tether, now. <stage>Enter SAM
        WILLOUGHBY, door in flat, and comes down, C.</stage> Here comes our young friend.
        <stage>(coaxingly to SAM WILLOUGHBY)</stage> Ah, my dear—so you've come out for a little
       hanky-panky with old Moss. Sit down. My friend, Mr. Walker. What'll you have?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>I don't care—I'm game for anything from sherry to rum-shrub. Suppose we begin with a brandy
       and soda, to cool the coppers?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(calls)</stage> Brandy and soda, Maltby.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>I had an awful go in of it last night at the balls, and dropped into a lot of 'em, like a
       three-year-old! <stage>(imitates action of billiard-play with his walking-cane for a
        cue)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Billiards, too! Lord! what a clever young chap you are! <stage>(MALTBY brings soda water
        and brandy)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(sits at back of table)</stage> Yes, I know a thing or two, <stage>(takes
        glass)</stage> I wasn't born blind, like a terrier pup— I rayther think. But you promised me
       my revenge, you old screw. <stage>(drinks)</stage> That's the tipple to steady a chap's hand.
       Now, fork out the pictures, old boy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(shuffling cards, R.)</stage> Oh, what a boy you are! What shall it be this
       time?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>A round or two of brag to begin with, and a few deals at Blind Hookums for a wind up.
        <stage>(as he deals, enter BRIERLY from inner room, R.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Heaven be thanked, another chance yet!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(as BRIERLY passes)</stage> Well, my little flannel-back, has he taken you on?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, I'm to come to work to-morrow morning. I'm in Ginger's gang.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>I'm Ginger. Come, let's wet thy footing.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>My last shilling! <stage>(throws it down)</stage> It's all I have, but you're welcome.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Nay, it shan't be said Ginger Bill ever cleared a chap out neither. I'll pay for thy
       footing, and thou'lt stand beer thy first pay night. Here, measter, a gallon
       <pb n="72"/> to wet t' new chap's name. Bob, we'll christen thee, cause thou hadst but a
       shillin'—Ha, ha, ha!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>Navvies.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(laugh they all drink)</stage> Here's Bob's health!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. C., recognizing SAM)</stage> Sam Willoughby, in this place, and over the devil's
       books, too. Oh! I'm sorry to see this —sorry —sorry. Poor old woman! If she knew!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(calling)</stage> Best card! <stage>(shewing a card)</stage> First stake!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Stop a minute—ace of diamonds!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>First stake to you. Hang it! never mind, <stage>(deal)</stage> one can't lose much at this
       game—I go a tizzy <stage>(puts a stake on cards)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>A shilling.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Five.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I stand.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Ten.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>A sovereign! thirty-one! Third stake, and the brag. <stage>(shews his cards)</stage> Pair
       royal—pair—ace of spades. Fork over the shiners.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, dear! oh, dear! I'm ruined—ruined. <stage>(pays sovereign)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(calls)</stage> Two colds without.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Now, for my deal. <stage>(he deals three cards to each— MALTBY brings brandy)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Best card! First stake. I stand.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>I brag. Hang peddling with tizzies—half a crown.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Five. <stage>(MOSS looks at SAM's hand, and signals to DALTON)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Ten.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>A sovereign.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! dear, what a boy it is! How much have you got in your pocket?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Lots! I'm paid quarterly now. Had my quarter to-day! Another cold without.
        <stage>(calls)</stage> Let's see—I'll hold on. <stage>(draws card)</stage>
       Thirty-four—overdrawn—confound it! Now let's see your hand. <stage>(to DALTON)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Three pairs—fives, trays, deuces, and the knave of clubs.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Hang it all! How is a man to stand against such cards?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="73"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>How is a man to stand against such play? He was looking over your cards, and
        see—<stage>(seizing a card from MOSS's lap)</stage> —the ace of diamonds! Handy to make
       pairs royal! Sam, if you won't believe me, believe your own eyes: you're being cheated,
       robbed. You old villain—you should be ashamed of yourself!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! dear, oh, dear! to say such things to a man at my time of life.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>We're not to be bullied.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(threateningly)</stage> You give me back my money! <stage>(MALTBY comes
        down)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>I shan't! Here, Mr. Maltby.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Come, be off. I can't have any disturbance here, Mr. Moss is a most respectable man, and
       his friends are as respectable as he is, and as for you if you won't leave the room
       quietly—you must be made to.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Who'll make me? Come on, <stage>(squaring)</stage> both of you! Stand up to 'em, Bob, I'm
       not afraid! <stage>(NAVIGATORS gather round)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MRS. WILLOUGHBY, door in flat.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> It's his voice—which well I know it. Oh! Sam—Sam, I've found you at
       last!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Well, suppose you have—what then?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>What then! Oh! dear—oh! dear. And I've run myself into that state of trimmle and
       perspiration, and if it hadn't been for the gentleman I might have been east, and west, and
       high, and low, but it's at the "Bridgewater Arms," you'll find him he says—and here I have
       found you, sure enough—and you come 'ome with me this minute.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Ah! you'd better go home with the old lady!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> And if you take my advice, you'll send him to bed without his
       supper.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(C., MRS. WILLOUGHBY pushing him away)</stage> I ain't a going. Now, you give me my
       money—I'm not going to stand any nonsense.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> And this is what he calls attending elocution class of a night, and
       improvin' of his mind— and me a toilin' and a moilin' for him which I'm his own
       <pb n="74"/> grandmother, gentlemen, and him the only one of three. <stage>(still holding
        him)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>It's no use, Granny, I'm not a child to be tied to your apron strings—you've no right to be
       naggin' and aggravatin', and coming after a chap, to make him look small this way. I don't
       mind—I shan't stir. There! <stage>(he flings down his cap on the table, and sits on it,
        swinging his legs)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mr. W.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! dear—oh! dear—he'll break my heart, he will.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> Sam, my lad, listen to me, if you won't hearken to her.
        <stage>(crosses, L.)</stage> A bad beginning makes a bad end, and you're beginning badly:
       the road you're on leads downwards, and once in the slough at the bottom o't—oh! trust one
       who knows it—there's no working clear again. You may hold out your hand—you may cry for help
       you may struggle hard—but the quicksands are under your foot—and you sink down, down, till
       they close over your head.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(seated, L.)</stage> Hear the little flannel-back. He talks like a missionary, he
       do. <stage>(all laugh)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Go home, my lad—go home with her—be a son to her —love her as she has loved thee—make her
       old days happy—be sober, be steady, and when you're a grown man, and her chair's empty at
       t'chimney corner, you'll mayhap remember this day, and be thankful you took the advice of
       poor, hunted-down, broken-hearted Bob Brierly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(who has betrayed signs of feeling while BRIERLY has been speaking)</stage> I don't
       know —I feel so queer—and —don't look at me. <stage>(to MRS. WILLOUGHBY—gets off table
        crosses to her)</stage> I've been a regular bad'un, Granny—I'm very sorry I'll put on the
       curb—I'll pull up —that is, I'll try.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(rises)</stage> Oh! bless him for those words! Bless you! my own dear boy.
        <stage>(crosses to BRIERLY)</stage> And you too, Mr. Brierly—which if the widow's blessing
       is worth while it's yours, and many of them. Oh! dear— oh! dear. <stage>(cries—gets out her
        handkerchief, and in doing so drops her purse and keys—MOSS picks up the purse— MRS.
        WILLOUGHBY catches his eye as he does so—DALTON unobserved by all picks up the
       keys)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="75"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(passes back to L.)</stage> Nay, don't thank me. It's late now. Go home—Sam, give
       her your arm.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Here's your purse, old lady. <stage>(making a final attempt on SAM)</stage> What, you won't
       stay and make a night of it?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>I'll trouble you not to speak to my grandson. If ever an old man was ashamed of his grey
       hairs, it's you ought to be. Come, Sam.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Baulked.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>No—I didn't give her back her keys.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(turning to MOSS)</stage> If I wasn't a going to turn over a new leaf—Oh, wouldn't I
       like to pitch into you!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit SAM and MRS. WILLOUGHBY.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(pretending to be very drunk)</stage> And so should I —an old varmint and so would
       all of us; —you're bad enough for a tommy shop-keeper.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>Navvies.</speaker>
      <p>Aye that he is— ought to be ashamed of himself.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses to c.)</stage> And who accuses me? A nice chap, this, to take away honest
       folk's characters!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Stow that! He's one of <emph>us</emph> now—a regular blue-stocking. Tottie's taken him on!
       He's paid his footing—eh, mates?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p>Aye—Aye.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Here's Bob's health, mates.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p>Aye—Aye.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Stop; <stage>(goes up c. towards L. table)</stage> before you drink that health, best know
       the man you're drinking to. You're a rough lot, I know; but you're honest men.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, man, if you've a heart —<stage>(rises)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>I owe you one—I always pay my debts— <stage>(to NAVVIES)</stage> You're not felons, nor
       company for felons—for jail-birds.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p>Jail-birds!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Aye—jail-birds. Ask him how long it is since he served his four years at Portland.
        <stage>(HAWKSHAW goes up, crosses, and sits quietly at head of table, L.)</stage> Look!— he
       turns pale—his lip falls; he can't deny it. <stage>(BRIERLY turns away)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Who knows, lads—perhaps he's repented.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="76"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p>No—no. <stage>(grumbling)</stage> No jail-bird—no convict— no ticket-of-leaver. —
        <stage>(they turn away from BRIERLY)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Aye, mates—it's true I was convicted, but I wasn't guilty. I served my time. I came out an
       altered man. I tried hard to earn an honest livelihood <stage>(they all turn away)</stage>
       Don't all turn away from me! Give me a chance—only a chance.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p>No—no.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Nay, then, my last hope is gone—I can fight no longer! <stage>(throws his head on his hands
        in despair)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>The NAVIGATORS retire up, HAWKSHAW pretending to be very drunk, appears to sleep with
      head on table. The NAVIGATORS drop off, and exit D. F. one by one.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to DALTON)</stage> Honesty's bowled out at last! It's our game now. <stage>(puts
        his hand on BRIERLY'S shoulder)</stage> I say, my friend—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Eh? <stage>(looking up)</stage> You! The man who told them! <stage>(fiercely)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L.)</stage> Yes—yes; but don't put yourself in a passion.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Only tell me —Is it you who have followed me in this way?—who have turned all against
       me?—who have kept me from earning honest bread?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Yes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>But why, man, why? I had done you no wrong.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Ask him. <stage>(pointing to DALTON)</stage> He's an old friend of yours.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I don't know him—yet—I've seen that face before. Yes, it is—Jem Downy! Thou villain!
        <stage>(he seizes him)</stage> I know thee now. Thou shalt answer to me for all this
       misery.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Easy does it, Bob. Hands off, and let's take things pleasantly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Not content with leading me into play, and drink, and devilry, with making me your tool,
       with sending me to a prison, it's you that have dogged me —have denounced me as a
       convict.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Of course you didn't think any but an old friend would have taken such an interest in
       you.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="77"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Did you want to close all roads against me but that which leads to the dock?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Exactly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(turns to MOSS)</stage>
      </p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Exactly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>You see, when a man's in the mud himself and can't get out of it, he don't like to see
       another fight clear. Come, honest men won't have anything to do with you—best try the black
       sheep—we ain't proud. <stage>(all sit, R.)</stage> We've a job in hand will be the making of
       all three. <stage>(fills his glass)</stage> Here, drink, and put some heart into you.
        <stage>(BRIERLY drinks)</stage> That's your sort—a lad of spirit—1 said there was real grit
       in him—didn't I, Mossey?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>You always gave him the best of characters.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Is it a bargain?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Yes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>There! Tip us the cracksman's crook—so! <stage>(shakes hands with a peculiar
       grip)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MAY EDWARDS, door in flat.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(c.)</stage> Robert—not here? <stage>(sees him)</stage> Ah—there he is!
        <stage>(going—pauses)</stage> Who are those with him?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Now a caulker to clench the bargain. <stage>(DALTON and BRIERLY drink)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(in pain)</stage> Ah—Robert!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>You here—lass?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, these petticoats!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>You're not wanted here, young woman.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>He is my husband, sir. He is not strong—the drink will do him harm.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Ha, ha, ha! Brandy do a man harm! It's mother's milk—take another sip. <stage>(fills
        BRIERLY'S glass again)</stage> To your girl's good health!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Robert, dear—come with me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Have you got work?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>No—not yet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No more have I, lass. The man took me on— it was the old story.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, Robert—come!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I shall stay with my friends here—thou go home, and don't sit up for me.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="78"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(imploringly)</stage> Robert!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I've my reasons.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Come, are you going?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(MAY clings to him)</stage> Stand off, lass. You used to do what I bid you ——stand
       off I say. <stage>(he shakes himself free from her)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, Robert, Robert! <stage>(staggers back to table, L., and sits)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> I must—or they'll not trust me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>These men! to what have they tempted him in his despair. They shan't drive me away.
        <stage>(aside)</stage> I'll watch.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, door in flat, after a mute appeal to BRIERLY.</stage>
     <stage>(the tables have been before this cleared of all the navvies except HAWKSHAW, who lies
      with his head on the table as if dead drunk—MOSS rises and goes down, R.)</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(re-entering from bar L. U. E.—shaking HAWKSHAW by the shoulder)</stage> Now, my
       man—we're shutting up the bar.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Shut up. I'm shut up. Good night. <stage>(lets his head fall)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(coming down)</stage> It's no use, he won't go, and I'm wanted in the concert
       room.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit MALTBY, L. U. E., <stage>(calling)</stage> Bar closed!</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to DALTON, suspiciously pointing to HAWKSHAW)</stage> There's a party—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(rising)</stage> Eh? <stage>(shaking HAWKSHAW)</stage> Holloa, wake up!
        <stage>(HAWKSHAW grunts)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>He's in a deplorable state of intoxication.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, he's got his cargo, no danger in him— now for business. First and foremost, no more of
       this. <stage>(pockets the bottle—to BRIERLY)</stage> You've heard the job we have in
       hand?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, but you've not told me where it is, or why you want my help?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>It's old Gibson's office. The five thousand you know—you know where it's kept.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Well.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>And you'll take us to it?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Yes.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="79"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>That's the ticket, then we may as well start.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Now?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Now. My rule is, never put off till to-morrow the crib I can crack to-day. Besides, you
       might change your mind.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>One has heard of such things.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>But—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>You crane—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I'll get a cab. <stage>(going)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>And I'll get another—we'd best go single. <stage>(following him)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>No, it wouldn't be polite to leave Mr. Brierly —<stage>(aside)</stage> I don't half trust
       him—don't let him out of your sight.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit door in flat.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>If he'll only leave me for a moment. <stage>(aside)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(crosses in front to R., sitting)</stage> He's carried off the bottle, and the bar's
       shut up, or we might have a little refreshment.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Perhaps, if you went to the landlord</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>No, I'd rather stay with you—I like your company, uncommon.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MALTBY, L. U. E., with a wine basket and a candle.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>Here's Mr. Tottie standing champagne round to the Wisconsin Warblers, and the bar stock all
       out, and the waiters in bed! I must go down to the cellar myself—very humiliating!
        <stage>(goes to trap near bar)</stage> What with the light, and what with the liquor—I say,
       Mr. Moss, if you would lend me a hand?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> I might give <emph>him</emph> the information. <stage>(to
        MALTBY)</stage> Let me help you, sir. <stage>(goes to trap)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Then I'll go too. <stage>(MALTBY opens the trap)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>The stairs are steep—two's quite enough.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>But I'm so fond of your company.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p>If you'll hold the light. <stage>(BRIERLY takes it and MALTBY goes down)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(aside)</stage> A word 'll do it. <stage>(going down—MOSS takes candle from him and
        gets between him and MALTBY)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>Allow me. The light will do best in the middle. <stage>(MOSS descends)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="80"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_M8">
      <speaker>Maltby.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(from below)</stage> Now, then!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(rapidly closes the trap, and stands upon it)</stage> Now's the time. <stage>(seizes
        the pen that stands on the bar, and writes, reading as he writes quickly)</stage> "To Mr.
       Gibson, Peckham. The office will be entered to-night; I'm in it to save the property, and
       secure the robbers—R. Brierly." But who'll take it?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(who has got up and read the letter over his shoulder)</stage> I will.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>You?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>I, <stage>(pulls off his rough cap, wig, and whiskers, and speaks in his own voice)</stage>
       Hawkshaw, the detective! <stage>(gives him a pistol)</stage> Take this—I'll be on the look
       out.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>(HAWKSHAW lets his head fall again as DALTON re-appears beckoning at the door, and MOSS
      re-appears from the trap —closed in)</stage>
    </div>
    <div type="scene" n="2">
     <head>SCENE SECOND.—A Street in the City—Moonlight.</head>
     <stage>Enter MRS. WILLOUGHBY and SAM, L. she is searching her pocket.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>You're sure you had 'em at the public?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Certain sure, my dear, leastways, I let myself out with the big street door, so I couldn't
       have left that in the kitchen window, and I'd the little ones all in my pocket, which I
       noticed a hole in it only yesterday— and it's best holland at one and six, and only worn
       three years, and they ain't dropped into my skirt, nor they ain't a hanging to my
       crinoline.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, bother, granny, we can't have a regular Custom House search in the street; let's go
       back to the public, perhaps they've found them.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Mr. and MRS. GREEN JONES, L.—she with shawl and bonnet, he with his basket and the
      guitar.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>There's only one set left: perhaps Providence has sent a customer. Trotters, mum?
        <stage>(to MRS. WILLOUGHBY)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(L. C., stopping him)</stage> In my company! I'm surprised at you! conceal that
       basket. <stage>(advancing to MRS. WILLOUGHBY)</stage> Why, if it isn't Mrs. Willoughby and
       Sam! Why, don't you know us the St. Evremonds?</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="81"/>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Lor bless me and so it is! and that dear, blessed man that suffered
       so in his shins—which perseverance is its own reward; and may I ask what Mr. Jones</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. St. Evremond.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. St. Evremond—what's he a doin'?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>He's in business.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, as a <stage>(producing basket)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(getting between Mrs. WILLOUGHBY and the basket)</stage> As a sort of a sheep
       farmer. But whatever are you doing here at this time of night?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F12">
      <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, my dear, it's a long story and if you wears pockets, mend 'em, is my advice—which,
       whether they dropped, or whether they was picked—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(impatiently)</stage> We can't get in—Granny's lost her keys.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>And you haven't a latch? Well, I wouldn't have thought it of you. Where did she lose
       them?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p>At the Bridgewater Arms—and the house is shut up now.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F11">
      <speaker>Emily.</speaker>
      <p>I'm engaged there; I don't mind knocking Maltby up—I rather like it. Come along, Jones,
       it's only a step; <stage>(aside to him)</stage> conceal that basket!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exeunt EMILY, SAM, and MRS. WILLOUGHBY, L. 12.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M5">
      <speaker>Green.</speaker>
      <p>Emily thinks trotters low; she don't see that even the trotter trade may be elevated by
       politeness and attention to seasoning.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, L. 1 E.</stage>
     <stage>Enter DALTON, MOSS, and BRIERLY, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Come along, Bob. All serene. <stage>(aside)</stage> Where could he have got that
       six-shooter from? However, I nailed the caps in the cab. Moss, you be crow—two whistles if
       the coast ain't clear—we'll work the crib. Lucky I nailed the old woman's keys. They'll save
       tools and time. Give me the glim. <stage>(MOSS takes out small lanthorn and gives it to
        him)</stage> Now, my lad, <stage>(to BRIERLY)</stage> take care; I'm a man of few words. The
       pal who sticks by me, I stick by him, till death. But the man who tries to double on me, had
       better have the hangman looking after him, than Jem Dalton.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exeunt DALTON, BRIERLY and MOSS, L.</stage>
     <pb n="82"/>
     <stage>Enter HAWKSHAW, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>This should be Crampton's beat. <stage>(gives a peculiar whistle, and enter a DETECTIVE, R.
        1 E.)</stage> Take the fastest Hansom you can find; tear down with this to Peckham.
        <stage>(gives note)</stage> Bring the old gent back to St. Nicholas Lane. Say he'll be
       wanted to make a charge. There's a crib to be jumped. I'm down on 'em. By the bye, lend me
       your barker. <stage>(DETECTIVE gives him a pistol, and exit, R. 1 E.)</stage> Jem Dalton's a
       tough customer. I always feel rather ashamed to burn powder. Any fool can blow a man's brains
       out. <stage>(tries caps and charges)</stage> So that lad's true blue after all. I had no idea
       that he tumbled to their game. He managed that letter uncommonly neat. Now for St. Nicholas
       Churchyard. When Jem Dalton planted his tools he never thought they'd come up darbies.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit L.</stage>
     <stage>Enter MAY, breathless, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <p>I've followed the cab as far as I could. I saw them get out, and lost them at the last
       turning. If I could only keep them in sight—if he could but hear my voice— Robert!
       Robert!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, L</stage>
    </div>
    <div type="scene" n="3">
     <head>SCENE THIRD—The Churchyard of St. Nicholas with tombstones and neglected trees; wall at
      back, L. C.; up, side of stage.</head>
     <stage>L. an iron railing supposed to separate the churchyard from the street; in flat, R. C.,
      the wall of Mr. Gibson's office, with practicable back door)</stage>
     <stage>DALTON and BRIERLY drop over the wall, L. C, followed by MOSS.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Now to transplant the tools! <stage>(gets tools from behind tombstone)</stage> All right.
       Moss, look alive! Here's the door and the keys.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit into office by back door, R. C., followed by BRIERLY.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(on the look out)</stage> Nice quiet place—I like working in the city; I wish
       everybody lived out of town, and left their premises in charge of their housekeepers.
        <stage>(MAY is heard, L., singing the refrain of her song)</stage> What's that? That girl!
       She must have followed us. Here she is.</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="83"/>
     <stage>Enter MAY in the street, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(sees MOSS)</stage> Oh, sir, you were with him! where is he?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>I'm just taking a little walk in my garden before retiring for the night; they've gone on
       to the Cave of Harmony—first turn on the left; there's a red lamp over the door, you can't
       miss it.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Exit, L. 2 E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, thank you—thank you!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M4">
      <speaker>Moss.</speaker>
      <p>That's neat! Trust old Moss when anybody's to be made safe.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>(HAWKSHAW during the above has dropped over wall at the back, seizes MOSS from behind,
      stops his mouth with one hand, and handcuffs him, R.)</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <p>Stir or speak, and you're a dead man!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(appearing at back door)</stage> Hang the cloud! I can't see. Moss!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(imitating)</stage> All serene!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(coming down)</stage> We've done the job. <stage>(calling to BRIERLY)</stage> Now,
       the box.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(within)</stage> I'll bring it. <stage>(comes from door with cash box)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>We'll share at the Pigeons in Duck Lane. The box! quick!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>A word or two first.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>We can talk in the cab.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No, here. You were my ruin four years ago.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I've paid you back to-night twice over. Come —the box!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>I suffered then for your crime. Ever since you've come between me and honest life—you've
       broke me down—you've brought me to this.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>I suppose you mean you've a right to an extra share of the swag?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No, I mean that you're my prisoner, or you're a dead man! <stage>(seizes him and presents
        pistol)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Hands off, you fool!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>Nay then <stage>(snaps pistol)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>You should have asked me for the caps. Here they are. <stage>(holds them up)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p>No matter; armed or unarmed, you don't escape me.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage><stage>(a struggle—</stage>DALTON strikes down BRIERLY, as
      <pb n="84"/> HAWKSHAW rushes from his concealment, R.)</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Now, Jem Dalton! It's my turn!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M2">
      <speaker>Dalton.</speaker>
      <p>Hawkshaw! <stage>(they struggle; HAWKSHAW is forced down on a tombstone and nearly
        strangled; SAM appears outside the rails, L., springs over them, seizes DALTON by the legs
        and throws him over; HAWKSHAW rises and puts the handcuffs on DALTON; MAY appears in the
        street, L.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Robert! Husband!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M7">
      <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(over DALTON)</stage> Lie still, will you? You're a nice young man! <stage>(crossing
        to R., looking over MOSS)</stage> You're a pair of nice young men!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Now Jem Dalton! remember poor Joe Skirrett—I promised him I'd do it. I've done it at
       last.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MR. GIBSON from back door of house, followed by MAY, who has gone round.</stage>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Gibson.</speaker>
      <p>This way! Here they are! The safe open! The cash-box gone?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>No, saved. <stage>(gives it to him)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Gibson.</speaker>
      <p>By whom?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>The man who is bleeding yonder, Robert Brierly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>My husband, wounded! Oh mercy! <stage>(she kneels over him)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M6">
      <speaker>Gibson.</speaker>
      <p>Thank heaven, he's not dead. I can repay him yet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M3">
      <speaker>Hawk.</speaker>
      <p>Men don't die so easily. He's worth a dozen dead men.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_F10">
      <speaker>May.</speaker>
      <p>Look, he opens his eyes. Robert, speak to me, It's May your own wife.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L0871_M1">
      <speaker>Brier.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(faintly)</stage> Darling, I'm glad you're here. It's only a clip of the head. I'm
       none the worse. It was all my game, to snare these villains. Who's there? Mr. Gibson? You
       wouldn't trust me, sir; but I was not ungrateful. You see, there may be some good left in a
       "TICKET-OF LEAVE-MAN," after all! <stage>(tableau)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>HAWK. MAY. BRIER. GIBSON. MOSS. DALTON. OFFICERS. SAM.</stage>
     <stage>R.</stage>
     <stage>L.</stage>
     <trailer>Curtain.</trailer>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
