<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L1070">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>THE TWO GALLEY SLAVES: A Melo-Drama, IN TWO ACTS.</title>
    <author>Payne, John Howard</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor>
    <idno type="LAE">L1070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="origin" n="72.5"><author>Payne, John Howard</author><title type="main"
      n="thetwogalleyslaves">The Two Galley Slaves</title><title type="sub">A Melo-Drama in two
      acts</title><title type="source" n="#FR">Adapted from the French</title><extent>26 pp (UM
      copy: 196 - 222)<measure type="pp" quantity="27"/>
      <measure type="spCount" quantity="295"/>
      <measure type="spvCount" quantity="0"/>
      <measure type="txWords" quantity="7820"/>
      <measure type="spWords" quantity="6722"/>
      <measure type="stWords" quantity="1098"/>
     </extent>
     <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 72, No. 1070</title><idno type="nic"
      >N02782</idno></bibl>
    <bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref
      target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453467&amp;seq=196 ">UM from
      HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol72/L1070/L1070-um.pdf"/></bibl>
    <listEvent>
     <event type="firstPerf" when="1822-11-16" source="text" where="Covent">
      <desc>Premiered at Theatre Royal, Covent Garden 16 Nov. 1822; Nicoll date 1822-11-06</desc>
     </event>
    </listEvent>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>Melo-Drama</term>
     <term>Two-Acts</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
   <particDesc>
    <listPerson>
     <person xml:id="L1070_M1">
      <persName type="role">Henry</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="58">Henry.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1070_M2">
      <persName type="role">Major De Lisle</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="24">De L.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1070_M3">
      <persName type="role">Bonhomme</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Bon.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="50">Bonh.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1070_M4">
      <persName type="role">La Route</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="31">La Route.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1070_M5">
      <persName type="role">Basil</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="46">Basil.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1070_M6">
      <persName type="role">Felix</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="7">Felix.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1070_M7">
      <persName type="role">Claude</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Claude.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1070_M8">
      <persName type="role">The Unknown</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="29">Unk.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1070_F9">
      <persName type="role">Louise</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="2">Louisa.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="34">Louise.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1070_mult">
      <persName type="role">[Multiple speakers]</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">All.</persName>
     </person>

     <person xml:id="L1070_M10">
      <persName type="role">[Villager]</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="7">1st Villager.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="2">2nd Villager.</persName>
     </person>
    </listPerson>
   </particDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2025-12-17">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change>
   <change when="2025-12-08">Auto-tagged by Gemini 3.0 (Flash 2.5)</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <titlePage>

    <titlePart type="main">THE TWO GALLEY SLAVES: A Melo-Drama, IN TWO ACTS.</titlePart>
    <titlePart>ADAPTED FROM THE FRENCH</titlePart>

    <byline>BY <docAuthor>JOHN HOWARD PAYNE.</docAuthor> AUTHOR OF <title>BRUTUS, </title><title>ALI
      PACHA, </title><title>LOVE IN HUMBLE LIFE, </title><title>CHARLES THE SECOND</title>, ETC.,
     ETC.</byline>
    <byline>WITH AN ILLUSTRATION, AND REMARKS BY D-G.</byline>
    <docImprint>THOMAS HAILES LACY, THEATRICAL PUBLISHER, LONDON.</docImprint>
   </titlePage>
   <pb n="2"/>
   <performance>
    <p>First Performed at the Theatre Royal, Covent Garden, (under the management of Mr. C. Kemble),
     on November 16, 1822.</p>
    <castList>
     <head>CHARACTERS.</head>

     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Henry</role>
      <actor sex="M">Mr. T. P. Cooke.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Major De Lisle</role>
      <actor sex="M">Mr. Egerton.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Bonhomme</role>
      <actor sex="M">Mr. Fawcett.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">La Route</role>
      <actor sex="M">Mr. Meadows.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Basil</role>
      <actor sex="M">Mr. Keeley.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Felix</role>
      <actor sex="M">Master H. Boden.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Claude</role>
      <actor sex="M">Mr. Atkins.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">The Unknown</role>
      <actor sex="M">Mr. Farley.</actor>
     </castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="F">Louise</role>
      <actor sex="F">Mrs. Chatterley.</actor>
     </castItem>
    </castList>
   </performance>
   <div type="costume">
    <head>COSTUMES.</head>
    <p>HENRY.—Light blue frock coat, crimson striped waistcoat, and light blue stocking pantaloons,
     striped stockings, and black shoes.</p>
    <p>MAJOR DE LISLE.—Blue regimental coat, white facings, gold lace, white breeches, long black
     boots.</p>
    <p>BONHOMME.—Green coat, gilt buttons, broad green striped waistcoat, buff cassimere breeches,
     short gaiters, white beaver hat.</p>
    <p>LA ROUTE.— Crimson coat, tambour silk waistcoat, buff cassimere breeches, powdered hair.</p>
    <p>BASIL.—White jacket, flowered waistcoat, blue breeches, striped stockings.</p>
    <p>FELIX. Grey boy's suit.</p>
    <p>CLAUDE.—Short brown coat, flowered waistcoat, buff breeches.</p>
    <p>THE UNKNOWN.—Brown trousers, spotted Guernsey shirt, leather belt, brown large cloak.</p>
    <p>LOUISE. Plain white, high muslin cap, and silk handkerchief.</p>
   </div>
   <set>
    <p>Time in Performance—1 hour 15 minutes.</p>
   </set>
   <pb n="3"/>
   <div type="liminal">
    <head>REMARKS.</head>
    <head>The Two Galley-Slaves.</head>
    <p>WHEN Michael Kelly, the composer, first set up wine merchant, his present majesty, the Prince
     of Wales, wittily remarked, that his old friend Mic was a <hi>composer</hi> of wine and an
      <hi>importer</hi> of musie. Now, Mr. Howard Payne, we suspect, is more <hi>au fait</hi> at
      <hi>drinking</hi> wine than<hi> making </hi>it; but he is a very considerable
      <hi>importer</hi> of foreign dramas, which he mixes up with sundry good things of his own, to
     suit the English market—as a certain patriotic dealer in gin and <hi>compounds</hi> ran a pipe
     of <hi>pontac</hi> into one of <hi>port</hi>, for the purpose, as he said, of
      <hi>improving</hi> the former, though the rogues of excisemen would have it that it was not to
     improve <hi>one pipe</hi> of pontac, but to make <hi>two pipes</hi> of port.</p>
    <p>The Two-Galley Slaves is derived from the French. The story is that of a <hi>ci-devant</hi>
     clerk in a Parisian bank taking upon himself the charge of felony, to screen the real offender,
     who is his own brother. He is therefore branded on the arm, and condemned to the galleys. In
     journeying to his place of destination, he contrives to scape; and, after some adventures, has
     the good fortune to captivate the heart of a rich buxom widow, who thinks the best proof she
     can give of her veneration for her dear departed is to appoint this young convict his
     successor. But, as a melodramatic hero is nobody without a due portion of mystification, Mr.
     Henry becomes on a sudden marvellously musing and melancholy. The
     <pb n="4"/> wedding-day at length arrives— the feast is prepared— the dances are drawn out—and
     joyful note of preparation is sounded, when, lo! an ugly customer appears, in the shape of
      "<hi>The Unknown</hi>" (a rascal, by all accounts better <hi>known</hi> than
     <hi>trusted</hi>), to spoil the sport. Who this unwelcome personage proves to be, we leave to
     the reader to find out; being determined not to mar the exquisite delight his curiosity will
     receive from the discovery. The monotony of the piece is enlivened by a conceited, inquisitive
     postmaster, who is an unsuccessful candidate for the young widow's affections—a Monsieur
     Bonhomme, whose name is sufficiently indicative of his good qualities; and Basil, a
     simple-hearted young villager, who is a rare adept at a joke and a junket. The characters were
     all well supported.—Mr. Fawcett acted with a generous roughness which no one can better portray
     than himself; Mr. Keeley was quaint and amusing; Mr. T. P. Cooke displayed his <hi>branded
      arm</hi> with picturesque effect; and Mr. Farley his <hi>brandied nose</hi>, that made us
     question if our ancient friend Bardolph, instead of being <hi>hanged</hi>, had not been
      <hi>transported </hi>for his portion of the <hi>Gadshill affair</hi>, or some such pranks, and
     exhibited his everlasting bon-fire light, in the person of "<hi>The Unknown</hi>!"</p>
    <p>D——G.</p>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <note>[Performance Free.]</note>
   <div type="act" n="1">
    <pb n="7"/>
    <head>THE TWO GALLEY SLAVES.</head>
    <div type="scene" n="1">
     <head>ACT I.</head>
     <stage>SCENE. On one side the Mill of St. Aldervon.— A landscape in the distance.— The rise of
      the curtain discovers gay groups of villagers, dancing on with bouquets, to compliment the
      betrothed, from R. U. E.—Music.</stage>
     <stage>Enter BASIL from the house, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Ah, lads and lasses, welcome! Let the joy of the day make your hearts as light as your
       heels. Skip and sing, my merry larks, and kick care to old Nick.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M10">
      <speaker>1st Villager.</speaker>
      <p>Huzza for Basil! Welcome, Master Basil!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Well, have you seen the bridegroom that is to be ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M10">
      <speaker>1st Villager.</speaker>
      <p>Not yet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Not yet? Out ever since daybreak, and not back yet? Stay—yes—now I know—he's gone to the
       farm, a few miles off, he always looked sharp after Madame Montel's concerns; now they're
       going to be one, of course her affairs are his; but it was just the same when he was only my
       fellow-servant in the mill, and before he dreamt of rising to be my master.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M10">
      <speaker>1st Villager.</speaker>
      <p>Tell us, now, what passed before the notary, when the marriage articles were drawn up. Did
       he say who his father was?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Not he.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M10">
      <speaker>1st Villager.</speaker>
      <p>What name did he give in, then?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Henry—no more. What have we to do with his father? Who knows if he ever had a father? But
       if he can't boast of his family, he may of his goodness.</p>
      <pb n="8"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M10">
      <speaker>1st Villager.</speaker>
      <p>Ay, and that's what won him my mistress's heart, which is worth more than a regiment of
       grandfathers, and which the highest born in the land couldn't have gained with a pedigree as
       long as a race-horse.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M10">
      <speaker>2nd Villager.</speaker>
      <p>Better be known, as Henry is, by a good character without a name, than the highest name
       without a character.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Name! If he brings no name to his wife, he'll leave one to his children; and he that can
       make both at once must be a clever workman. Think what he has done for the district! Now,
       last year, when the prize was offered, you know, for hunting wolves, he always got it. 'Twas
       of no use my trying to keep up with him. I felt brave enough till I heard the rascals howl,
       then, somehow, we always lost one another in the thick of the fray—he took to the wolves and
       I took to my heels; he won the feast, and I helped to eat it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M10">
      <speaker>1st Villager.</speaker>
      <p>How the robbers skip when he scours the woods! But for him, I should not have a home over
       my head, and my poor babes would be starving.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, and old daddy Bertrand, that tumbled into the water, would have been food for fishes.
       He was drowning, when Henry jumped in, and saved him:—ay, jumped souse into the water, for
       all he had his Sunday clothes on.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M10">
      <speaker>1st Villager.</speaker>
      <p>What a pity it is, that, when he makes everybody else so joyful, he should be so sad
       himself.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, he'll sparkle presently. Love made him dismal, but wedlock will bring him to. Madame
       Montel was so pleased with her former trial that way, that, after two years holiday, she now
       ventures again, and takes a second husband, in compliment to her first. Were it only for the
       love she bears her son, she ought. So fine a boy deserves a father, and here he comes. Look
       at him! there's a pattern to work by! <stage>(Music.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M6">
      <speaker>Felix.</speaker>
      <stage>Enter FELIX, gaily dressed, from house, L. 2 E.</stage>
      <p>See, Basil! am I fine enough for my new father's wedding?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Fine enough? Why, sure you can tell without asking ?—You've been at one wedding before.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M6">
      <speaker>Felix.</speaker>
      <p>Not I.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Oh then, you wasn't by when your first father was married?</p>
      <pb n="9"/>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter BONHOMME, R. 2 E., speaking as he enters.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Mind, George, fill all the baskets with fruit. Roll out two hogsheads of the best wine.
       Nothing can be too good for my sister's wedding. <stage>(apart, sighing)</stage> Would to
       Heaven I could think the bridegroom good enough!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Monsieur Bonhomme, we come with the most respectful salutations, to make humble
       manifestations of the sincerest congratulations. <stage>(all bow.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Thank ye, my friends, thank ye <stage>(to FELIX, who goes up to kiss him)</stage> Is not
       your fa — father—<stage>(the word chokes me)</stage> that is to be, come back yet? A
       bridegroom keep all waiting thus! Well, my sister knows her own taste. But a slight on such a
       day is more than I could bear.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>We'll go and meet him on his way from the farm, and surprise him with compliments:—and we
       can gather new garlands as we go, too, for the road-side is full of flowers. Come, lads and
       lasses.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M6">
      <speaker>Felix.</speaker>
      <p>And I'll go and finish the two letters, which I am to paint all in flowers, at the top of
       the verses the schoolmaster has been composing for me to present. You can't think how pretty
       I shall make those two letters! — Now for it! <stage>(FELIX goes into the house, L.
        Music-Exeunt BASIL, with the VILLAGERS, at the back, R. 2 E.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>LOUISE enters from house, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>

      <p>Brother why did you leave me so coldly ?— When everybody else approves my choice; why is it
       blamed only by my brother ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Your brother would see you happy, permanently happy; and he dreads, lest the man you have
       chosen— I hurt your feelings, my dear, but you know my heart.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, and I trust I know <hi>his</hi>, too, better, much better than prejudice will suffer
       you to know it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>I fear the fatal prejudice is not with me. A man of no condition, no means, and received
       here under such circumstances! — Little did I expect a result like this, when, seven years
       ago, alarmed by groans amid the howling storm, the flashes of the lightning gave him to my
       view, stretched, fainting with hunger and fatigue, before our mill. Ah, Louise! may the
       homeless outcast we sheltered from the tempest, ne'er prove a serpent to sting thee! But
       there's ever a lurking devil in mystery: —mere misfortune has nothing it can be ashamed of
       <pb n="10"/> telling; and, depend upon it, girl, when the conscience is clear, the tongue has
       no concealments.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Has he not told us, over and over again, that the disclosure of his secret would endanger
       the safety of his family? His half avowals leave us no room to doubt. You know Henry has been
       a soldier—may be— a deserter.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Desert the colours of his country!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Be sure 'tis something of that nature which weighs upon his soul, and wraps him in so deep
       a gloom.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>But his deep gloom has cast no cloud between him and his interest; — he has kept a sharp
       look out to that. A starving adventurer, who can worm himself into the good graces of a young
       and pretty woman, and into the proprietorship of a fine establishment, has no cause to
       complain, and no right to look melancholy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Nay, brother—you do him wrong. Had interest been his incentive, would he not have been
       eager to have urged our wedding? would he so often have put off the ceremony, which is to
       make my hand and wealth irrecoverably his?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Well, well, we're only wasting words, so we'll drop an ungracious subject. As the proverb
       says, — "What can't be cured, must be endured." I'm sure I'm disposed to like him, and I
       should like him, if he'd be frank, and tell us who and what he is;—or, rather, tell you, for
       Heaven knows, I'm only inquisitive on your account. But to you! to you, whom he owes
       happiness, life itself, to keep up this mystery is shameful. Presently, however, you'll be
       his. May you never have cause to repent! But, should regret and sorrow be your portion, be
       sure these arms can ne'er be shut against you. Fly hither from the blast, and in your
       brother's bosom seek shelter and a home. <stage>(Music.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter BASIL, running, R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>The bridegroom! the bridegroom! Now we shall have the ceremony. Like Cupid, I'm wedlock's
       forerunner, and I've fairly run myself out of breath, too, which Cupid has no right to do,
       before marriage, for that comes quite soon enough after.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(looking off, R. 2 E.)</stage>
      <p>I see no bridegroom. There's La Route, the owner of the post house, turning the corner, but
       no bridegroom.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Monsieur La Route! so it is! well they say Cupid's blind, and here's a proof.</p>
      <pb n="11"/>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter MONSIEUR LA ROUTE, R. 2. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>

      <p>Worthy widow, I kiss your hand. Friend Bonhomme, yours to command. <stage>(gives him his
        hand.)</stage> And where is the worthy and good Henry? I would fain congratulate him. Though
       a rival, I am a philosopher; for, gentle lady, you know it is entirely your own fault, that
       you are not, at this moment, Madame La Route, and, without wishing to disparage any body, I
       don't think I'm to be sneezed at.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>At any rate, every one knows who you are.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Who I am? I believe you. There'd be no getting on, in this country, but for me. The
       post-house has, for the last sixty years, (father and son understand) been my property; and
       it is hard that I, who have moved half the kingdom should have failed to move the sweet widow
       there.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>But, now, since the widow is happy in the choice of— <stage>(Music</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <stage>(who has been on the watch)</stage>
      <p>Henry! Henry at last —huzza! huzza! huzza!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter HENRY, rapidly, R. U. E.</stage>
     <stage>(Exit BASIL, R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p> Oh, my heart's comfort! Trust me, my beloved Louise, a circumstance, beyond my control
       withheld me from you thus. Each moment away from you has been an age of impatience to me,
       love!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>So <hi>you</hi> are late, too. <stage>(HENRY looks round gloomily.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Monsieur La Route, our neighbour.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(coldly inclining his head)</stage>
      <p>Good morning, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Proud as Lucifer! "Set a beggar on horseback"—umph "!— <stage>(aloud)</stage> Ay, as I was
       saying, you are over your time, and so am I; and if you hadn't come in, I should have told
       these good folks how it happened I was so late; for I'm seldom behindhand at a jollification.
       But, I dare say, you'll be as much interested as any body —so, you must know, just as I was
       coming out, up galloped a detachment of gendarmery, and made a halt at my house.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(starting—apart)</stage>
      <p>Gendarmery!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>The horses were dropping with fatigue and the men with hunger. So I had to wait till both
       were fed and rested, before I could hope to find out what brought
       <pb n="12"/> 'em; for, though I'm not prying, I like to know what's going on. So, at an
       hour's end—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Well?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>I was as wise as at its beginning. After a thorough search through my premises, off they
       set.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(anxiously.)</stage>
      <p>To return no more?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, no. They're sifting the neighbourhood, and will be back here, I dare say, to open your
       wedding-ball with you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(affecting perfect calmness)</stage>
      <p>With what intention ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>What intention? Oh, these gentlemen are not so fond of telling their intentions. Yet from
       the few words they let drop, I could smoke 'em. Penetration is a gift, and they that have it
       discover things, which sometimes, astonish the finder. <stage>(significantly—HENRY
        starts—goes up to him mysteriously.)</stage> Were I sure you could keep a secret.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Speak—speak!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>'Tis very important, observe! Don't get me into a scrape, now <stage>(casting a glance all
        round.)</stage> They seek deserters, and hunt after certain criminals, escaped on their way
       to the galleys.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(L., glancing at HENRY)</stage>
      <p>Deserters!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(R., looking also at him)</stage>
      <p>Criminals!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>It is suspected, nay, it is pretty certain, that, for a long time past, several of them
       have found refuge in this district. Such measures are taken, that nothing but a miracle can
       screen them from justice. They'll have the deserters, and the deserters will have their
       deserts.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(L. C.)</stage>
      <p>Unhappy men!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Unhappy! ha! ha! ha!—so it is — never content. Half the world are crying out. that they
        <hi>can't</hi> get their due, and the other half, because they <hi>do</hi> get it,</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Sir, the wretched, though guilty, claim pity, and not sneers. There is nothing so unsafe as
       severity. Who knows but among these proscripts, there may be some who have merited a better
       fate? The victims even of law may be the victims of error; and, till man can be infallible,
       he has no right to be unfeeling.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Had I any compassion to spare, I think I might bestow it better than on convicts.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(with emotion)</stage>
      <p>Louise, a moment longer and we shall be one. Heaven knows such bliss o'ertops my proudest
       hope, fulfils my dearest wishes. Still, whate'er the cost, I am ready to sacrifice my
       happiness to yours. The wretched sport of destiny, nameless, pennyless, with no earthly prop
       but you, you only, to whom I owe everything, what can I
       <pb n="13"/> offer in return? Nothing, but a heart which adores you; and even that heart
       marked by sorrow for its own. Pause, Louise; there is yet time. If you repent, speak! Let me
       mourn your loss, rather than your reproaches. Let me despair, rather than see you
       wretched.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(with kind-heartedness)</stage>
      <p>I have weighed all. My resolution is as unalterable as my love.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>That is not the language of dishonesty. <stage>(aloud.)</stage> Henry, you have spoken as a
       man should do. This candour shakes the prejudice I had against you; and all I wish is, that
       you would carry your unreserve still further. But the die is cast, and if you make my sister
       happy, you shall never look in vain for a friend, while she, who has chosen you, has a
       brother.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. HENRY grasps the hand of BONHOMME—LA ROUTE tries to hide his spite at this
      picture of happiness.</stage>
     <stage>Enter BASIL, R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>

      <p>Here come all the villagers, men, women, and children, to conduct them to church.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter FELIX from house.</stage>
     <stage>(VILLAGERS dance on from R. U. E. with garlands and bouquets —the UNKNOWN then appears
      on the bridge: he walks with difficulty—fear is stamped on all his features —perceiving the
      characters on the stage, he stops short, terror-struck.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(apart)</stage>
      <p>Great Heaven! should they observe! <stage>(he cowers behind the rising ground, at the back
        of the stage.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Believe me, I deserve your friendship, and shall deserve it. Though worn by affliction, I
       am pure from guilt.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Lead to the ceremony. </p>
     </sp>
     <stage>(Music. The VILLAGERS form on opposite sides, two by two -BONHOMME gives his arm to
      LOUISE-HENRY takes the hand of FELIX-BASIL and LA ROUTE follow the procession files off over
      the bridge.</stage>
     <stage>The UNKNOWN enters L. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>

      <p>They are gone—not a soul left. Now for a moment's halt. Ah! I can no longer drag on without
       rest. <stage>(glancing round)</stage> Where am I? Still in this cursed Auvergne! Three days,
       and I shall have no more to fear <stage>(comes down to tree, R.—Music. —starts.)</stage>
       Hark! footsteps! <stage>(listens —a moment's silence)</stage> No, no, nothing, nothing. Those
       infernal
       <pb n="14"/> gens-d'armes! I see them in every bush: I hear them in every breeze. 'Twas tough
       work to give them the slip. The shots whizzed round me; but chance stood my friend. What a
       devilish hard life, skulking about these mountains, without a moment's peace! Be it so: I
       have my liberty, and with that, if I must suffer, I can make others suffer too <stage>(he
        eyes the house.)</stage> A pleasant dwelling! They are happy to whom it belongs; and I, a
       wanderer and a fugitive, forced to hide from every eye, and wresting my bread from the terror
       or the pity of strangers — and this is justice! But 'tis time for me to set forward. On then.
       Infernal chance! My limbs refuse to bear me, and hunger, terrible hunger, gnaws me to
       desperation. I'll try again! It cannot be! Must I die here for want <stage>(Music.)</stage>
       They're at hand—they are upon me! Oh! let me perish, sooner than surrender. <stage>(He makes
        a last effort to escape—his limbs fail—he drops down, and, when fallen, attempts to drag
        himself on his hands, but faints.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter BASIL, FELIX, and 1st and 2nd VILLAGERS, from the bridge, R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>

      <p>At it, my lads! Make all ready, so that, when they come, there'll be nothing to do, but to
       eat and caper. <stage>(Music. As he advances towards the house he discovers the UNKNOWN
        stretched upon the earth.)</stage> Halloo! what have we here? By St. Dominic, a dead
       man!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M6">
      <speaker>Felix.</speaker>
      <p>No, he's not dead. Help! help! <stage>(Exit into house, and returns with
       bottle.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>The very spot, and the very condition, in which, seven years ago, we found poor Henry. Lift
       him up—<stage>(the TWO VILLAGERS raise him.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(stares round wildly, and struggles)</stage>Stand off! I will not yield!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>What the devil are you afraid of ? Nobody here wants to hurt you. <stage>(giving him some
        wine, FELIX has brought out of the house)</stage> Hold! drink, and you'll mend—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(drinks)</stage>
      <p>Thanks, thanks!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>That's a cure for all evils.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(apart)</stage>
      <p>I had well nigh betrayed myself. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Thanks! Forced marches—the hot
       sun—my strength wasted—I'm better now, much better, and I haste—<stage>(strives to
        walk.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M6">
      <speaker>Felix.</speaker>
      <stage>(stopping him)</stage>
      <p>"The more haste, the worst speed," as my schoolmaster says. Take my advice, and stay here
       the rest of the day. There's a wedding too, and that will please you. You shall tell me your
       story, and that
       <pb n="15"/> will please me: the sadder it is, the more I shall be diverted, for I like sad
       stories, and, if very dismal, it will be delightful.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>The boy's right; don't think of stirring. <stage>(they place him on seat under tree,
        R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>I accept your kindness. <stage>(apart)</stage> To deny them would raise suspicion. Besides,
       in the bustle, 'twill be easy<stage>(music.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter HENRY, LOUISE, LA ROUTE, BONHOMME, and VILLAGERS, from Bridge, R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M6">
      <speaker>Felix.</speaker>
      <p>Mamma, you won't scold me, I'm sure you won't. See, I've been helping this poor man. We
       found him dying on the bare ground. You always told me, 'twas our first duty to relieve the
       afflicted.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>And 'twill always be our pride, my boy, to see you remember such lessons. <stage>(to the
        UNKNOWN)</stage> Whoever you may be, you are welcome here. Beneath this roof the persecuted
       and the suffering shall ne'er in vain seek a refuge.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(apart)</stage>
      <p>That voice! I've heard it before, somewhere.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>That face! Should it be——</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(apart)</stage>
      <p>Can I be mistaken! No—there's not a doubt. 'Tis he!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(apart)</stage>
      <p>Withering recollection!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(rising)</stage>
      <p>Comrade, this is not our first meeting.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(confounded)</stage>
      <p>Do you think so?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>I know so.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>'Tis done! I'm discovered!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(significantly)</stage>
      <p>What, shun an old friend! Oh, that'll never do!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>An old friend!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>What! my name and face forgotten—both? I've a better memory. Your name is—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(terrified and grasping his arm)</stage>
      <p>Hold! hold! hold!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(advancing L. C.)</stage>
      <p>Come, come, Henry. Our worthy neighbours wait. By St. Denis, at your age, I should have
       been the first to lead the dance.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>I—I—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>I—I—what ails you Come, come; lead forth your bride. You, sir, <stage>(to the
        UNKNOWN)</stage> are more disposed for rest and food than to join in our sports, I take
       it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>Both rest and food, indeed, would be welcome, sir.</p>
      <pb n="16"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>You shall have them. Here, Basil, show this stranger an apartment, and provide food and
       wine.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>Thanks! thanks! <stage>(BONHOMME goes up.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>I wish the stranger had continued so. Now I shall lose the dancing; but I won't, though.
       This way— this way— <stage>(Showing UNKNOWN the way.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(coming forward)</stage>
      <p>Be cautious, I implore. <stage>(goes up.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>I warrant; he saves me, or he sinks with me. <stage>Exit, L.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Now, then; lads and lasses, married and single— the dance—the dance!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>DANCE—TABLEAU, AND END OF ACT I.</stage>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div type="act" n="2">
    <head>ACT II.</head>
    <div type="scene" n="1">
     <stage>SCENE —A Hall, open at the back. —Lights a little down, R. and L.-Secret door, L.—A lamp
      is burning on a little table.—Music.</stage>
     <stage>The UNKNOWN discovered sleeping in a chair, L., HENRY sitting, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>

      <p>He sleeps profoundly! He sleeps—with a life deformed by crime, and threatened momently with
       the scaffold! He sleeps! while I, with an untroubled conscience, court repose in vain!
       Agonizing fate! After unprecedented woes, happiness began to brighten round me, when this
       monster comes to strike my soul with terror, and disturb the peace of a seclusion, till now
       unknown to sorrow. One word, and Louise is lost to me for ever! I am given up to dishonour,
       and can find no refuge but in death. Oh, pitying Heaven! turn aside the storm ready to burst
       on my devoted head. I did not care to live, till love gave live a value; but, now, blest in
       the affection of an angel, I cannot bear to die. <stage>(village clock strikes six)</stage>
       Six! 'tis time he should depart, may his own safety, and the allurement of gold, guarantee
       his silence. <stage>(x's, and awakes him)</stage> Rise! You must hence.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>Hence?</p>
      <pb n="17"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Would you break your promise? Now the darkness favours you; and ere another hour,
       gens-d'armes may be here.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>Let 'em. I don't know how it is; but somehow, since I have had the luck to meet you, I
       begin not to care so much for the gens-d'armes. You can't let me be taken, you know; for,
       once caught, I might— 'Twas high time to stop my mouth, lad. I was just going to let all out:
       no wife for you, then; and, what's worse, no fortune, neither. She's a rich dowry, eh? You're
       a lucky dog. Who the devil would have guessed seven years ago No matter. I wouldn't change
       places with you, for all that. I have nothing to lose, and you are in my power.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Can man be humbled lower?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>It's a pity. But, pluck up. I'll not blab; but you know the terms.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>I shall keep my word. There's not a moment to be lost. Take this purse:—it will provide for
       your present wants. If I may be sure of your silence, yearly, on the same day, you will
       receive the same sum.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>Ay, you may be certain of me. I've no love for law, but a great respect for money.
        <stage>(aside)</stage> 'Twill cost him dear. I don't see any means, but the fortunes of his
       new wife, by which—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Hence! Nothing is in the way of your departure now. Hence! and in some deep, impenetrable
       seclusion abjure your errors, expiate your crimes, and open your heart to penitence.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>Oh yes: I repent as it is <stage>(aside)</stage> that I hav'nt made better use of my time.
       Patience! Could I return back unseen?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(having assured himself that there is no one coming, leads the UNKNOWN towards the
       little door, L.)</stage>
      <p>It is of the deepest importance that your going should not be observed.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>I know that.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>That door leads to a passage, opening on the court-yard. Once there, you have only a low
       garden-wall to scale, a hedge to pass over, and you are beyond our premises.<stage>(Lights up
        gradually.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>I was just thinking how I should contrive to get back, and he has shown me the way.
        <stage>(aloud, taking HENRY's hand, who cannot restrain a movement of repugnance.)</stage>
       Farewell, comrade. Come, come, don't bear malice: —you shall know my lurking-place in a few
       days. Mind you're punctual. <stage>(Exit by secret door, L.</stage></p>
      <pb n="18"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(after a deep sigh.)</stage>
      <p>He's gone, and I am safe, at least for a time</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>Enter Bonhomme, с.</stage>
      <p>Henry! what the deuce are you about here? They're all asking after you. <stage>(HENRY
        going.)</stage> But now, hold, sir. Since you and I are by ourselves, you must allow me to
       demand a little explanation of you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>An explanation! On what subject, pray ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Why, your mysterious manner, which nobody can explain. You must have seen plain enough,
       that I'm not pleased with you, though I've done my best to keep it down before Louise; for I
       wouldn't have made her unhappy by what I suspect.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>By what you suspect ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, sir, by what I suspect.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(agitated.)</stage>
      <p>What do you suspect?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>That you have no affection for her. Before you were married, I ascribed your sadness to
       your fears of losing her. You've got her, and now you absent yourself, and seem more sad than
       ever. Why, sir, do you steal away from her at this moment? The man who can use any woman ill,
       is cowardly and base; but he who can wound the heart of an affectionate girl who loves him,
       is un. deserving of the name. There, now it's out, and so you may make the best of it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Bonhomme, you have always been against me, notwithstanding my unwearied efforts to
       deserve your friendship. I call Heaven to witness, my whole soul is devoted to Louise! I
       thought yesterday you had renounced your prejudices; but your language to-day proves I was
       mistaken.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>No sir, you were not mistaken: but let me find that you deserve my friendship.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>There is no sacrifice—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>I want no sacrifice. I want open dealing. So tell me what is become of the man whom we
       assisted yesterday, he, whose sudden arrival astonished you so, and seemed to give you
       uneasiness? What's become of him ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>That man you'll see no more.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>So much the better! He has one of those countenances one don't care to meet twice.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter LOUISE and FELIX, C.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M6">
      <speaker>Felix.</speaker>
      <p><stage>(to HENRY)</stage> I've been preparing such a surprise
       <pb n="19"/> for you! There's a little specimen of my writing and painting. <stage>(gives the
        paper)</stage> The two large letters, with wreaths round them at top are all my own doing.
       See! —H. L. Can you guess what those two letters signify?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(apart, terror-struck)</stage>
      <p>Great Heaven! Maddening remembrance! Terrible coincidence! Detested letters! My eyes cannot
       look on them and not shudder.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(who has remarked his agitation)</stage>
      <p>Henry!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! nothing, nothing. This child's device—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Flutters your heart, as it does mine. The first union of our initials thus seems to give a
       reality to the dawning union of our lives, and could not but excite emotion <stage>(X
        L.)</stage> Henry and Louise! Thus love unites names never to be parted.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music-Enter BASIL and the DANCERS.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(apart)</stage>
      <p>Where'er I turn, the horrid brand of opprobrium and dishonour!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>What agitates him now! There's a something about that man that baffles every
        conjecture.<stage>(music)</stage>
      </p>
     </sp>
     <stage>(a carriage is heard to stop without, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <stage>(entering, c.)</stage>
      <p>There's a post-chaise at the door. <stage>(music.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(alarmed)</stage>
      <p>A carriage at this hour! What can bring—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <stage>(at the door)</stage>
      <p>And two people stepping out. <stage>(looking out)</stage> Ah! I see now. There's Monsieur
       La Route with an officer.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>An officer ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, an old officer.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter LA ROUTE and MAJOR DE LISLE, C., Basil goes off, c.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>

      <p>You see, I'm a man of my word. When I promised to come back, I little expected to come in
       such good company. Permit me to introduce a new guest to you. This gentleman comes into
       Auvergne for the purpose of buying that beautiful estate, of which you have the disposal. It
       was impossible for me to give the gentleman all the information he required, so I took the
       liberty to bring him to you. I was just going out, when he came in, so, as he offered me a
       seat in his chaise, I accepted the honour, and here we are.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>A wedding! Had Monsieur La Route made me aware of this sooner, I would not have intruded.
       This is no time to talk of business; and I am much afraid in my presence—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Sir, the presence of a soldier and a gentleman,
       <pb n="20"/> which your appearance bespeaks, can never be but welcome to us all.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>I thank you for your politeness; but I should be exceedingly sorry to be in the way of—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(x's to DE LISLE)</stage>
      <p>You are in no one's way, my dear sir; and if the rejoicings of our worthy villagers are not
       disagreeable to you, we should be happy if you would rest under our roof from the fatigues of
       your journey; and to-morrow we will endeavour to give you the information you require.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Allow me, sir, to join in the invitations of my husband and my brother.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Didn't I tell you they were the best souls in the world? You can't stand out much longer, I
       am sure.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>I accept your kindness; and, believe me, it gives me pride and pleasure to find myself in
       such worthy company. Led to Auvergne by motives of much deeper interest than the purchase of
       a domain, which is but a secondary object, perhaps you may be able to serve me more than you
       imagine. But let not my coming disturb any of your arrangements. <stage>(Music</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Shouts of "Stop thief!" from behind-BASIL rushes in C. D., out of breath.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Stop thief! stop thief! A man, whose face I couldn't get a glimpse of, has got into the
       bedroom, broken open the desk, and taken out all the money. Seeing me, he dodged out of the
       way; but I'll be bound he's not off yet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Just heaven! can it be?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Let him be pursued. <stage>(All but HENRY hurry off, C. D.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>If he be taken, I am lost. Should the robber be that wretch, he will seek to escape by the
       passage, which, in the terror of the moment, I myself pointed out to him. Unheard of
       perplexity! Forced to favour the flight of a miscreant, whom, with one word, I might— might
       what? am I not in his power? <stage>(music.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>The UNKNOWN darts in from L. 1 E.--he is pursued, and seeks to escape at the back-HENRY
       perceives him.</stage>
      <p>Ha! behold the criminal! 'Tis he! Stop! you go to your destruction. <stage>(pointing out to
        the little door)</stage> That way turn your steps. <stage>(The UNKNOWN stops short, and
        seems surprised at HENRY.</stage> Your infamy is known, and your life in my hands. But I
       <pb n="21"/> will not take undue advantages. Restore the fruits of your crime, and escape on
       the instant.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>Too civil by half! I should lose more than I can afford by that bargain.
        <stage>(going.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(stops him)</stage>
      <p>Would you seal my ruin?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>I only do like you—make the most of my situation.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(holding him back)</stage>
      <p>Restore, I charge you, the fruits of your crime, or I give you up instantly to the
       tribunals.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(shaking him off)</stage>
      <p>And I devote you to shame and infamy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>This is too much! I will no longer bear this thraldom. Rather death at once, than life in
       base subjection to a miscreant like thee.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>Death! Well, then, death be it—death—but on the scaffold.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>The scaffold! Monster! then your life shall pay for it. <stage>(music.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>HENRY seizes a sword—UNKNOWN draws a pistol.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>(L. C.)</stage>
      <p>Stand there. I defy your impotent rage.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(R. C.)</stage>
      <p>Come what may, I care not. Ere I perish, I'll have vengeance. <stage>He plunges on the
        UNKNOWN, "Follow, follow!" heard on all sides— the UNKNOWN fires, wounds HENRY, and escapes
        at the L. door—the CHARACTERS rush in, crying—</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p>Here! here! this way, this way!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>The scoundrel's given us the slip. </p>
     </sp>
     <stage>They group round HENRY, who staggers, and sinks into their arms—music—LOUISE rushes in
      c.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
      <p>Just Providence, protect my Henry! Great Heaven! he's wounded.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>'Tis but slight: the ball has but grazed his arm.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>There can be no danger.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>No, no—I warrant, none, sister. <stage>(stripping up his sleeve, and seeing the mark,
        exclaims)</stage> Oh, horror! The mystery is cleared. Henry is a—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>What?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Behold the indelible brand, the fatal mark!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>What mark?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>That of a galley slave!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>She utters a cry of horror, and falls fainting on the floorthe VILLAGERS all group about
      her-music-tableau-they are closed in. </stage>
     <note>(If played in 3 acts all that follows takes place in the above Scene; if in 2 acts, a
      front scene is necessary.)</note>
     <pb n="22"/>
    </div>
    <div type="scene" n="2">
     <head>SCENE, II. The lobby of Madame's house. (1st grooves.)</head>
     <stage>Enter BASIL followed by VILLAGERS, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M10">
      <speaker>2nd Villager.</speaker>

      <p>Oh, dear! oh, dear! who would have believed that such an honest man as Mr. Henry could have
       been such a rogue, as to be branded as a galley slave!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Silence! hold your tongue! Mightn't he have been born with it? You're a ninny, and don't
       know what you're talking about.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M7">
      <speaker>Claude.</speaker>
      <p>But, tell us, Basil, does any one know what's become of the rascal that gave him the
       wound?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>No—but never fear, he'll be caught, for there's more than sixty of our comrades at his
       heels. But here comes that inquisitive post-master, M. La Route.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter LA ROUTE, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>

      <p>Hey, how, staying here yet? Arn't you afraid the walls will fall about your ears?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Come, come, Monsieur la Route, your tongue goes faster than your horses, and wants what
       they never do.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>What's that?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>A curb. If honesty's the word, you'll find more here than you bring.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Ahem; queer, very queer, When I think I should have ventured to such a suspicious place, I
       wonder at my boldness; I really don't know what to think of myself.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>I'm sure nobody wants you to stay, and the sooner you go the better. This house, sir, is my
       master's, and I mind nobody here but Mr. Bonhomme, and Henry, my new master,</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Your new master. Ha, ha, ha! A pretty master he is. He'll teach capital letters with a
       vengeance; he'll not soon forget the lesson he learned.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Why, Monsieur La Route, what did you mean by capital letters P</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>What! didn't you see the brand upon his arm, H. L., hard labour? You'd much better take
       yourselves off, or you'll get into a scrape. Any moment the premises may be surrounded by the
       soldiers. Whoever they catch will be taken for witnesses, and accomplices too, for aught I
       know; so, take my word for it, you'd better make yourselves scarce. <stage>(The VILLAGERS
        make a sign of approbation, and go off at R. 1 E.</stage></p>
      <pb n="23"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>And can you, who pass for such a good sort of fellow, have the heart to stick by 'em, eh
       ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Why, will it hurt my character, think you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Ruin it, don't you see that?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Not I.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>You're a fool.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, then you think I shan't pass for what I<hi> am</hi>?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Zounds! you'll get a pretty name. Fancy the people saying —"Who does Basil live with?"—"Why
       that Henry"— "What, he, we heard?"—"Ay."—"You don't say to"—"Truth, on my word"—"Really—oh
       oh!"</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>No?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>You'd better cut. If you like to go—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Well?</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter BONHOMME, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>

      <p>I've a place to bestow.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Indeed!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>What wages do you get here? Thirty crowns a-year ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Exactly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Well, come and live with me, and you'll have the advantage of being in a virtuous family,
       which is a great deal, you know, and I'll give you twenty crowns a-year.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>What! ten crowns short! I give ten crowns for your virtue? That's more than my own's
       worth.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Can you really think of staying in the house of a malefactor ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(advancing c.)</stage>
      <p>Stop, sir. Whatever that man's faults, you are beneath his roof, and there is no crime more
       despicable than his, who basely seeks to cool the few friends who remain faithful to a man in
       the hour of his adversity.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, sir, and I'd have you to know, sir, I love my master, and I'll stay by him to the
       last, and you'll never get me to quit him, with all your flummery—<stage>(aside)</stage>—for
       ten crowns a-year short.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>Mr. Bonhomme, your servant insults me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>You shouldn't have put it in his power.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>You take a tone which doesn't become your situation.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>My situation! Sir, I can hold up my head anywhere. I never talk behind backs, and in
       whispers; nor
       <pb n="24"/> do I shrink, sir, from giving a proper answer to calumny, wherever I may meet
       it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>'Twould be well for you all, could you prove it calumny..</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>The smoothest tongues are as little to be trusted as the worst appearances, sir. I thought
       you were afraid this house would hurt your character. The door is open, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>And tell your virtuous family, they inweiggle no servants from here
       -(aside)-for~ten~crowns~short.$</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M4">
      <speaker>La Route.</speaker>
      <p>I'm going, sir! don't be alarmed—I'm going. And never, while I live, will I set foot in
       this place again! I'm going. <stage>(going—returns)</stage> I'm going! Compliments to your
       worthy brother-in-law. Safe journey to the sea-side for him. Sea air is a wonderful mender of
       his disease. <stage>Exit, L.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <stage>(calls after him)</stage>
      <p>Go to the devil, with your ten crowns short.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Go to <hi>your</hi> work, sir; and if you wish to leave our service, no tampering with our
       foes first, but do it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <stage>(aside)</stage>
      <p>Not for ten crowns short. <stage>Exit, R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(walking about agitated)</stage>
      <p>My sister judged truly of that meddling, prating postmaster. His glih tongue took me in; a
       rascally knave, to trample on a fallen man thus! I never took Henry's part before; but now
       I'll fight for him through thick and thin. <stage>Exit, L.</stage></p>
     </sp>
    </div>
    <div type="scene" n="3">
     <head>SCENE III.-The Hall (same as Scene 1., Act 2.)</head>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>Enter BONHOMME, L.</stage>
      <p>Where, where can my sister have hid herself? Why, why does she shun the presence of her
       brother? Ah! she comes!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>Enter LOUISE, R.</stage>
      <p>Spare me, brother! I know what you have a right to say. Had I listened to your advice—could
       I have believed. But I am punished cruelly, most cruelly. Don't add reproach to what I
       suffer.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Reproach, Louise! The severity of a true friend never follows calamity—so, no more of the
       past. What's to be done?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Alas! <stage>(she weeps.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>No, no; don't weep.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>I know my duty, and will do it, though 'twill cost me dear. You shall know all.
        <stage>(changing her tone, she
        <pb n="25"/> proceeds firmly)</stage> I am resolved to bestow on him, whom I no longer dare
       call my husband, all the attention which his situation renders necessary. If, as I hope, his
       life is not in danger, as soon as my presence and my watchfulness shall have ceased to be
       essential, we shall have ceased to live for one another, and until we meet in heaven, we
       never meet again.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Good, sister, good. That's more than I could have ventured to hope.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Perhaps it is more than I could have dared to resolve, had not the sight of my boy awakened
       me to what I owe him, and the world. Still, my brother, if, spite of my reason, spite of
       myself, too weak to sustain the sacrifice, I should fall, at last, a victim to shame and
       love, swear, swear solemnly never to forsake that child; and though his mother did not heed
       your warning, remember that his father was an honest man, <stage>(She sobs, BONHOMME attempts
        to reply, but has not the power, and can only rush into her arms they embrace.)</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>DE LISLE appears c.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>Madam, I am—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(apart, ill-temperedly)</stage>
      <p>What, what does he want?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>Your pardon, madam. Your husband—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(at the word "husband," staggers, sinks on a chair, and hides her face,)</stage>
      <p>My husband! 'Tis done! True, he is my husband!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Pray, sir, what would you have with us? You perceive my sister is not in a state of mind to
       receive strangers.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>I have several times attempted to see her husband, but ineffectually. All that I have been
       able to learn of him proves, that his conduct has been most exemplary ever since he has lived
       in this part of the country.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Be sure, sir, had it not, William Bonhomme and his sister would not have received him under
       their roof.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Oh! yes, sir, if ever he did forget the laws of honour, his conduct for the last seven
       years has been a reparation most ample and most public.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>Seven years an inhabitant with you!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, sir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>And found under very strange circumstances, I understand?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bon.</speaker>
      <p>Yes, sir. <stage>(LOUISE looks at her brother with disquiet, and makes a sign to him to be
        silent.)</stage></p>
      <pb n="26"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>They say, too, he never gave any intimation of his name or family. But I can hardly think
       that. Surely, with you he could have no reserves.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>He ought to have had none, sir, but he had.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(apart)</stage>
      <p>I see it now! 'tis Henry they mean to pursue.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>He was born in Paris, was he not? He has a brother. Did you never hear him speak of that
       brother ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(restraining himself)</stage>
      <p>Sir, I tell you again, I know nothing about him, nor should I have ever been inquisitive,
       but on my sister's account; for I have no great opinion of those that try to worm themselves
       into the confidence of others, while they are so very guarded with respect to themselves.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>I understand your allusion, Mr. Bonhomme; but it does not touch me; and, were you aware of
       the motives upon which I act, you might deem me worthy of a better opinion.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, sir, there's no great penetration wanting to see into your motives.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>You are your own master, sir; but there is a way to get at the truth; and, as I am
       determined to find it out, that way I must adopt.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(alarmed)</stage>
      <p>Sir!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(in a hurried tone, and rapidly to BONHOMME)</stage>
      <p>Brother, he will be lost, if not hurried from this place instantly. Save him from public
       shame. <stage>Exit BONHOMME, R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(glancing round)</stage>
      <p>Ah, sir! I supplicate you, if Henry's fate is in your hands.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>You mistake me, madam.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>No, no! You seek in vain to hide your purpose. I see, I feel, that you have long been in
       pursuit of this unhappy fugitive.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>That's perfectly true, madam; but—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Then, in the name of Heaven, <stage>(throwing herself on her knees in an agony of
        grief)</stage> grant that he may escape the ignominy that awaits him! In pity depart, that
       he may fly to some foreign land. Let not the agony of his wife implore in vain.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <stage>(raising her)</stage>
      <p>Madam, this posture ill becomes you. Believe me, had it been in my power to restore your
       husband to happiness, your tears had been dried up ere now.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>I hear steps. They are leading him this way. Perhaps this is the last time we can ever
       meet.</p>
      <pb n="27"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>I leave you, madam. Heaven grant that my return may bring you happier tidings! <stage>(Exit
        DE LISLE, C.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter HENRY, R., leaning on BASIL he is pale, and his arm slung in a black
      handkerchief-BONHOMME and FELIX follow.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>

      <p>Henry! It breaks my heart to see him.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(appears feeble)</stage>
      <p>Ah, madam! this last kindness is more than all the rest. To consent to see me, after—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M3">
      <speaker>Bonh.</speaker>
      <stage>(taking FELIX by the hand-in an undertone)</stage>
      <p>Forget not your duty to your child. Come, Felix, come with me. <stage>(goes out, followed
        by FELIX and BASIL, C.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Dearest Louise! Can I ever hope your pardon for what I have made you suffer?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>My pardon! Are not your sufferings as great as mine?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Greater than words can picture. Do you not hate the causer of your woes?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
      <p>Hate you? Our moments are numbered. We are beset by spies. An hour hence, perhaps, you
       cannot escape their vigilance. If you still love me, fly, fly! It must be; for your ruin is
       sworn. Go, live far from your Louise, and trust her love, whose heart is yours for ever.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Unparalleled devotedness! Can I have concealments from a heart like this? Louise, I claim
       more than love—I claim your esteem and, ere I leave you, you shall own I merit it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(with intense emotion)</stage>
      <p>What! Oh, speak! Go on, but don't—oh, don't deceive me!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Not for worlds! Learn, then, I was never guilty. <stage>(LOUISE is completely absorbed in
        the narrative, and stands, statue-like, with outstretched arms, as if impatient to hurry on
        the story.)</stage> Eight years ago I was placed by my elder brother in the banking-house of
       a rich uncle in Paris, whom I never saw. My brother was himself one of the head-cashiers, and
       I his assistant. His income would have been ample, but for a guilty passion for gaming. He
       supplied his wants from the funds entrusted to his charge. Suspicions arose in the bank, but
       none knew on which of us they ought to rest. One night, my brother rushing in wild, pale, and
       in the last agony of desperation, avowed to me the cause and consequences of his crime. He
       drew a pistol—he was about to deprive his wife and little ones of their only stay. I fell at
       his feet, and implored him to live for their wretched sakes. In this situation the officers
       surprised us. My brother fainted. I declared myself the
       <pb n="28"/> culprit, and was taken. All his attempts to fix the guilt on himself were
       fruitless. He was admired for the wish to make a generous sacrifice—I was condemned,
       sentenced to the galleys, and branded with that mark of infamy— which will go down with me to
       the tomb! but 'twas to save a brother, his despairing wife, and helpless little ones!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <stage>(darts forward, and falls upon her knees)</stage>
      <p>Great Heaven, I thank thee! <stage>(springs up, leaps into her husband's arms, and holds
        him some time closely pressed to her bosom)</stage> My heart did not deceive me. But, by
       what miracle did you get free?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>An officer, moved by my early years, and deep calamity, lent himself to my escape. I
       effected it with the wretch who recognised me this morning, and who, less fortunate than I
       was, was captured, has only gained his purpose after many years of suffering, dreadful,
       though deserved.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>And why would you not reveal this sooner?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Oh, I could not make my innocence apparent, without bringing on my brother the punishment
       from which he had been redeemed by my sacrifice.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>O, my Henry, we may yet be happy! Now my heart may own thee. Conscience no longer struggles
       with my love.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter DE LISLE, suddenly, c.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>

      <p>Fly hence, unhappy man!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Whither, sir? He is innocent! whither would you force him?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>To safety. I tremble for him. The villagers are armed. They conduct the soldiers
       hither.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <stage>(with dignity)</stage>
      <p>I know not, sir, whence the interest you express for me can arise; but, whatever may be
       your object, I have her esteem, whose approbation is more dear than life, and now I defy
       calamity.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>Confide in me. One word may save you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_F9">
      <speaker>Louise.</speaker>
      <p>Ha!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>Avow your name. I answer for the result. <stage>(Music. A pistol shot.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <stage>Enter BASIL, in a hurry c. from L.</stage>
      <p>Huzza! huzza! They've got him! They've got him!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Who?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M5">
      <speaker>Basil.</speaker>
      <p>The devil!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>The wretch who deceived me.</p>
      <pb n="29"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <stage>Enter the UNKNOWN, C. from L.</stage>
      <p>Save me, or we both are lost!.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>Infamous villain! dare you—</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M8">
      <speaker>Unk.</speaker>
      <p>Save me, I say, or give me arms: I'll fight 'em to the last—<stage>(Music. Enter
        GENS-D'ARMES and armed VILLAGERS — they rush on the UNKNOWN, and force him to the ground —
        all the CHARACTERS come on.)</stage> What! deny me help? Nay, then, we fall together.
        <stage>(to those who hold him.)</stage> Arrest that man. The scaffold claims him:—'tis Paul
       De Lisle!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>Paul de Lisle! Great Providence! thy ways are just. The object of my long search is gained.
       The monster, who would crush thee, destroys himself, and gives thee back to the world, to
       happiness, to honour.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M1">
      <speaker>Henry.</speaker>
      <p>What do I hear ?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1070_M2">
      <speaker>De L.</speaker>
      <p>Your brother, dying, avowed his guilt your sentence is revoked, your innocence proclaimed.
       Be happy in your uncle's arms, and share his heart and fortune! <stage>Music. They
        embrace.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>TABLEAU AND CURTAIN.</stage>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
