<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<head>Encoding Manual for Digital Lacy</head>

<p>The Digital Lacy project makes available in TEI-XML format a corpus of over
100 plays transcribed from Lacy's Acting Edition of plays (1845-1878). This
document provides details and explanation of the XML encoding and editorial
practices followed. </p>

<p>The corpus as a whole is represented by a single <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element,
which embeds a sequence of <gi>TEI</gi> elements. Each play is represented by a
single <gi>TEI</gi> element with an <att>xml:id</att> value used to identify it
throughout the archive. This identifier consists of the letter L (for Lacy) and
four digits, corresponding with the number originally allocated to this play in
the published series. In the few cases where a second play exists using the same
number, its identifier is suffixed with the letter R (for replaced). This Lacy
identifier (such as "L0234") is also used to name the XML file containing the
play. </p>

<p>Each <gi>TEI</gi> element is organised in the same way, following standard
TEI practice, and using standard TEI elements. It has two constituents: a
<gi>teiHeader</gi> and a <gi>text</gi>. The <gi>teiHeader</gi> provides metadata
identifying and documenting the play: see further <ref target="#hdr">section
2</ref> below. The play itself is represented by a <gi>text</gi> element. </p>

<div xml:id="hdr">
<head>The teiHeader</head>
<p>The function of the TEI Header is to provide metadata describing the
resource. It has the usual TEI structure, a <gi>fileDescription</gi>....</p>
</div>

<div xml:id="txt">
<head>The text</head>
<p>The <gi>text</gi> element contains an accurate transcription of the textual
content of the play, as printed in the edition used as source. The
transcription excludes supporting matter such as covers or advertising pages,
but is otherwise complete, including page breaks, title pages, prefatory
remarks, appendixes, etc. The transcription aims to represent correctly all of
the printed text and to indicate its intended function (as a title, speech,
stage direction etc.); it does not however aim to represent directly its visual
appearance, although each section of transcription may be linked to a page image
by means of the <gi>pb</gi> element representing a page break in the document
used as copy text. The typographic exuberance often found in title pages and
programme notes is not encoded at all, and the particular form of visual
salience used to signal (for example) a speech prefix or a character name in a
stage direction is not recorded. </p>

<p>The <gi>text</gi> element may have three components:  a <gi>front</gi>, a
<gi>body</gi>,. and an optional <gi>back</gi></p>

<div>
<head>Front matter</head>

<p>The front matter of a play consists of its title page (optionally preceded by
a frontispiece), and whatever else precedes the heading of the first act or the
start of the play. These structural components are represented using one or more
of the following elements:<list>
<item>titlePage</item>
<item>performance and castList</item>
<item>div</item>
</list></p>

<div>
<head>Title Page</head>
<p>The <gi>titlePage</gi> element contains a transcription of the words of the
title page, disregarding its formatting. It typically contains one or more
<gi>titlePart</gi> elements containing a title, subtitle, etc., followed by a
<gi>byline</gi> element optionally containing the name of the author/s tagged
with <gi>docAuthor</gi> and a list of other works by the same author, each
tagged with <gi>title</gi>. At the end of the page, the words of the imprint are
tagged with <gi>docImprint</gi>.</p>
<p>Here is an example where no explicit author is given: <figure>
<head>A simple title page</head>
<graphic url="file://media/L0013-titlepage.png" width="40%"/>
</figure>
</p>
<p>In Lacy XML we make no attempt to capture typographic features of the
original: case is normalised, and font changes ignored. This example is encoded like this: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<titlePage>
<titlePart>Novelty Fair; or, Hints for 1851.</titlePart>
<titlePart>An Exceedingly Premature, And Thoroughly Apropos Revue.</titlePart>
<byline>By the Authors of <title>Valentine and Orson</title>, <title>Whittington
and his Cat</title>, <title>Cinderella</title>, &amp;c, &amp;c.,
&amp;c.</byline>
<docImprint>T. H. Lacy, 17, Wellington Street, Strand, London.</docImprint>
</titlePage><!-- L0013 -->
</egXML></p>
<p>Here is a more elaborate titlepage, containing an epigraph, multiple
subtitles, descriptions of the contents of the work, indications of its source,
etc. <figure>
<head>A more complex title page</head>
<graphic url="file://media/media/L0287-titlepage.png" width="40%"/>
</figure>
</p>
<p> The element <gi>epigraph</gi> may be used to encode the Shakespearian
quotation here, but most such additional components should be marked up using
the <gi>titlePart</gi> element, with an appropriate value for its
<att>type</att> attribute:  <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<titlePage>
<titlePart type="main">"The Birds" of Aristophanes</titlePart>
<titlePart type="sub">A dramatic experiment in one act</titlePart>
<titlePart type="desc">Being an humble attempt to adapt the said "Birds"to this
climate, by giving them new names, new feathers, new songs and new tales, </titlePart>
<byline>By <docAuthor>J. R. Planché, Esq.</docAuthor>Author of
<title>"Fortunio,</title><title>"The White Cat,"</title><title>"Beauty and the
Beast,"</title><title>"The Sleeping Beauty,"</title><title>"The Drama at
Home,"</title><title>"The Fair one with the Golden Locks,"</title>
<title>"The Bee and the Orange Tree,</title> &amp;c. &amp;c. </byline>
<epigraph><quote>"A jest's prosperity lies in the ear Of him that hears it,
never in the tongue Of him that makes it.</quote>Shakespere.</epigraph>
<titlePart type="desc">Correctly Printed from the Prompt Book,with Exits,
Entrances, &amp;c . </titlePart>
<titlePart type="performance">First performed at the Theatre Royal Haymarket,
Monday April 13th, 1846</titlePart>
<docImprint> London: Published by S. G Fairbrother, Bow Street, And W. Strange,
Paternoster Row, Sold Also By W. Barth, Brydges Street, C. Harris, Bow Street,
And All Booksellers. </docImprint>
<titlePart type="price">Price Sixpence. </titlePart>
</titlePage>
</egXML><!-- L0287 --></p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Performance and CastList</head>
</div>
<div>
<head>Other kinds of front matter</head>
</div>
</div>
<div>
<head>The body of a play text</head>
<p>The body of a play text is made up of the following components:<list>
<item>Acts and Scenes</item>
<item>Speeches</item>
<item>Stage directions</item>
<item>Musical numbers</item>
</list>
</p>

<div>
<head>Acts and scenes</head>
<p/>
</div>

<div>
<head>Speeches</head>
<p/>
</div>

<div>
<head>Stage directions</head>
<p>Stage directions may appear in various contexts and have different functions.
Most plays begin with a lengthy stage direction describing the scene, which is
distinct from stage directions describing action on the stage. A stage
direction may appear within the speech of a character, usually if it is short
and indicates something about the way the actor is delivering their lines (e.g.
'aside', 'laughing'), or relating to their movement only (e.g. 'crossing to
U.R.', 'Exit'). Stage directions may also appear between speeches, usually
describing the entrance or exit of multiple characters, or a large amount of
stage business. In Lacy texts, it is customary to indicate an actor's position
on stage by means of an abbreviation such as 'L.' (for stage left), or a
sequence of abbreviations referencing not just the side of the stage but also
the depth, sometimes expresed in terms of the "grooves" in which stage scenery
is set, '1' being the groove nearest the audience,; sometimes less exactly using
codes such as 'U' (for upstage, i.e. away from the audience). The code 'C'
stands for 'centre'; the code D for 'door'; 'L. 1. E.' (stage left, first
groove, entrance)</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</body>
