<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Digital Lacy and the Victorian sense of humour</title>
    <author>Lou Burnard</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition> <date>2024-11-01</date> </edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Shortened draft text as presented at <ref target="https://we-are-amused.sciencesconf.org/">Punch Pocket Books conference</ref></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>Written by OpenOffice originally and then tidied up by hand</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <listChange>
    <change when="2024-11-18">Added links to slides</change><change> <name>Lou</name> <date>2024-11-01T12:08:50.077655613</date> tweaked auto generated
     header </change>
   </listChange>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <head rend="main">Digital Lacy and the Victorian sense of humour</head>
   <head>Lou Burnard (Independent Researcher)</head>
   <div>
    <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(2)"
     >Introduction</ref></head>
    <p>The Digital Lacy project aims to make 100 volumes of <title>Lacy’s Acting Edition of
     Plays</title> (LAE) freely available in digital form, both image and transcription, along with
     detailed documentation. The LAE comprises 1500 titles, including for example the celebrated
     farce <title>Box and Cox</title>, the melodrama <title>Ambrose Gwynett</title>, the "problem
     play" <title>Society</title>, the sensational dramatization of <title>Lady Audley's
     Secret</title>, and of course the fantastical spectaculars by J.R. Planché alongside works by a
     host of other authors now forgotten. Its availability fills a serious gap: Victorian theatre
     has not enjoyed systematic documentation or digitization on the scale of the Victorian novel:
     there is nothing analogous to Troy Bassett’s ATCL, for example. This may reflect scholarly
     perceptions of the relative merits of stage and page, or maybe just perpetuates 19th century
     prejudice. For it is evident that the Victorian popular theatre and the Victorian popular novel
     were in many ways complementary. In Emily Allen's words, "Victorian theatre was the novel's
     ally, inspiration, and competitor"; likewise, there are clear connexions between 19th century
     and contemporary flavours of melodrama, comedy, documentary, or pantomime. Perhaps our
     reactions to Victorian theatre’s exuberant combination of sensational spectacle and social
     comment, absurdity and realism may say as much about ourselves as about its original audiences. </p>
    <p>Our experience of the Victorian stage is however determined in different ways from that of
     its original audiences: for us, it is the archive which determines what is available, and our
     own context which determines which aspects of that are considered salient. To quote Richard
     Schoch, “Our very idea of the theatrical past is determined by the more or less invisible
     structures of archives, in which Henry Irving is much more visible than Joseph Grimaldi.” The
     example may be debatable but the principle is incontrovertible. This paper first explores the
     stages or forms in which a typical play text has been transmitted to us. <!--
            By
            examining some features of its composition, we then attempt to determine how well one particular archive,
            the collected volumes of Lacys Acting Edition, may serve to approximate nineteenth
            century theatre as a whole.--> <hi>CLICK</hi> </p>
   </div>

   <div>
    <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(3)">Available forms
     for the drama</ref></head>
    <p>We distinguish seven formal varieties for components of the LAE, listed here, each of which
     we now consider in more detail. <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
    <!--  <list><item>manuscript</item><item>performance traces</item>
               <item>acting edition</item><item>collection of scripts</item><item>volume set</item><item>post facto edition</item><item>digitization</item></list>
            -->

    <div>
     <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(4)">The
      Manuscript</ref></head>
     <p>After the 1843 Theatres Regulation Act, no play could be performed unless vetted by the Lord
      Chamberlain’s Office. As an interesting consequence, an original manuscript had to be
      submitted, often within a few days of the play’s first performance. These manuscript versions
      typically lack detailed notes on costume or stage directions, but do often include indications
      of passages to be struck out in performance, along with other significant textual variation. </p>
     <p>Surprisingly many of them have survived, and are deposited in the British Library; some have
      even been digitized, as part of a Gale collection covering the period 1824-1858. This enormous
      resource – comprising several thousand titles – seems to have had strangely little impact on
      contemporary theatre studies, despite the promise of a project with the apt title “Buried
      Treasures” which in 2009 had catalogued and allegedly transcribed a significant number of
      manuscripts, perhaps because these materials do not seem to be currently accessible online.
      <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(5)">Traces of
      Performance</ref></head>
     <p>Once licensed, a play might be advertised and performed. The records of performance provided
      by such evidence as handbills and posters have been widely if unsystematically collected and
      studied; notably by Allardyce Nicoll for the 4th and 5th volumes of his monumental
      <title>History of English Drama 1660-1900</title>. Such records cannot capture the full
      richness of the dramatic experience, but they give an indication of where and how often a new
      piece was performed: as part of a provincial tour, or benefit, a London first night, a regular
      run etc. General purpose periodicals such as <title>Punch </title> and specialist journals
      such as <title>The Era</title> are also rich with contemporary gossip about and reviews of
      performances. <hi>CLICK</hi> </p>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(6)">Acting
      Editions</ref></head>
     <p>According to Crompton-Rhodes, “The first of the 'acting-editions' was The New English Drama,
      edited by William Oxberry, of the Theatre Royal, Drury Lane, which began printing play scripts
      in the early 1820s". The novelty was to include "the Stage-plot, or disposition of the
      characters" -- for "Such an addendum must prove of incomparable value to provincial
      performers…" The acting edition is as much a recipe for the production of a dramatic
      performance, as it is a record of one. A working document, it was cheaply printed and sold
      unbound in bulk at a modest price. A professional actress called Clara St Casse built up a
      personal library of 600 such items, which eventually found its way into the special
      collections of the University of Warwick Many other libraries have similar holdings,
      suggesting that this form of publication was widely dispersed. Indeed, by the 1830s, the
      acting edition seems to have entirely replaced the more respectable (and expensive) octavo or
      dudodecimo formats in which individual dramatic titles had found their way into print
      hitherto. <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(7)"
      >Collections</ref> </head>
     <p> Lacy was by no means the first person to hit on the idea of reprinting and publishing
      uniform editions or collections of such play scripts. Like his predecessors John Dick, John
      Cumberland, and John Duncombe, his business plan was to buy up (where necessary) or steal
      (where possible) the copyrights of individual texts and reprint them for a mass market, thus
      enabling him also to collect licence fees for successful performances. It has been plausibly
      argued that from the 1850s onwards, such reprints targetted the middle class amateur who might
      have felt uncomfortable in a real theatre, rather than the professional actor or producer.
      <hi>CLICK</hi> As a skilful entrepreneur Lacy understood what we now know as <ref
      target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(8)">>market
      segmentation</ref>; he also advertised at least two complementary series, Lacy’s “Dramas for
      Private Representation” and “the New British Theatre”, to say nothing of the short-lived “Lacy
      Home Plays” billed as “an inexhaustible source of harmless amusement”</p>

     <p>However, the LAE continued to be his main breadwinner, with “new” titles appearing regularly
      until 1873 when the business was sold to Samuel French, an American publisher with whom Lacy
      had long co-operated; French’s Acting Editions continued to be published well into the middle
      of the 20th century. <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(9)">Volume
      sets</ref></head>
     <p>The first advertisements for the LAE show a simple list of 75 titles, available at 6d a
      title, postage included. But soon thereafter, Lacy began to complement the sales of individual
      titles by sales of bound volumes, each containing 15 titles. By 1870, he had reached a total
      of 100 volumes, which advertising puffs proudly announced as “<ref
      target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(10)">the most perfect Edition
      of Plays ever published</ref>, and no Library can be considered complete without them” . </p>
     <p><hi>CLICK</hi></p>
     <p>Easier to preserve than individual paper copies, varyingly complete sets of these bound
      volumes are to be found in libraries across the world. No full bibliographic study of these
      different sets has been carried out to my knowledge, but their composition seems to have
      remained stable for most of the century. I have found only a dozen or so cases where a title
      appearing in one volume of a set was missing from the corresponding volume in another set, and
      only a few other disparities. <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(2)"
      >Editions</ref></head>
     <p>Few of the authors credited in the LAE achieved any degree of fame or recognition beyond
      their own life time, or even within it. Nevertheless, there are some whose works received the
      ultimate Victorian reward of a collected edition, often in many volumes, usually shortly after
      their decease; examples include J.R. Planche, Douglas Jerrold, and T.W. Robertson. There are
      also several authors who (once respectable) were tempted into publishing fat volumes of
      theatrical gossip and autobiographical reminiscence, such as F.C. Burnand whose memoirs
      include a memorable description of Lacy and his business procedures. </p>
     <p>A consideration of modern editions of 19th c theatre is beyond the scope of this paper.
      However, such evidence as I have suggests that the choice of authors on which modern reference
      works focus may not always correspond with the evidence attested by collections such as the
      LAE. Of the three LAE authors responsible for 50 or more titles, only one features in Gale’s
      <title>Dictionary of Literary Biography.</title> Of the 71 authors responsible for more than
      five titles in the LAE, together accounting for about two thirds of its contents, only 20 are
      listed in the DLB. Wikipedia does a little better, with 57. <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(12)"
      >Digitization</ref></head>
     <p> Mass digitization efforts, such as Google’s or Gale’s, have swept through the holdings of
      major research libraries, not entirely indiscriminately but sometimes selecting on largely
      contingent grounds. Nevertheless, their efforts, like those of the microfilmers who preceded
      them, have resulted almost accidentally in a new lease of life for the long-forgotten bound
      volumes and scattered prompt books attesting to earlier incarnations of the theatre, and are
      entirely to be celebrated. </p>
     <p> Only a few LAE titles (82) have never been digitized at all, though well over half the
      titles (957) seem to be available from one online source only. The Digital Lacy online
      catalogue includes links to over a thousand freely available digitized versions so far
      discovered; there are many more to come. </p>
     <p> A digitization in page image form is not however the same thing as a machine-tractable
      transcription, and does not offer the same affordances for analysis. Only a handful of LAE
      titles are currently available in some transcribed form online: Project Gutenberg offers a
      total of 23 titles complete with some vapid automatically-generated summaries; Proquest’s
      “Literature Online” collection includes 42 LAE titles in RTF format, derived from an old
      Chadwyck-Healey product. The Digital Lacy project has begun the task of making available
      preliminary TEI versions of texts originally produced for the Victorian Plays Project from the
      Birmingham Library collection mentioned earlier: around 60 are online so far.
      <hi>CLICK</hi></p>

    </div>
   </div>

   <div>
    <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(2)"
     >Representativeness</ref></head>
    <p>Every type of collection necessarily provokes questions of representativeness and selection
     bias. Although we cannot be certain of the rationale behind all of Lacy’s selection decisions,
     clearly the LAE was not composed in an opportunistic or haphazard manner. By contrast, the
     25,000 entries constituting Allardyce Nicoll’s monumental <title>Handlist</title>s approximate
     an exhaustive listing of theatrical activitybetween 1800 and 1900. By comparing statistical
     properties of the two we should be able to detect any systematic bias, and characterize more
     reliably the sample before us. [Both LAE and Nicoll datasets are freely available from the
     project’s Github repository at <ptr target="https://github.com/lb42/Lacy/"/>]</p>
    <p> We present here some tentative statistically-based conclusions, based on analyses of date,
     size,authorship, and genre. <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
    <div>

     <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(14)">Date</ref> </head>
     <p>Nearly every play in the Lacy dataset has a date of first performance, usually explicitly
      given in the front matter of the text. Many also have a date of licensing, usually a few days
      or weeks earlier. These dates supply a <foreign>terminus a quo</foreign> for the play’s
      composition: it cannot have been written after its first performance date, nor performed
      before its licensing date. This is not an entirely satisfactory procedure but short of much
      more extensive bibliographic research it is the best we can do. Within limits, each item in
      the two datasets is datable. </p>
     <p>As a first experiment, we calculated the number of titles with a first performance date in
      each decade between 1800 and 1900, for both datasets. Each bar here represents that count as a
      percentage of all titles: blue for Nicoll, red for Lacy. The height of the blue bars rises
      steadily through the century, reflecting a steady rise in theatrical activity. The red bars
      however, although rising in line with the blue for the first three or four decades, shoot up
      in the 1850s and 1860s before tailing off abruptly, with no titles at all from the 80s or 90s.
      We conclude that while Lacy has a strong preference for plays from the mid century, his
      coverage of the earlier parts of the century is reasonable, and certainly more reliable than
      for its end. We should be wary of making any inferences about plays produced after the 1870s.
      <hi>CLICK</hi></p>

    </div>

    <div>
     <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(15)"
      >Size</ref></head>
     <p>The Nicoll data gives no indication of the size of each play, and it is therefore not
      possible to ascertain whether Lacy has a systematic preference for longer or shorter pieces.
      The data available suggests that in fact there is a good mix of sizes in the LAE. </p>
     <p>This graphic shows the counts for “small” (less than 20 printed pages), “medium” (less than
      50), or “large” (50 or more) plays, expressed as a percentage of the total number of plays
      assigned to each decade. For the decades before the 1820s, the preponderance of long plays may
      be attributable to the influence of the traditional repertoire (Shakespeare et al). Lack of
      data makes the counts for the 80s and 90s inherently unreliable, as previously noted. However,
      for the six decades between, we observe a reasonably stable distribution of roughly 50% small,
      40% medium, and 10% long titles. <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
    </div>
    <!--   <div>
               <head>Authorship</head>
               <p>Authorship is a much contested property. The best we can do, faced with numerous
                  incidences of multiple authorship, simple pseudonymity, and anonymity, is to
                  believe what the title page tells us, even if there is good reason to believe that
                  the work in question is misattributed, plagiarized, or downright stolen. It tells
                  us mostly that where authors are not entirely unknown – and approximately half of
                  the entries in Nicoll’s lists fall into that category – they are primarily male
                  and middle class, and occasionally polyphiloprogenitive. Which is to say that
                  several Victorian dramatists were remarkably prolific.</p>
               <table rend="frame" xml:id="Table2">
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell cols="3" rend="center">LAE</cell>
                     <cell cols="3" rend="center">Nicoll’s Handlists</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell role="label">authors</cell>
                     <cell role="label">titles</cell>
                     <cell role="label">%titles</cell>
                     <cell role="label">authors</cell>
                     <cell role="label">titles</cell>
                     <cell role="label">%titles</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Few (&lt;5)</cell>
                     <cell>267</cell>
                     <cell>431</cell>
                     <cell>26.9</cell>
                     <cell>3290</cell>
                     <cell>5250</cell>
                     <cell>31.7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Some (5-10)</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                     <cell>568</cell>
                     <cell>35.5</cell>
                     <cell>274</cell>
                     <cell>2043</cell>
                     <cell>12.3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Many (&gt;10)</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>599</cell>
                     <cell>37.4</cell>
                     <cell>309</cell>
                     <cell>9222</cell>
                     <cell>55.8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">total</cell>
                     <cell>338</cell>
                     <cell>1598</cell>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>3873</cell>
                     <cell>16515</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>This table shows the numbers of authors represented by “many” (more than 10),
                  “some” (between 5 and 10), or “few” (less than 5) titles, in the LAE and in
                  Nicoll’s Handlists. For both datasets, less than a third of all titles are
                  produced by less prolific authors, despite their greater numbers. The most
                  prolific authors account for 37% of Lacy titles, significantly less than in the
                  Nicoll lists where they account for more than half. These differences suggest a
                  conscious decision on Lacy’s part to diversify as far as possible his chosen
                  authors.  <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
            </div>-->
    <div>
     <head>Genre</head>
     <p>Victorian theatre is obsessed with itself. The ostentatiously exuberant language of the
      title pages bear witness to its self-importance even where this is being mocked. The theatre
      itself is very often the subject of the play. In Planche’s <title>Garrick Fever</title>
      (Olympic, 1839, L0321) an Irish actor much given to channelling Garrick’s Shakespeare is
      mistaken for the genuine article, thus enabling him to gain the approval of his girl
      friend’sactor-manager father. In the same author’s <title> The Camp at the Olympic</title>
      (played somewhat recursively at the Olympic in October 1853, L0170) real life theatre managers
      Mr and Mrs Wigan attempt to decide on the style of their next production – a conceit so
      pleasing that it was more or less entirely stolen by Henry James Byron ten years later for his
      <title>1863 ; or, The Sensations of the Past Season </title>(St James’s. Dec. 1863, L0911) </p>
     <!--  <p>The subtitle of a play usually claims a place for it within an implicit
                  contemporary terminology, often simply stated : “A Domestic Drama in three acts”
                  (L0646) for example. Sometimes, as here, the claim is clear (“A Farce”, “A
                  Burlesque”, “An original Tragedy” , “An Entirely New and Original Extravaganza”).
                  Sometimes, it is entirely misleading: Morton’s version of the classic farce
                     <title>Box and Cox</title> describes itself ironically as “A Romance of Real
                  Life in one act” And rather frequently the text deploys a deliberately opaque
                  terminology clearly intended to be self-mocking “An entirely new and original
                  Operatico Terpsichorean Burlesque in two acts” (L0016); “A Scandinavian sketch,
                  containing as much irrelevant matter as possible” (L0044); or “An Original Irish
                  Stew” (L1307). </p>-->
     <p> When compiling his Handlists, Nicoll added a code to each entry to indicate “the nature of
      the play itself”, with the caveat that "Where possible, the designation employed in the
      original bills has here been followed” – These characterisations are thus indicative of the
      language with which Victorian theatre chose to describe itself at a particular moment , rather
      than any kind of formally organized taxonomy. The two lists propose some very general terms (D
      for drama, F for Farce, P for Pantomime etc.); and many others more nuanced such as “Military
      Drama”, “Operatic Drama”, “Poetic Drama” etc. Of the 178 different codes, nearly two thirds
      (117) are used fewer than 5 times. Or, to put it another way, the top ten codes between them
      account for 19,833 out of the total number of 24,408 entries – over 80% of the whole
      population. This suggests that we will not go too far wrong if we simply disregard the 160
      codes with relative frequencies below 1%. </p>
     <p>A similar frequency distribution applies in the 1477 titles which appear both as an entry in
      Nicoll’s handlists and as a title in the LAE: here, 97% of titles are accounted for by the top
      20 codes. </p>

     <p><hi>CLICK</hi> The height of the bars here indicates <ref
      target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(17)">the number of titles for
      each genre code</ref>, expressed as a percentage. Only codes with values of 1% or above in the
      Nicoll list are included. Several differences between the two datasets are apparent: for
      example, 30% of LAE titles (red) are coded F (farce), but only 11% of Nicoll titles (blue) .
      Conversely, 30% of the titles in Nicoll’s list are coded D ( Drama ), but this code is used
      for only 20% of LAE titles. Several categories (notably Ext for Extravaganza, and Bsq, for
      Burlesque) are over-represented in the LAE . Particularly striking is the under-representation
      of category P (pantomime) which makes up 10% of Nicoll entries, but less than 1% of Lacy
      titles. We may hypothesize, again, that this follows conscious selection by Lacy – thinking
      perhaps that pantomime scripts are unlikely to sell as well as farce – or seek some other
      explanation. <hi>CLICK</hi></p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head><ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-11-07_caen_slides.html#(18)"
     >Conclusion</ref></head>
    <p>We conclude that the LAE is a good source of information about the development of
     specifically comic performance of various kinds and sizes in the period between 1850 and 1870.
     Before 1850 the data is harder to analyse because of interference from older classic titles;
     after 1870 the data is simply missing. We suggest that the LAE provides a sound basis for
     understanding the evolution of the Victorian sense of humour over this period. </p>
   </div>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
