<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/home/lou/Public/TEIslides/teislides.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>"The most perfect edition of plays ever published": the Digital Lacy project</title>

    <author>Lou Burnard (Independent Scholar)</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>born digital</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2025-08-18">Created file</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <!-- <div type="slide">
    <head>"The most perfect edition of plays ever published": the Digital Lacy project</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/theBestest.png"/>
    </figure>
    
   </div>-->

   <div type="slide">
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/THLacy.jpg" height="55%" width="50%"/>
     <head>Thomas Hailes Lacy (1809-1873)</head>
    </figure>

    <cb/>
    <list>
     <item>Lacy was the
      leading theatrical publisher of "Acting Editions" -- practical working documents printed at 6d
      a copy for individual titles, or 5s for a bound volume of 15 titles. </item>
     <item>Between 1848 and 1873, his <title>Lacy's Acting Edition of Plays</title>, grew to contain
      100 volumes of 15 titles each: it was sold across the globe, and made him a reasonable
      fortune.</item>
     <item>The LAE is a unique sample, apparently covering the full range of Victorian Theatrical
      presentations</item>
     <item>The population it samples approximates to the titles listed in vols 4 and 5 of Allardyce Nicoll's magisterial <title>History of English
       Drama</title> -- c. 24,000 distinct titles performed between 1800 and 1900.</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Research question: how representative is the LAE ?</head>
    <p>A corpus is a sample, hopefully representative of a known population. Initial comparisons
     between the LAE and Allardyce Nicoll's <title>Handlist</title>s suggest distributions of size,
     age, and mode are comparable. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/agebyvol.png"/>
     <head>First performance dates by volume</head>
    </figure>
    <p rend="box">"It is hard to avoid the conclusion that Lacy astutely leavened the mix for each
     volume, using mainly contemporary titles to complement the old favourites." (cf. <ref
      target="https://doi.org/10.58079/140cy">How old are these plays?</ref>)</p>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Digital Lacy project</head>
    <list>
     <item>Builds on and expands data from Richard Pearson's <title>Victorian Plays Project</title>
      (VPP), AHRB funded 2005-2007 </item>
     <item>
      <list>
       <item>The VPP produced a catalogue of the LAE, along with c. 15,000 page images from a copy
        held at Birmingham Library</item>
       <item>These were OCRd, proofed, and made available in a PDF format as visually faithful as
        possible to the original</item>
       <item>By 2014, the project had processed 340 titles which were distributed from a site at the
        University of Galway</item>
       <item>Following Pearson's death in 2018, the project was frozen; by June 2022 the website had
        disappeared...</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>In 2022, with the aid of researchers who worked on the project, I recovered most of the
      resources it had created and transferred them to a github repository, where I continue to work on them</item>
     <item>Digital Lacy now combines : <list>
       <item> a detailed and expanding set of metadata relating to the LAE and its authors, enhanced
        with links to available digital versions</item>
       <item>a slowly increasing number of TEI-XML transcripts</item>
      </list></item>
    </list>
    <p>Proto-website at <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/"
     >http://lb42.github.io/Lacy</ref></p>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Current workflow</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/workflow-1.png" width="80%"/>
    </figure>
    <cb/>
    <list>
     <item>Goal is consistent minimal encoding of a known source edition</item>
    <item> VPP texts: 
     <list><item>VPP-PDF to Docx (OCR by Abby, thanks Huma-num)</item>
     <item>DocX to TEI-All (XSLT by TEI)</item>
     <item>TEI-All to Lacy XML (homegrown XSLT scripts)</item></list></item>
     <item>Minimal markup, largely ignoring visual salience</item>
     <item>TEI schema defined by ODD very close to dracor-schema </item>
    </list>
    <p>Impossible without manual intervention: this is the main bottleneck in current workflow.</p>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>DraCor vs Lacy: how close ?</head>
    <p>DraCor and Lacy have a few ideological differences...</p>
    <list>
     <item>In DraCor metadata, the digital version is primary, any source version being nested
      within it; in Lacy, that hierarchy is reversed. </item>
     <item>Some DraCor metadata (notably performances and identifiers) is relegated to a
       <gi>standOff</gi>; in Lacy it is imbricated in the TEI Header </item>
     <item>DraCor uses explicit scene divisions to define stage-presence, as the basis for its
      network analysis; a quarter of Lacy titles don't have scene divisions.</item>
     <item>Lacy uses many of the available TEI tags for the front matter of a play ; DraCor largely
      ignores these. </item><item>DraCor makes no attempt to support metadata such as editorial correction, variant readings, modifications for performance, etc; Lacy should, but doesn't. </item>
    </list>
    <p rend="box">However - the DraCor team is very responsive and helpful !</p>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Tagging headaches are another persistent challenge </head>
    <p>These texts are full of phenomena which break or strain the simple OHCO model... </p>
    <list>
     <item>speaker may be implicit or multiple</item>
     <item>musical numbers (<gi>spGrp</gi>) don't tesselate and may self-nest</item>
     <item>metadata may be missing, uncertain, inconsistent or just wrong </item>
    </list>
    <p>For example ....</p>
   </div>


   <div type="slide">
    <head>Implied speaker</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/impliedSpkr.png"/>
     <graphic url="media/impliedSpkrX.png"/>
     
    </figure>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Speeches assigned to multiple speakers</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/egMult.png" width="70%"/>
     <graphic url="media/egMultx.png" width="60%"/>
    </figure>
    <p>(<gi>stage</gi> not currently permitted within <gi>speaker</gi>)</p>

   </div>


   <div type="slide">
    <head>Nesting of simultaneous speech or song</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/parallelExample.png" width="65%"/>
    </figure>
    <cb/>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/tyrolienne.png" width="45%"/>
    </figure>
    <p>The whole dance (the Tyrolienne) is contained by a <gi>spGrp</gi> element which contains two
     nested <gi>spGrp</gi> elements, each containing two <gi>sp</gi> elements to be performed in
     parallel. (See also <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2695">TEI Issue 2695</ref>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Tentative suggestions and conclusions</head>
    <list>
     <item>TEI conformance is crucial to the interoperability of DraCor corpora. The DraCor
      profile/ODD should specify which parts of the TEI model are mandatory, desirable, permissible,
      unsupported ... </item>
     <item>The documentation provided by the DraCor ODD is good, but could be improved: more
      examples and more discussion of edge cases would be useful ; as would simple tutorial guides showing how to use DraCor-conformant corpora with a variety of
      tools (not only python, plz)</item>
     <item>Provide a forum for corpus creators to compare methods and tools, and to discuss possible solutions to common encoding problems</item>
     <item>Encourage corpus creators to facilitate gap-filling in DraCor coverage, e.g. ECCO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
