<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>The most perfect edition of plays ever published: an introduction to the Digital Lacy Project</title>
    <author>Lou Burnard</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2023-11-30</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Working draft available online</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>This is an original document</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <listChange>
    <change><date>2023-12-06T00:10:02Z</date><name>First TEI edition</name></change>
   </listChange>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
    <head>     
     “The most perfect Edition of Plays ever published” : digitizing Lacy’s Acting
     Edition.</head>
    <p><graphic n="1001" width="14.047611111111111cm" height="3.003902777777778cm"
     url="media/image1.png" rend="block"/></p>
    <p>The Victorian theatre has not enjoyed documentation or digitization as systematically as has
     the Victorian novel, reflecting perhaps scholarly perception of their comparative artistic
     significance. Yet it is a truism that the Victorian popular theatre and the Victorian novel
     were in many ways complementary. In Emily Allen's words, "Victorian theatre was the novel's
     ally, inspiration, and competitor" [Allen] As an ongoing expression of popular culture,
     nineteenth century theatre has deep roots and many branches. Its lineage takes us from the high
     gothic of romantic melodrama to the memes of cinema and modern day television; its voices
     combine sensational spectacle, social commentary, and domestic realism. </p>
    <p>Nineteenth century dramatic works were frequently reprinted or re-edited, both in London and
    the USA, well into the twentieth century, attesting to a continued demand, despite the supposed
    lack of literary merit in the works of Douglas Jerrold, J.R. Planché, Shirley Brooks, J.
    Palgrave Simpson, John Madison Morton, and other stalwarts of the Dramatic Authors’ Society.
    Unlike the popular novel, however, the popular theatre produced very few authors or works we
    would now consider “canonical”, although many writers attest to their influence.</p>
    <p>The decline of the Victorian theatre over the long period between the glory days of 18th
     century Covent Garden and the emergence of Shaw and Ibsen has frequently been attributed [eg
     Barrett 1999] to the fact that plays were not published to be read, but for the benefit of
     actors and managers planning to produce them on stage, and primarily as a means of giving the
     work some degree of copyright protection. The typical “acting edition” was a low budget, often
     down at heels, and purely utilitarian production, designed to facilitate the full theatrical
     experience, but in no way replace it. Like the libretto or the score of an opera, it was not
     aimed at the critic in his study, still less the general reader. </p>
    <p>Consequently,for those wishing to see the phenomenon as a whole and to perform a kind of
     distant reading of its texts, bibliographic resources are hard to find, and reliable
     collections of play texts even more so. A small number of encyclopaedic reference lists
     [Nicoll, Mullen] exist, but documentation of the Victorian theatre tends to focus on the
     careers of individual actors, writers, or institutions. Similarly, where collections of the
     primary source materials are available, it is as a consequence of individual collections or
     bequests rather than any attempt at systematic coverage. The literary canon provides no
     guidance as to how we should best sample theatrical production between (say) the end of the
     Napoleonic wars and the end of the 19th century, though those years are liberally sprinkled
     with works of enormous vigour, originality, and influence – as well as much dross. </p>
    <p>As a proxy for such a sample, we propose to use the approximately 1500 titles making up
    Lacy's Acting Edition of Plays, published by Thomas Hailes Lacy (1809-1873) between 1848 and
    1873. Lacy was by no means the first person to hit on the idea of reprinting and publishing
    uniform editions of dramatic texts. Like his predecessors John Dick, John Cumberland, and John
    Duncombe, Lacy’s business plan was to buy up (where necessary) the copyrights of successful
    pieces, and reprint them for a mass market, both as individual texts, and in collected volumes.
    The public he envisaged included both devotees of the theatre and professionals seeking material
    for guaranteed hits. Consequently, his “Acting Editions” provided everything needful to produce
    a play: including details of costumes, settings, blocking, accompanying business etc. as well as
    cast lists and the text itself. It has been plausibly argued [Weig 2017] that during the Acting
    Edition’s long publication history, its target audience changed, aiming more at the middle class
    amateur who would have felt uncomfortable in a real theatre, and less at the professional
    theatrical entrepreneur. In any case, “new” titles appeared regularly until 1873 when Lacy sold
    the whole collection to Samuel French, an American publisher with whom he had exchanged plays
    for publication for the previous two decades. </p>
    <p>Lacy accumulated authors’ copyrights assiduously over many years, and also maintained a small
     stable of hack authors under contract, who produced dozens of titles each. It seems unlikely
     that the constituent elements of each volume of the Lacy’s Acting Edition – 15 titles for each
     of the 100 volumes under study – were selected in a purely adventitious way. The choice of
     titles for the “Acting Edition” probably reflects the insight of a shrewd publisher as to which
     titles were most likely to sell. A consideration of the salient characteristics of each of the
     titles published in the series over its long history may therefore serve as an approximate
     metric for the evolution of taste – or perhaps the vagaries of fashion – during the period
     concerned. Such characteristics as genre, length, source, antiquity, and expense, which can be
     determined relatively simply for each title, may also be useful as a means of determining the
     extent to which any given subset of titles is representative of the whole. </p>
    <p>Copies of individual titles, individual volumes, or sets of volumes from Lacy’s Acting
     Edition are to be found in many libraries worldwide, though the edition itself has not, to my
     knowledge, been the subject of any extensive bibliographic study. Many surviving copies, both
     of individual titles and of complete volumes or volume sets, have been digitized in page
     format, typically by Google acting on behalf of the holding library. One particularly notable
     example is the University of Michigan’s copy of a nearly complete set of the first 94 volumes,
     all of which were digitized (though with varying degrees of success) and are now “freely”
     available to those able to access the Hathi Trust collection. But an Internet prowl will
     quickly reveal the existence of many other titles, including some from the remaining six
     volumes, similarly digitized by Google, using copies from a number of other libraries.</p>
    <div>
     <head>The Victorian Plays Project</head>
     <p>Production of a digitized version of the Acting Edition was first proposed by Prof. Richard
      Pearson, whose Victorian Plays Project (VPP) was funded by the UK’s Arts and Humanities
      Research Council between 2005 and 2007. Initially hosted at the University of Worcester in the
      UK, the project moved to the National University of Ireland in Galway in 2014. Sadly, the VPP
      website has not been developed since 2015, and the untimely death of Professor Pearson at the
      end of 2018 (<ref target="https://bavs.ac.uk/uncategorized/obituary-richard-pearson/"
      >https://bavs.ac.uk/uncategorized/obituary-richard-pearson</ref>) casts its future
      development into serious doubt. As is all too often the case, preservation of a digital
      archive turns out to depend as much on individual personal support as on technological
      constraints. </p>
     <p>A key deliverable of the VPP was an online catalogue of the whole of Lacy’s Acting Edition,
      based on a copy preserved in what was then the Birmingham Central Library. The current Digital
      Lacy project is thus an attempt to revive the VPP, by extending and correcting that catalogue,
      and by creating a balanced sample of transcribed texts. </p>
     <p>In the Spring of 2022, I was funded by the CLS Infra project to produce a short scoping
      study (see
      https://clsinfra.io/opportunities/tnafellowships/tna-archive/tna-fellow-lou-burnard/),
      investigating the current state of the VPP deliverables, and looking at what might be needed
      to revive it. I introduced a new numbering system to the catalogue, made numerous minor
      corrections, and enriched it with links to existing digital versions of the texts. Some of the
      challenges involved are described in a blog posting titled Hunting for Lacy traces in the
      digital world, dated 16 Aug 2022; see <ref target="https://foxglove.hypotheses.org/678"
      >https://foxglove.hypotheses.org/678</ref> . I also started work on producing TEI-conformant
      transcriptions of some of the titles.</p>
     <p>Titles for inclusion in the original VPP were selected apparently at random though with
      notably fewer titles from the later volumes. Individual titles were scanned and saved as TIFF
      files, a total of nearly 16,000 pages. These were then processed by Abbyy Fine Reader to
      produce a plain text transcription, which was then edited to mimic the typographic appearance
      of the original publications, and saved in PDF format. My understanding is that this PDF was
      again proof read and corrected directly using Adobe software, which implies that the PDF
      versions available online (until recently) probably represent the best available texts as
      regards accuracy, though they are still not entirely error-free. On the other hand,
      corrections in some cases introduced some variation in formatting (for example font size or
      case changes not present in the original). </p>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head>Other online sources</head>
     <p>Another interesting subset of Lacy titles is to be found online in the Hall Collection of
      Prompt Books held by the University of Warwick.
      [https://wdc.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/hall] A prompt book is quite a different
      beast from a collected volume: it will typically contain annotations from its first owner,
      indicating all manner of changes to the text, intended to facilitate an individual actor’s
      performance. The Hall collection comprises about 600 individual scripts, used as prompt books
      by Clara St. Casse, an actress, who travelled with various British touring companies in the
      19th century. These are freely available both as TIFF page images, and in a lightweight PDF
      form from the Internet Archive. 116 titles are derived from the LAE. </p>
     <p>A digitization in page image form is not of course the same thing as a machine-tractable
      transcription. Some LAE titles have however been transcribed, and may be found online. Project
      Gutenberg has a total of 17 titles in various shades of HTML; the diligent searcher will also
      find a few cases where a site dedicated to a particular writer has included some texts from
      the Lacy edition: for example titles by Henry Milner, or W.S. Gilbert. And finally in a sort
      of half way house about 40 LAE titles are currently included in Proquest’s “Literature Online”
      collection. These titles were originally prepared in TEI format for publication by Chadwyck
      Healey in a collection of “Nineteenth Century English Drama” on CD, but now seem to be
      available only in RTF form.</p>
     <p>LAE titles are thus potentially available from a variety of sources and in a number of
      formats:</p>
     <p>(1) Page images from the UM volume set (1381 of 1422 titles found)</p>
     <p>(2a) Page images used by the VPP from the Birmingham volume set (263 found)</p>
     <p>(2b) Page images from the VPP corrected version of 2a (343 found)</p>
     <p>(3) Page images from the Hall collection of individual titles (76 found)</p>
     <p>(4) Page images from various other sources (887 found)</p>
     <p>(5) Transcriptions derived from the Chadwyck Healey publications: (42 found)</p>
     <p>(6) Transcriptions in HTML distributed by Project Gutenberg and (mostly) checked against
      page images from the Internet Archive (17 found)</p>
     <p>In practice there is little overlap. A few LAE titles (82) have never been digitized at all.
      957 – well over half – are available in one form only; I have found 410 titles for which two
      different forms are available, and only 63 for which there are 3 or more.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head>Towards TEI transcriptions</head>
     <p>I experimented with a number of different workflows in pursuit of my quixotic goal of
      producing a TEI conformant version of the LAE. None of these was 100% successful, in that all
      of them required a degree of manual tidy up, varying in the length of time needed.</p>
     <p>Sophisticated machine-learning approaches to create TEI-XML versions more or less
      automatically from PDF sources have been used, for example in the Europarl or RDA projects.
      But these projects are for the most part dealing with very large quantities – thousands – of
      fairly consistently formatted documents. Almost every PDF I looked at in the VPP has a
      slightly different format. There is little consistency in the way in which speaker prefixes or
      stage directions are formatted. Variations in type size and format are unpredictable. The
      colleagues I approached with expertise in this area confirmed my suspicions that it would be
      impractical to adopt this approach until a reasonably large number (in the hundreds) of
      correctly tagged play texts was available to serve as a training set. </p>
     <p>In the absence of a training set, I experimented with some freely available tools claiming
      to convert PDF to HTML, or XML. Such tools attempt to represent the way the characters of a
      PDF file recognised are to be displayed on the page, in terms of lines, blocks, pages etc.
      There are two widely used open XML standards for encoding such information: PAGE and ALTO; an
      interesting project called SegmOnto is developing generic tools for constructing a conversion
      pipeline based on ALTO, though there is as yet no stable product. I experimented with a much
      older tool, called pdftohtml derived from the venerable xpdf library which was originally
      developed in order to produce printed output from a PDF file independently of Adobe software.
      This can be used to generate XML files conforming to an ALTO-like schema which can then be
      processed by a series of XSLT scripts (for example, those provided by Dario Kampkaskar in his
      pdftotei library) generate something more tractable and TEI-like. </p>
     <p>I also carried out some experiments with Abby FineReader, probably the current market leader
      in commercial OCR software. The French research agency Huma-Num provides access to Abbyy and
      also to Tesseract, its leading open source competitor, which enabled me to do some comparison
      between the two. </p>
     <p>The devil is, as ever, in the details. Of the systems I experimented with, all failed one or
      more of the following hurdles:</p>
     <list rend="bulleted">
      <item>white space between individual words must be preserved</item>
      <item>order of substrings within the document must be preserved</item>
      <item>font distinctions (italic vs roman) should be preserved</item>
      <item>adjacent structural units (e.g. a series of &lt;hi&gt; elements with the same values for
       @rend) should be merged correctly (almost impossible when for example an italicized stage
       direction contained non-italicized words)</item>
     </list>
     <p>None of the approaches I considered was able to provide a complete solution for a typical
      VPP PDF. The “least worst” solution I found was a pipeline in which Abbyy was used to generate
      a docx representation in order to preserve much of the original formatting, which was then
      further refined by a series of XSLT stylesheets, starting with the TEI-provided “docxtotei”
      conversion, and ending with a manual check of each transcript against the page images.</p>
     <p>Recognition of the gross structure (division into acts and scenes) was partially successful
      for most texts I examined, because the TEI stylesheets mostly correctly distinguished heading
      lines from body text. Similarly, it proved possible to automatically identify individual
      speeches by pattern matching (e.g. looking for blocks of text beginning with an italicized
      word followed by a full stop); to identify stage directions (individual blocks beginning with
      a [ character, or substrings given between parentheses) and so on. However, since these
      typographic patterns varied considerably across, and even within, texts a degree of manual
      intervention remains necessary.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head>The Lacy Markup Scheme</head>
     <p>As with any other TEI project, the target markup scheme for Lacy TEI XML files is defined by
      an ODD, which specifies all the TEI elements used, their attributes, datatypes etc. The first
      draft of this document was produced automatically from a preliminary set of six plays marked
      up by hand, and then further adapted as more plays were tested. It remains a work in
      progress.</p>
     <p>The Lacy ODD requires all plays to follow the same basic structure, and records only textual
      features likely to be of general use in analysis. It makes no attempt to support detailed
      philological markup, for example of textual variation, formatting effects, metrical or
      linguistic analysis etc. It does however include provision for recording detailed metadata
      about performance details, genre, size etc. for each title. Full details of the specification
      are provided by the Lacy Manual, which is maintained online along with the TEI documents (see
      http://lb42.github.io/Lacy/)</p>
     <p>Every title (that is, each work reprinted in the LAE) is considered to be a single
      &lt;TEI&gt; element, containing a TEI Header, and a &lt;text&gt; element. Every text element
      has front matter, a body, and an optional back. </p>
     <p>The body of a text consists of a sequence of stage directions, speeches, and speech-groups
      (e.g. musical numbers), represented by the TEI elements &lt;stage&gt;, &lt;sp&gt;, or
      &lt;spGrp&gt; respectively. An &lt;sp&gt; element will usually contain an initial speaker
      indication (&lt;speaker&gt;) followed by a series of paragraphs (&lt;p&gt;) or verse lines
      (&lt;l&gt;). These elements all contain running text alone, though a small number of other
      text-level elements is also permitted, for example page breaks, notes, words or phrases
      printed in italic, and transcriber corrections. Acts and scenes, if indicated in the source
      text, are marked using the TEI &lt;div&gt; element.</p>
     <p>Here for example is the start of R.H. Horne’s The Death of Marlowe (L1325)</p>
     <figure>
      <graphic n="1002" width="16.298333333333332cm" height="10.95375cm" url="media/image2.png"
       rend="block">
       <desc/>
      </graphic>
     </figure>
     <p>And here is the TEI encoded version of the same passage:</p>
     <figure>
      <graphic n="1003" width="17.5895cm" height="8.090958333333333cm" url="media/image3.png"
       rend="block">
       <desc/>
      </graphic>
     </figure>
     <p>Note that font variation, in particular the use of small caps and italic, has been discarded
      entirely, as has the additional indentation used to indicate fragmentation of the verse line.
      The goal of this encoding is not to represent every visually salient feature, but simply those
      which are likely to be functionally significant. A program such as CETEICEAN can take
      advantage of this markup to produce something visually satisfactory:</p>
     <figure>
      <graphic n="1004" width="16.853958333333335cm" height="9.181041666666667cm"
       url="media/image4.png" rend="block">
       <desc/>
      </graphic>
     </figure>
     <p>The front matter of a Lacy title can contain several distinct components:</p>
     <list rend="bulleted">
      <item>a titlepage</item>
      <item>performance notes</item>
      <item>a cast list, usually listing roles and actors</item>
      <item>information on costumes</item>
      <item>a list of scenes or spectacles</item>
      <item>other prefatory or dedicatory matter</item>
     </list>
     <p>For each of these, we use the standard TEI elements, and their subcomponents, as listed
      below. Again, we do not attempt to reproduce fully the appearance of the original even though
      title pages and programme lists in particular often exhibit considerable typographic
      exuberance. </p>
     <div>
      <head>Title Page</head>
      <p style="text-align: left;">The &lt;titlePage&gt; element contains a transcription of the
       text printed on the title page of a play. This will usually contain</p>
      <list rend="numbered">
       <item>at least one and usually several title fragments, each within a
        &lt;titlePart&gt;</item>
       <item>a byline indicating the author and their other works</item>
       <item>an imprint, usually including Lacy’s address</item>
      </list>
      <p style="text-align: left;">For example:</p>
      <figure>
       <graphic n="1005" width="8.639527777777777cm" height="13.073944444444445cm"
        url="media/image5.png" rend="block">
        <desc/>
       </graphic>
      </figure>
      <p>This would be encoded as follows:</p>
      <figure>
       <graphic n="1006" width="17.5895cm" height="3.653013888888889cm" url="media/image6.png"
        rend="block">
        <desc/>
       </graphic>
      </figure>
      <p>The formatting of the original is mostly discarded: the markup only distinguishes the main
       title from its subtitle, and also indicates the boundaries of the other titles mentioned.
       Case is normalized, and line breaks ignored, just as when transcribing the text of the play.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div>
      <head>Performance notice and cast list</head>
      <p>Most plays contain a formal statement recording the date and place of their first
       performance, since this counts as an assertion of copyright. It is often associated with a
       dramatis personae, indicating the characters of the play and usually an actor’s name. </p>
      <figure>
       <graphic n="1007" width="12.197291666666667cm" height="8.588375cm" url="media/image7.png"
        rend="block">
        <desc/>
       </graphic>
      </figure>
      <p>The list of roles is potentially of importance in analysing for example the differing
       contributions made by male and female roles, and in identifying how often a female actor
       takes on a male role. We include this information in the tagged version :</p>
      <figure>
       <graphic n="1008" width="17.5895cm" height="5.753805555555555cm" url="media/image8.png"
        rend="block">
        <desc/>
       </graphic>
      </figure>
     </div>
     <div>
      <head>Setting and costumes</head>
      <p>Information about the setting, the length of presentation, and detailed notes on costume
       are also commonly found in the front matter. </p>
      <figure>
       <graphic n="1009" width="11.959166666666667cm" height="8.757708333333333cm"
        url="media/image9.png" rend="block">
        <desc/>
       </graphic>
      </figure>
      <p>These are marked up as follows:</p>
      <figure>
       <graphic n="10010" width="17.5895cm" height="5.596819444444445cm" url="media/image10.png"
        rend="block">
        <desc/>
       </graphic>
      </figure>
     </div>
     <div>
      <head>Other prefatory matter</head>
      <p style="text-align: left;">Plays occasionally include other kinds of prefatory matter, as in
       this case</p>
      <figure>
       <graphic n="10011" width="17.755305555555555cm" height="9.673166666666667cm"
        url="media/image11.png" rend="block">
        <desc/>
       </graphic>
      </figure>
      <p style="text-align: left;"> Such matter may be marked up up using the usual TEI elements
       &lt;div&gt;, &lt;head&gt;, &lt;p&gt;, &lt;list&gt;, &lt;signed&gt;, &lt;epigraph&gt;,
       &lt;quote&gt;, etc. In this case, the first paragraph contains a highlighted phrase, and a
       title, for which we use &lt;hi&gt; and &lt;title&gt; respectively. </p>
      <figure>
       <graphic n="10012" width="18.139833333333332cm" height="3.4060694444444444cm"
        url="media/image12.png" rend="block">
        <desc/>
       </graphic>
      </figure>
      <p>Further examples are provided in the Lacy Manual referenced above.</p>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div>
     <head>Next steps</head>
     <p>As of this writing, over 50 titles have been converted to TEI format, and the work is
      continuing, if slowly. At the same time, I am working on stylesheets and other tools to
      analyse the emerging corpus. But the first priority will be to launch a new “Digital Lacy”
      website presenting the revised catalogue, enriched with links to other useful resources. </p>
    </div>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
