<div>
 <head>APPENDIX A
  THE THEATRES, 1800-1850</head>
 <div>
  <head>I. London and Environs</head>
  <p>
   In this list I have included all the theatres and houses of enter-
   tainment known to me between the opening and the middle of
   the century. This account, of course, could have been extended
   to great length by the enumeration of managers and the occupancy
   of actors, but such detail appeared not to have importance enough
   for inclusion here. I have restricted myself, therefore, to the
   outstanding facts, which I have endeavoured to make as accurate
   as possible. It will be observed that change of name was common
   in this period, and I have thought it best to tabulate the theatres
   separately under their various titles rather than group these titles
   under a single heading. Full cross-references indicate the history
   of any single building during the half-century.
  </p><p> 
   Almost all these theatres are new. In 1800 only nine theatres
   were in regular use: Drury Lane, Covent Garden, the Opera House
   in the Haymarket, the Theatre Royal, Haymarket, Sadler’s Wells,
   the Royal Amphitheatre, the Royal Circus, the Royaliyf and the
   Sans Souci. Of these, practically all were rebuilt during this era,
   and, as will be realised, many fresh playhouses rose in rivalry
   to them in many districts of London.
   </p><p>
   The Academic Theatre (Leicester-place, Leicester-square). Under
   this name the Sans Souci was opened in 1806 as a Dramatic
   Academy.<note>  
    See The News for March 16, 1806.</note>
   </p><p>
   The Adelphi (Strand) [Adel.]. As the Adelphi, the old Sans
   Pareil was opened on Saturday, Oct. 23, 1819. This theatre was
   one of the best of the minors, F. H. Yates, Daniel Terry, the
   Mathews, B. N. Webster and Madame Celeste being among its
   most famous managers. It was rebuilt in 1858. Noted for weird
   and wonderful melodrama, it favoured the introduction of strange
   “effects” and of animal performers. Towards the close of the
   period it was also becoming famous for its burlesques.
   </p><p>
   The Albert Saloon, or Royal Albert Saloon (Shepherdess-walk,
   Britannia Fields, Hoxton). This house of entertainment seems to
   have been opened in 1844. In its most flourishing days it was
   owned by H. Brading. A remarkable feature in it was the two


  <pb n='223'/>

stages built at right angles to one another, one opening into a
closed theatre, the other in front of an open-air auditorium.
</p><p>
The Albion Theatre (Windmill-street, Haymarket). Not much
is known of this house. It was opened about 1832 and renamed
the following year as the New Queen’s. Its short life was ended in
1836.
</p><p>
The Aquatic Theatre. See Sadler’s Wells.
</p><p>
The Argyll Theatre or Argyll Rooms (Argyll-street, Regent-
street). French plays were given here by subscription between
1819 and 1823. See The New Private Saloon Theatre.
</p><p>
Astley’s Pavilion. See The Olympic Theatre.
</p><p>
Astley’s Theatre. See The Royal Amphitheatre.
</p><p>
The Bower Saloon (Stangate-street, Lambeth). This house of
variety entertainment was opened in 1837 by Phillips. It later
became the Royal Stangate Theatre, which was closed in 1878.
</p><p>
The Britannia Theatre or Saloon (High-street, Hoxton). Pre-
senting the usual mixed fare of “illegitimate” drama, the
Britannia, managed by Lane from 1841 to 1849, was directed
for fifty years (1849-99) by his widow, Mrs Sarah Lane.
</p><p>
The Brunswick Theatre. See The New Royal Brunswick Theatre.
</p><p>
The City Theatre. See The New City Theatre.
</p><p>
The City of London Theatre. See The Royal City of London
Theatre.
</p><p>
The Clarence Theatre. See The Royal Clarence Theatre.
</p><p>
The Coburg Theatre. See The Royal Coburg Theatre.
</p><p>
The Colosseum Theatre (Albany-street, Regent’s Park) [Col].
This house was opened for minor shows and variety entertain-
ments on Wednesday, July 12, 1837.
</p><p>
Covent Garden, Theatre Royal [C.G.]. As rebuilt in 17921,
Covent Garden stood unaltered until it was burned to the ground
on Sept. 20, 1808. The century opened with a bitter dispute
between the management and the actors (season 1799-1800)’.
In 1803 Kemble purchased a share in the theatre and took part
in its direction, On the destruction of their house the actors, in
1808, moved to the Opera House in the Haymarket. The founda-
tion stone of a new structure, designed by Robert Smirke, was
laid on Dec. 12, 1808, and this new Covent Garden was completed
by September 18 of the following year. The old building, which
had an ovoid auditorium, held 3013 persons®; the new building, in
<!--</p><p>
1 See A History of English Drama, iii. 229.
</p><p>
2 See A Statement of the Differences subsisting between the Proprietors
and Performers of the Theatre-Royal, Covent Garden (1800).
</p><p>
3 Gilliland, The Dramatic Mirror (1808), i. 135-8. The pit held 632,
the boxes 1200, the first gallery 820 and the upper gallery 361.
</p><p>-->
<pb n='224'/>

point of capacity, seems to have been a trifle smaller, but its stage
for accommodation and excellence of machinery was considered
“superior to that of any theatre in Europe!.”’ On its opening,
the attempt of the managers to raise the prices led to the notorious
O.P. riots’. In 1823 Charles Kemble assumed full control; under
his management and with the assistance of Edmund Kean (1827-
33) there was presented here a series of elaborate Shakespeare
productions. Alfred Bunn in October 1833 took over the manage-
ment of the two patent theatres; in October 1835 a new lessee,
Osbaldistone, tried the experiment of reducing prices—but with-
out success ; the Macready management lasted from 1837 to 1839;
that of Vestris and Mathews from 1839 to 1842. The next years
saw the gradual encroachment of musical shows, and on Tuesday,
April 6, 1847, the theatre was formally opened as The Royal
Italian Opera House. This was burned in 1856; the present
Covent Garden Opera House was opened two years later.
</p><p>
The Dominion of Fancy Theatre (Strand, ‘between South-
ampton-street and Exeter ’Change’’). This was opened on Friday,
March 1, 1816, for the exhibition of “pieces of mechanism,
ombres, chinois, etc.”
</p><p>
Drury Lane, Theatre Royal [D.L.]. The latest Drury Lane house
had been built by Holland in 17943. For the seasons 1800-1 and
1801-2 Kemble was in command. On his withdrawal, the theatre
sank steadily in dignity and worth; Feb. 24, 1809, saw its complete
destruction by fire. During the period from October 1809 to
May 1812, the Theatre Royal company acted at the King’s
Theatre in the Haymarket (March—May 1809) and at the Lyceum.
£400,000 was subscribed for a new building, the foundation-stone
of which was laid on Oct. 29, 1811, and which was formally
opened on October 10 of the following year. It was slightly
smaller than the 1794 structure, but still too large for the pro-
duction of intimate plays. When Elliston was manager, the
interior was reconstructed under Beazley’s direction; this, with
minor alterations, remains to the present day. At first managed
by Arnold and others, in 1814 it was taken over by a committee
which included Lord Byron. Edmund Kean aided in keeping
the house from bankruptcy. In 1818 Stephen Kemble became
manager and prices were lowered from 5s. and 3s. to 3s. and 2s.
The following year the theatre was leased to R. W. Elliston, who,
however, was forced to abandon it in 1823. Kean, Macready and
Liston were then its most noted actors. Various other lessees
<!--</p><p>
1 Covent-Garden Journal, i. 61.
2 See supra, pp. 9-10.
3 See A History of English Drama, iii. 229.
</p><p>-->
<pb n='225'/>

were secured, but all ended in failure. The notorious Alfred Bunn
management of the two patent theatres dates from October 1833
to 1839. In 1841 Macready assumed control, but was compelled
to retire in 1843, when Bunn once more took over the manage-
ment, with no more successful results.
</p><p>
Ducrow’s New National Arena (Church-street, Whitechapel).
This house was opened on Monday, Jan. 27, 1834, but I know
nothing more of its history.
</p><p>
The Eagle Saloon, also called The Grecian Saloon and The
Olympic Saloon (Shepherdess-walk, Britannia Fields, Hoxton).
Built by Thomas Rose about 1838, as the Grecian, this enter-
tainment theatre began to present “‘illegitimate”’ dramas regularly
from 1843. It was taken over by Benjamin Conquest in 1851 and
rebuilt by him in 1877; now it is used by the Salvation Army.
Evidently one of the most famous of the variety houses, its name is
immortalised in the still-remembered song, “ Pop goes the weasel.”
</p><p>
The East London Theatre (Weliclose-square, E.) [E.L.]. Under
the name of the Hast London, the Royalty was opened in August
1816, with considerable renovations, It had not a very distin-
guished. career, and, after being extensively altered in 1819
(opening Wednesday, Nov. 3), was burned down in 1826. On its
site was erected The Royal Brunswick Theatre.
</p><p>
The Effingham Saloon (Whitechapel). This saloon theatre was
opened in 1843 and rebuilt in 1867. It was burned in 1870, re-
erected and again destroyed by fire.
</p><p>
The English Opera House. See The Lyceum Theatre.
</p><p>
The Fitzroy Theatre. See The Royal Fitzroy Theatre.
</p><p>
Garrick’s Subscription Theatre (Leman-street, Goodman’s
Fields). The Garrick had been erected on the site of the old
Goodman’s Fields Theatre, and was opened on Monday, Jan. 3,
1831. It was burned in 1846 and rebuilt by B. O. Conquest. In
1859 it was used as a music-hall.
</p><p>
The German Theatre (Leicester-place, Leicester-square) [Ger-
man]. This is but a new name for the Sans Souci, used for the
performance of German dramas by “Schirmer’s Children”
during the season 1805-6. It opened under the new title on
Wednesday, July 17, 1805.
</p><p>
The Globe Theatre or Rotunda (Blackfriars-road). This was
opened as a theatre in 1833; by 1838, however, it had been turned
into a concert hall.
</p><p>
The Grecian Saloon. See The Eagle Saloon.
</p><p>
Haymarket, King’s Theatre or Opera House [H.J. A new
King’s Theatre had been built in 17901, and this, about 1801, was
<!--</p><p>
1 See A History of English Drama, iii. 230.
</p><p>-->
<pb n='226'/>

remodelled by Marinari. The stage was very large, 60 feet deep,
80 feet broad and 46 feet from box to box. Apparently at this
theatre “persons could walk from the pit or boxes behind the
scenes during the performance!.” In 1809 it was used by the
homeless patent companies. A reconstruction was undertaken
in 1818; in 1867 a fire destroyed the building; and a new Opera
House was erected in 1871-2. This was later known as Her
Majesty’s and was pulled down in 1892.
</p><p>
Haymarket, Theatre Royal (H.”]. The original “‘ Little Theatre?”
as built by Foote in 1766, was managed till 1820 by George
Colman the Younger, under whose direction it had a highly
successful career, specialising in farces and lighter pieces. On
Colman’s retiral, a new building was opened (on Wednesday,
July 4, 1821) by Morris, near the old site. In 1837 B. N. Webster
assumed the management. Here Samuel Phelps and Madame
Celeste first appeared in London, while from 1839 to 1841
Macready and Helen Faucit acted as “stars.” Webster retired
from the management in 1853.
</p><p>
Little Drury Lane. On Monday, April 19, 1813, an announce-
ment was made by the managers of the Olympic Pavilion that
their theatre would open under this name. The patentees objected
and the title was abandoned.
</p><p>
The Lyceum (Strand) [Lyc.]. Often described as the Large
Theatre, Lyceum, this building had originally been erected in 1765
as an exhibition room for artists, but by 1790 it was being used for
variety entertainments by Charles Dibdin. In 1794 it was rebuilt,
and when the century opened it was presenting such attractions as
“‘Musical Glasses,” “‘Phantasmagoria”’ and -battle pictures, with,
it is interesting to note, illumination by gas. The first theatrical
show I have been able to trace here appears in 1807. In 1809
S.J. Arnold received a licence to open it for musical plays, which
he did on Friday, April 21, 1809. From 1809 to 1812 it housed
the Drury Lane company and then once more returned to musical
drama. On Saturday, June 15, 1816, still under Arnold’s direction,
it was formally opened as The English Opera House [E.O.H.}, after
almost complete rebuilding. This was burned down in 1830, when
Arnold’s company acted in various theatres, chiefly the Adelphi.
The present Lyceum, as designed by Beazley, was opened on
Monday, July 14, 1834, for “‘the representation of English operas
and the encouragement of indigenous musical talent?.” From 1844
to 1847 it was managed by Robert and Mary Keeley; in 1847
</p><p>
1 Gilliland, op. cit. i. 167.
</p><p>
2 See A History of English Drama, iii. 229.
3 The present building was actually reconstructed about 1904.
<pb n='227'/>
Vestris and Mathews took it over, the latter retiring in 1855. In
the bills, both Lyceum and English Opera House are used to
describe this building.
</p><p>
The Marylebone Theatre (Church-street, Edgware-road)
[M’bone]. Under thisnamethe New Royal Sussex Theatre (or Royal
Pavilion, West) opened, it is said, in 1837; I have been unable to
discover an earlier record than 1844.
</p><p>
The Minor Theatre (Catherine-street, Strand). In 1829 the
Theatre of Variety seems to have assumed this name. Here stage-
struck youths were encouraged to pay for the privilege of appearing
in dramatic réles.
</p><p>
Miss Kelly’s Theatre and Dramatic School (73 Dean-street,
Soho-square) [Kelly’s]. Under the patronage of the Duke of
Devonshire, and fortified with a “minor” licence, Miss Kelly
opened this (the first of the personally-named theatres) on
Monday, May 25, 1840. It was used by her for the presentation
of plays for a few years; after 1850 it became The Soho and The
Royalty.
</p><p>
The New Theatre (Tottenham-street, Tottenham-court-road)
[New]. This house, “the decorations designed and executed by
Mr Greenwood” and “‘licensed by Act of Parliament,” was
opened on the site of The New Royal Riding School on Monday,
April 23, 1810. The following season it was renamed The Regency.
</p><p>
The New City Theatre (Milton-street, Fore-street, Cripplegate)
[City]. The New City Theatre was opened by John Kemble
Chapman on Monday, April 4, 1831, and ran till 1836, when it
was demolished. It was among the more respectable of the
“minors,” and welcomed such performers as Kean, Mrs Stirling
and Webster to its boards. For a time, from November 1833,
Moncrieff was its manager. An effort was made here to create
a Dramatic Academy, and for one season at least the house was
run in conjunction with The Royal Coburg.
</p><p>
The New Private Saloon Theatre, Argyle-street. The building
was opened in July 1807, and a few old plays were performed
occasionally. As the Argyll Rooms, it later (1819-23) witnessed
the production of some French dramas.
</p><p>
The New Queen’s Theatre. See The Albion Theatre.
</p><p>
The New Royal Brunswick Theatre (Goodman’s Fields). After
the burning of The East London Theatre in April 1826, a new
theatre was erected and opened on Monday, Feb. 25, 1828, as
the Brunswick. The following Thursday, during rehearsal, the
entire fabric collapsed.
</p>
<!--1 The Dramatic Magazine (1829), pp. 173-4.-->
<pb n='228'/>
The New Royal Riding School, late His Majesty’s Ancient
Concert Rooms, Tottenham-street. I find a pantomime presented
here in 1808. On the site of this building rose The New (later The
Regency) Theatre.
<p>
The New Royal Sussex Theatre (Church-street, Edgware-road).
This was apparently opened in 1832, and was later renamed as
The Royal Pavilion, West, and the Marylebone.
</p><p>
The New Royal West London Theatre (Tottenham-street)
[W.L.]. After considerable “improvements” The Regency
(formerly The New) opened under this name on Tuesday, Dec. 26,
1820. In 1822 it was described! as “‘the smallest of these places
devoted to the drama; and being of too humble pretensions to
create jealousy, is permitted to play tragedy, comedy, or farce, in
as legitimate a manner as the company is capable of doing.”
Later it became the Tottenham-street Theatre and The Queen’s
Theatre.
</p><p>
The New Standard Theatre. See The Royal Standard Theatre.
</p><p>
The New Strand Theatre. See The Strand Theatre.
</p><p>
The Olympic Theatre (Wych-street, or Newcastle-street, Strand)
[Olym.]. As the Olympic Pavilion [Pav.] or Olympic Saloon, this
house was opened by Philip Astley on Monday, Dec. 1, 1806. In
1807 it was called Astley’s New Olympic Pavilion and in 1808
Asiley’s Pavilion. Thereafter, it was usually named The Pavilion,
until it was taken over by Elliston in 1814, who, after failing to
open it as Little Drury Lane (q.v.), styled it The Olympic. The
opening day was Tuesday, Feb. 8, 1814. Rebuilt in 1818, it was,
from 1819 to 1831, managed by a variety of directors, including
Oxberry and Vining. At this time it specialised in melodrama.
In 1831 Madame Vestris took control and, with her extravaganzas
and light entertainments, made it one of the most refined theatres
in London. In 1839 Vestris and Mathews moved to Covent
Garden, leaving The Olympic to Samuel Butler, who in 1841
abandoned it to George Wild. In 1846 Miss Kate Howard and in
1847 Davidson undertook the direction. The theatre was burned
to the ground in March 1849, and a new house, which was finally
closed in 1899, was erected the following year. The importance of
the Vestris management of 1831-9 cannot be minimised.
</p><p>
The Olympic Pavilion. See The Olympic Theatre.
</p><p>
The Olympic Saloon. See The Olympic Theatre and The Eagle
Saloon.
</p><p>
The Orange-street Theatre (King’s-road, Chelsea). This is said
to have been used in 1831.
</p><p>
The Pantheon (Oxford-street). The older Pantheon had been
<!--</p><p>
1 The Percy Anecdotes Original and Select (1822), p. 168.-->
<pb n='229'/>
burned in 17921, but a new house under this name was opened on
Thursday, Feb. 27, 1812. It was used only during 1812 and 1813.
</p><p>
The Pavilion (Wych-street, Strand). See The Olympic Theatre.
</p><p>
The Pavilion (Whitechapel). See The Royal Pavilion.
</p><p>
The Peckham Theatre (High-street, Peckham). This was used
in 1828.
</p><p>
The Prince’s Theatre (King-street, St James’s) [Prince’s]. The
St Fames’s seems to have assumed this name for a time on Monday,
April 27, 1840.
</p><p>
The Princess’s Theatre (Oxford-street) [P’cess]. The Princess’s
began its history as The Royal Bazaar, The British Diorama and
Exhibition of Works of Art in 1828. The building was burned one
year after opening and was re-erected in 1830, when various
entertainments were given. In 1834 it seems to have been called
The Queen’s and, after a rebuilding in 1836, The Court®. In 1840
it became The Princess’s, and was opened originally (on Wednesday,
Sept. 30) for promenade concerts and musical shows. For a
number of years foreign opera in English was its chief attraction,
mainly directed by one Maddox. In 1850 the theatre was taken
over by Charles Kean.
</p><p>
The Queen’s Theatre (Fitzroy-square, Tottenham-court-road)
[Queen’s]. Under this title the Tottenham-street house was
opened on Thursday, Feb. 3, 1831 (see The New Royal Riding
School, The New Theatre, The Regency, The Regency Theatre of
Varieties, The New Royal West London Theatre and The Totien-
ham-street Theatre). George Macfarren was its first manager. Two
years later, it became The Royal Fitzroy Theatre, but a reversion
was made to the name of The Queen’s on Monday, Jan. 19, 1835.
In 1865, under the management of the Bancrofts, it became The
Prince of Wales’s.
</p><p>
The Regency Theatre (Fitzroy-square, Tottenham-court-road)
[Reg.]. Under this title The New Theaire was opened on Monday,
Oct. 28, 1810, with Moncrieff as manager. It had not a very
distinguished career. In 1818 it reopened, after a period of
inactivity, as The Regency Theatre of Varieties.
</p><p>
The Regency Theatre of Varieties (Fitzroy-square, Tottenham-
court-road). The old Regency was opened under this name on
Thursday, July 17, 1818. In 1820 it became The New Royal West
London Theatre.
</p><p>
The Royal Adelphi Theatre. See The Adelphi Theatre.
</p><p>
The Royal Albert Saloon. See The Albert Saloon.
</p><p>
The Royal Amphitheatre (Westminster Bridge Road) [R.A_].
</p><p>
<!--1 See A History of English Drama, iti. 230.
* I have been unable to verify these statements.-->
<pb n='230'/>
After the burning of the original circus-ring theatre on Friday,
July 2, 18031, plans were immediately made for a new house,
which opened on Monday, April 2, 1804. Its most famous period
was between 1830 and 1841, when Ducrow was manager. In 1807
it was called Astley’s Royal Amphitheatre and in 1808 Astley’s
Amphitheatre. Throughout its career it specialised in equestrian
melodrama and spectacle.
</p><p>
The Royal Borough Theatre (Tooley-street, S.E.). This was used
between 1834 and 1836, and then destroyed.
</p><p>
The Royal Circus (Blackfriars-road) [R.C.]. A rival of
Astley’s, The Royal Circus gained some notoriety through its
“‘burletta” exploits*. In 1810 it was taken over by Elliston and
renamed The Surrey Theatre, but, when Elliston moved to The
Olympic Pavilion in 1814 and Thomas Dibdin became manager,
it was redecorated and rebuilt ‘on the old plan” and once more
named The Royal Circus (opened on Monday, July 4, 1814). Its
second title (The Surrey) was given to it again on Monday, July 5s,
1819.
</p><p>
The Royal City of London Theatre (near Bishopsgate Station,
Norton Folgate) [C.L.]. This house was opened on Monday,
March 27, 1837, by Cockerton, and made a speciality of domestic
melodrama. By the middle of the century it had fallen to a very
low level, and was eventually closed in 18683,
</p><p>
The Royal Clarence Theatre (King’s Cross, New-road) [Clar.].
Under this name The Royal Panharmonion was opened on Monday,
May 7, 1832.
</p><p>
The Royal Coburg Theatre (Waterloo-road) [Cob.]. This theatre
was built by Dunn and Jones in 1816, and was opened, “under
the patronage of H.R.H. Prince Leopold of Saxe-Coburg,” on
Monday, May 11, 1818. The architect was Rudolph Cabanal
of Aachen. It had a very deep and narrow stage (94 feet by
32 feet) and in 1820 boasted the possession of a magnificent
looking-glass curtain. In 1819 it was managed by Moncrieff;
under him and others it indulged in melodrama of the most
startling nature; performed before audiences of the “‘lowest kind.”
Occasionally, however, West End players of distinction, such
as Edmund Kean and Madame Vestris, made their appearance
on its boards. In July 1833 it was formally renamed The Royal
Victoria Theatre.
</p><p>
The Royal Fitzroy Theatre (Fitzroy-square, Tottenham-court-
<!--</p><p>
1 It had been built in 1777. See A History of English Drama, iii,
230.
</p><p>
® See id. p. 230; and supra, p. 140.
</p><p>
3 On this theatre see M. Williams, Some London Theatres (1883).-->
<pb n='231'/>
road). Under this title, The Queen’s was opened in the autumn
of 1833. It was renamed The Queen’s on Monday, Jan. 109,
1835.
</p><p>
The Royal Kent Theatre (Kensington High-street). This theatre
was opened in 1834, and, after a chequered career, was closed in
1840.
</p><p>
The Royal Manor House Theatre (King’s-road, Chelsea). This
theatre was opened about 1838 and continued its career, partly
under the management of E. L. Blanchard, till 18411.
</p><p>
The Royal Marylebone Theatre. See The Marylebone Theatre.
</p><p>
The Royal Panharmonion Subscription Theatre (King’s Cross,
New-road). This, the first King’s Cross theatre, was opened on
April 18, 1831. The following year it became The Royal Clarence
</p><p>
Theatre.
</p><p>
The Royal Pavilion, West. See The New Royal Sussex Theatre.
</p><p>
The Royal Pavilion (Whitechapel-road, Mile-End). This house,
celebrated for “‘ Newgate melodrama,” was opened, under the
direction of Wyatt and Farrell, on Monday, Nov. 10, 1828. It
was burned to the ground in 1856, but, rebuilt, it has continued its
activities to the present day, being now the home of Yiddish drama
in the East End.
</p><p>
The Royal Princess’s Theatre. See The Princess’s Theatre.
</p><p>
The Royal Standard Theatre (Shoreditch) [Stand.]. This theatre
was opened for various entertainments in 1835, when it seated over
2000 people. In 1845 it was remodelled and was opened in
January of that year as The New Standard. In 1866 it was destroyed
by fire and rebuilt in 1868. ;
</p><p>
The Royalty Theatre (Wellclose-square) [Royalty]. The old
Royalty had been built in the eighteenth century by John Palmer?.
Denied a licence for plays, its managers specialised in spectacular
and musical shows. In 1800 it was owned by Philip Astley, who
seems to have used it as a winter house. In August 1816 the interior
was remodelled, and the new building opened as The East London
Theatre.
</p><p>
The Royal Victoria Theatre (Waterloo-road) [Vic.]. The Royal
Coburg definitely changed its name to this title in July 1833°.
It became one of the most successful of the minors, and was “‘in a
good way” under Abbot in 1834. It has, of course, since won fame
for its Shakespeare productions as the “Old Vic.’”
</p><p>
Sadler’s Wells Theatre (Rosebery Avenue, Islington) [S.W.].
<!--<p>
1 See E. L. Blanchard, Some Managerial Memories (The Theatre Annual,
1885, pp. 16-21).
</p><p>
2 See A History of English Drama, iii. 230.
</p><p>
3 See The Times for Tuesday, July 2, 1833.
</p><p>
4 See Cicely Hamilton and Lilian Baylis, The Old Vic. (1926).-->
<pb n='232'/>
The basic structure of this theatre dates back to 17651. Under
a variety of managements, and with the aid of the New River, it
indulged freely in nautical melodrama, using in 1806 the title of
The Aquatic Theatre. Charles Dibdin, Thomas King and William
Siddons were among its early managers. In 1844 Samuel Phelps
adopted it for his remarkable Shakespeare and other “legitimate”
productions. His direction continued until 1862. The theatre
as standing at present has the distinction of possessing the most
ancient fabric of any playhouse in London.
</p><p>
The St James’s Theatre (King-street, St James’s) [St. J.]. This
theatre was opened on Monday, Dec. 14, 1835 by John Braham
and for a few years struggled on precariously with musical shows.
By 1840 it was ‘‘to be let,” was renamed The Prince’s for a short
time, and eventually became the home in London of drama in
French. Its architect was Samuel Beazley.
</p><p>
The Sans Pareil Theatre (Strand) [Sans P.]. This was built by
one Scott and was opened on Friday, Nov. 27, 1806. It had a fair
career among the minors and in 1819 was renamed The Adelphi.
</p><p>
The Sans Souci Theatre (Leicester-place, Leicester-square)
[Sans S.]. As a house of varieties, The Sans Souct had been
opened by Dibdin in the eighteenth century. It had a chequered
career in the nineteenth, sometimes presenting crude farce,
sometimes (as The German) acting as a home of German drama,
sometimes professing, as The Academic Theatre, to be a Dramatic
Academy. Its importance is slight.
</p><p>
The Standard Theatre. See The Royal Standard Theatre.
</p><p>
The Strand Theatre (Strand) [Strand]. This house was opened
in 1820 as “‘Reinagle’s and Barker’s New Panorama near the
New Church in the Strand,’’ which later became “ Burford’s
Panorama.” Rebuilt in 1831, the house was opened on Thursday,
Jan. 26, 1832, as The New Strand Subscription Theatre. A varied
career followed. At first extraordinary devices were used to evade
the letter of the law, but in 1835 a partial licence was secured,
and on April 25, 1836, the playhouse was formally opened under
the direction of W. J. Hammond and Douglas Jerrold. William
Farren the Younger, who assumed management in 1848, brought
it to a state of unprecedented popularity, and it had later glories
(after 1858) with burlesque. Even in 1840 it was praised for
“its tiny spectacles...humorous burlesques...and_ spirited
actors*.” The theatre was eventually destroyed to make way for
Aldwych Underground Station.
</p><p>
The Surrey Theatre (Blackfriars Road) [Surrey]. Under this



<!--</p><p>
! See A History of English Drama, iii. 230.
® Tomlins, op. cit. p. 63.-->
<pb n='233'/>
</p><p>
title The Royal Circus was opened under Elliston’s management
on Monday, April 23, 1810. On July 4, 1814, it reverted to its
original name, but became The Surrey once more on Monday,
July 5, 1819. T. J. Dibdin and R. W. Elliston were its two most
famous early managers. In 1827 the latter reassumed control and
under his direction the theatre became exceedingly popular.
Melodramas of many kinds were exhibited here; comedy and
farce under Jerrold were ably interpreted by T. P. Cooke; and
sporadic attempts were made in the “legitimate” way. Altogether
The Surrey was one of the most important of the minors. It was
burned down in 1865, to be rebuilt a few years later.
</p><p>
The Theatre of Variety (Catherine-street, Strand). I find this
house exhibiting a few shows in October 1823. It was this house
which in 1829 was named The Minor Theatre.
</p><p>
Tottenham-street Theatre (Fitzroy-square, Tottenham-court-
road) [Tottenham]. Under this name, the Royal West London was
presenting plays in the spring of 1830.
</p><p>
Vauxhall Gardens (Vauxhall) [Vauxhall]. The first records of
plays produced here seem to occur in 1826, when Moncrieff
became manager. Thereafter a few vaudevilles and operettas were
originally produced at the Gardens.
</p><p>
The Westminster Subscription Theatre (Tothill-street, S.W.).
Under T. W. Davenport, who had been stage-manager at The
Strand, this theatre was opened on Thursday, May 17, 1832, and
remained open until 1835.
</p><p>
It must be noted that, in addition to these playhouses and places
of entertainment, there were a number of private theatres and of
saloons where dramatic pieces were occasionally performed.
</p></div>
 <div><head>II. The Provinces</head>
<p>
Aberdeen. In 1745 and 1751 there are records of outside players
performing in a wooden booth somewhere without the city walls.
In 1768 there was a New Inn Theatre in Castle-street, in 1779
another in Shoe-lane, and about 1780 another in Queen-street.
The first permanent playhouse, however, was the old Marischal-
street Theatre Royal, opened in 1795 under the management of
Stephen Kemble. It held £65. Its history is traced by J. Keith
Angus in A Scotch Playhouse (1875). Aberdeen had a stock
company and was also the chief town of a Northern circuit.
</p><p>
Andover. The theatre at Andover, in the Thornton circuit,
seems to have been opened early in 1803.
</p><p>
Arbroath. This was in the Ryder circuit, which embraced
 
<pb n='234'/>

Aberdeen, Glasgow, Edinburgh, and Dundee. A New Theatre was
built in 1793 and the Trades Hall was used for plays from 1812.
Aylsham. This town had a “‘theatre”’ in 1757, and performances
were given there in the nineteenth century.
<p>
Bath. A booth of some kind existed at Bath in the early years
of the eighteenth century. In 1747 Hippisley started a permanent
troupe, but in 1750 a certain John Palmer raised subscriptions for,
and erected, a new theatre in Orchard-street. This house for long
maintained a theatrical monopoly, although a rival theatre existed
in 1753-4; and on its reconstruction in 1767 a special patent valid
for 21 years was issued to Palmer’s son. This was dated Nov. 26,
1767, and was operative from March 25, 1768. This Theatre
Royal had a distinguished history in theatrical annals. It was
closed in 1805 to give place for the Beaufort-square Theatre.
This held £300. In 1834 Macready undertook its management,
and from 1844 to 1850 Mrs Macready directed its fortunes.
Until about 1817 the Bath playhouse was run in close connection
with that at Bristol. A regular stock-company was maintained,
which was supplemented on occasion by London “‘stars.”
</p><p>
Beccles. A theatre was built here by David Fisher in 1819.
</p><p>
Beverley. A Walkergate Theatre was used in the late eighteenth
century by Tate Wilkinson. Its place was taken by The Playhouse,
opened in 1804. A Victoria Pavilion was erected about 1842.
</p><p>
Birmingham. There are records of several theatres in Birming-
ham in the early eighteenth century, but the first of real importance
was the King-street Theatre opened in 1751-2. This, after a series
of remodellings, was closed in 1780. In 1774-5 another and larger
theatre in New-street was opened. Burned in 1792, it was rebuilt
in 1795. This held £268. W. C. Macready managed it for a
decade during the nineteenth century. A patent for a Theatre
Royal was obtained in 1807. This house was burned in 1820 and
rebuilt the same year.
</p><p>
Bridlington. A theatre, still standing, was opened here about
1803.
</p><p>
Brighton. In 1774 Brighton had a North-street Theatre which
gave way in 1790 to the Duke-street Theatre, a small house,
holding £100. This existed till in 1807 a New-road Theatre was
opened.
</p><p>
Bristol. Bristol had booths in the early eighteenth century, and
John Hippisley fitted out a regular Facob’s Well Theatre in 1729.
The King-street Theatre was opened in 1766 and a Royal licence
was secured in 1778. Until 1817 Bristol co-operated with Bath.
</p><p>
Bungay. A theatre was built here in 1827 by David Fisher, but
a New Theatre had been in existence since 1773.
<pb n='235'/>
Cheltenham. A theatre was in existence here in the early eight-
eenth century; see T. Hannam-Clark, Drama in Gloucestershire
(1928).</p><p>
Chichester. A theatre was built at Chichester in 1792; it held
only £50.</p><p>
Cirencester, A theatre was built at Cirencester in 1794; see
T. Hannam-Clark, op. cit. pp. 129-32.
</p><p>
Dereham. David Fisher built a theatre at Dereham in 1816,
but the Norwich players had visited the town as early as 1758.
</p><p>
Doncaster. Doncaster, in the York circuit, had a theatre which
was opened in 1776.
</p><p>
Dundee. In the Aberdeen circuit, Dundee had a booth or
theatre from the second half of the eighteenth century, The Town
Hall was used for performances from 1755 to 1767. A Yeoman
Shore theatre was opened in 1800, a Theatre Royal in 1810, and
a Thistle Hall theatre in 1840. See R. Lawson, The Story of the
Scots Stage (1917).
</p><p>
Edinburgh. Booths existed in Edinburgh at an early date, and
one in Carrubber’s Close was fitted out by Allan Ramsay in 1736
as a permanent theatre. A New Concert Hall in the Cannongate
about a decade later was used for dramatic entertainments. This
in 1767 became a Theatre Royal. It held £70. A new Theatre
Royal in Prince’s-street holding £140 was opened in the winter of
1769. In 1809 a patent was secured by Henry Siddons who
opened a New Theatre Royal in a house which had been used in
1790 as The Amphitheatre, or Edinburgh Equestrian Circus. In
1811 the company moved back to Prince’s-street, and the ‘‘New
Theatre Royal” became, first, Corri’s Pantheon, and, later, The
Caledonian Theatre and The Adelphi. The Edinburgh theatre had
a notable series of managers and important stock-companies.
At the Theatre Royal some of the finest London actors made their
appearance. See J. C. Dibdin, The Edinburgh Stage (1888).
</p><p>
Exeter. In the Plymouth circuit, Exeter had an “old” theatre
erected in 1749. The New Theatre opened in 1787 held £100. It is
interesting to note that between 1811 and 1813 Edmund Kean,
then unrecognised, appeared on its boards. The management
seems to have been a progressive one, for as early as 1817 gas was
introduced. A new theatre was opened in 1821 to take the place
of the 1787 structure, which had been burned the year previous.
This in turn was destroyed in 1885.
</p><p>
Eye. David Fisher built a theatre here in 1815.
</p><p>
Fakenham. A playhouse at Fakenham was in use during the
nineties of the eighteenth century.</p><p>
Glasgow. In 1764 a playhouse was erected, outside the borough,
<pb n='236'/>
at the junction of Hope-street and Argyle-street. In 1782 a new
house in Dunlop-street, known as The Caledonian, was opened.
It held £90. A Queen-street Theatre holding £260 appeared in
1805, and this was followed by The York-street Theatre (opened
October 1829), The Adelphi (opened December 1842), The City
(opened May 1845), The Prince’s (opened January 1849), and
The Queen’s (opened October 1849). The Glasgow theatres had
important managers and some brilliant stock-companies. See
W. Baynham, The Glasgow Stage (1892).
</p><p>
Gloucester. A Barton-street Theatre was opened in 1763; the
New Theatre was opened in 1791.
</p><p>
Grantham. A theatre had been established here as early as
the fifties of the eighteenth century; it formed part of the Lincoln
circuit.
</p><p>
Halesworth, A theatre was built here by David Fisher in 1809.
</p><p>
Holt, In 1791 the White Lion Inn was used for dramatic
performances and touring actors performed there in the early
years of the nineteenth century.
</p><p>
Hull. Hull belonged to the York circuit. The Lowgate Theatre
was being used in 1768. The following year a Theatre Royal was
opened in Finkle-street. This was supplanted by a new Theatre
Royal in Humber-street, opened in 1810 and burned in 1859.
Another house, first a circus (1820), then called the Sans Pareil
(1825), the Minor (1826), the Summer (1827) and the Clarence
(1831), was eventually pulled down in 1836. A third playhouse,
the Adelphi, was opened in 1827, while the Royal Amphitheatre
(1846) and the Queen’s (1847) added a further element of com-
petition.
</p><p>
King’s Lynn. St George’s Hall was used for performances till
a Theatre Royal was erected in 1815. This is still standing.
</p><p>
Leeds. Also in the York circuit, Leeds had a theatre by 1771.
</p><p>
Leicester. In 1750 the first permanent theatre was built at
Leicester. A New Theatre was opened in 1800 and was closed in
1836.
</p><p>
Lewes, Lewes possessed a booth theatre in the nineteenth
century.
</p><p>
Liverpool. Beyond a series of booths Liverpool does not seem
to have had a regular theatre till on June 5, 1772, a patented house
was opened in Williamson-square. In 1821 The Royal Court
Theatre, then known as The Royal Amphitheatre, was opened.
</p><p>
Lowestoft. A theatre built here by David Fisher in 1827.
</p><p>
Maidstone. The first records of performances at Maidstone
seem to be those connected with the performances of a summer
company in 1757 led by Wignell. For a time the rude theatre

<pb n='237'/>

there was run by a Mrs Baker. The New Theatre, which held £60,
in the High-street was opened on April 12, 1798.
</p><p>
Manchester. Various booths existed in Manchester in the early
eighteenth century. In 1775 was opened a Theatre Royal in
Spring-gardens. This was burned in 1789 and a new building
erected on the same site in 1790. A New Theatre Royal in
Fountain-street was opened in 1807; this was also burned in 1844,
and another Theatre Royal in Peter-street was opened in 1845.
Macready’s father was manager from 1807 to 1809. An Amphi-
theatre was opened in 1793. Manchester formed part of the Derby
</p><p>
circuit. See W. T. Baker, The Manchester Stage (1903).
Margate. Margate was part of a Kent circuit which apparently
</p><p>
was established by William Smith in 1762. At this time the
performances took place in a converted barn. Charles Mate, who
took over the circuit in 1779, succeeded in gaining a patent,
and a Theatre Royal, holding £80, was opened on June 27, 1787.
In the nineteenth century, Margate ceased to be part of a regular
circuit and the theatre was open in the summer months only.
</p><p>
Newbury. A New Theatre was opened here in November 1802.
</p><p>
Newcastle. This formed part of a regular Newcastle circuit.
A Theatre Royal was opened in 1789 and a New Theatre Royal
in 1837.
</p><p>
North Walsham. A theatre was built here by David Fisher in
1828.</p><p>
Norwich. This was one of the chief towns in a Norwich circuit.
</p><p>
Plays were presented here in the early eighteenth century at the
White Swan Inn. In 1758 Thomas Ivory opened The New
Theatre, near Chapel Field, and a formal licence was granted in
1768. This house was enlarged in 1801. The later Theatre Royal
(the house standing today) was opened in 1826. For this and other
theatres in the circuit see T. L. G. Burley, Playhouses and Plays
in East Anglia (1928).
</p><p>
Perth, This town was in Corbett Ryder’s circuit. The Glovers’
Hall was used for plays in 1786. A New Theatre, in the disused
Grammar School, was opened in 1810 and closed in 1819. A
Theatre Royal was opened in August 1820.
</p><p>
Plymouth. An early eighteenth century house, which held £75,
was rebuilt in 1804. This formed part of a Plymouth circuit.
</p><p>
Portsmouth. Little seems to be known of the earlier history
of the Portsmouth theatre; it formed part of the Winchester
circuit.
</p><p>
Reading. In 1788 a theatre in Friar-street, holding £40, was
erected by Thornton.</p><p>
Richmond. A theatre which was regarded as “‘a model for
<pb n='238'/>
theatrical architects’’ was in existence here in the early nineteenth
century. The town was regularly served during the summer
months by the London performers.
</p><p>
Sheffield. Early performances were given in the yard of the
Angel Inn; a permanent theatre was built in 1762. For a
number of years Tate Wilkinson was manager and included the
town in various circuits.
</p><p>
Southampton. A New Theatre in French-street, holding £100,
</p><p>
was opened in 1803.
</p><p>
Stroud. On the theatres at Stroud and Tewkesbury see T.
Hannam-Clark, op. cit. pp. 132-7.
</p><p>
Sudbury. A theatre was built here by David Fisher in 1814.
</p><p>
Swaffham. A theatre was built here by David Fisher in 1822.
</p><p>
Tunbridge Wells. ‘Tunbridge Wells belonged to the West Kent
circuit. Various early performances are chronicled for the period
1700-1800; in 1770 Mrs Baker built there a regular playhouse. A
new building was opened on July 8, 1802.
</p><p>
Wakefield. In the York circuit, Wakefield had a theatre from
the seventies of the eighteenth century.
</p><p>
Wells. A theatre was built here by David Fisher in 1812.
</p><p>
Winchester. A theatre is recorded at Winchester as early as
1760, although the first regular playhouse was not erected till
1785. This held £60.
</p><p>
Windsor. The Windsor theatre, erected in 1793, was a summer
house only and depended largely on royal residence at the Castle.
It held £70.
</p><p>
Woodbridge. A theatre was built here by David Fisher in 1814.
</p><p>
Yarmouth. Various makeshift theatres were used here in the
early eighteenth century. The present Theatre Royal, opened in
1778, is one of the oldest theatres in England.
</p><p>
York. The chief town in an important circuit, York had a royal
patent dating from 1759.
</p></p></div><div>
<head>III. The Old Circuits</head>
<p>
Aberdeen. The Northern circuit included, in addition to
Aberdeen, the towns of Perth, Montrose and Dundee.
</p><p>
Bath and Bristol. This hardly formed a regular circuit, but
until 1817 the theatrical activities of the two towns were closely
associated.
</p><p>
Exeter. Plymouth, Weymouth and Exeter for long years were
connected by a regular circuit.
</p><p>
Kent. The Kent circuit originally included the following towns:
Margate, Canterbury, Dover, Deal, Maidstone, Faversham and
<pb n='239'/>
Rochester, Later there was a division made between the East and
West Kent circuits.
</p><p>
Manchester. The Manchester circuit included, with Manchester
itself, Shrewsbury, Chester, Lichfield and (usually) Buxton.
</p><p>
Newcastle. The earlier circuit included Newcastle, Lancaster,
Chester, Whitehaven and Preston. Later the towns visited were
Newcastle, Scarborough, Durham, Sunderland, South and North
Shields, Stockton, Darlington and Coventry.
</p><p>
Norfolk and Suffolk. Organised by the Fishers; included
Halesworth, Wells, Woodbridge, Sudbury, Eye, Dereham,
Beccles, Swaffham, Lowestoft, Bungay, North Walsham, Thetford
and Newmarket.
</p><p>
Norwich. The order of the Norwich circuit was usually Yar-
mouth, Ipswich, Norwich, Yarmouth, Bury, Colchester, Ipswich,
Norwich, Lynn, Norwich and so back to Yarmouth [see also
under Norwich, p. 232].
</p><p>
Winchester. This circuit included Portsmouth, Winchester,
Southampton, Chichester and Newport.
</p><p>
York. One of the chief circuits, and that with which Tate
Wilkinson in the eighteenth century, and J. P. Kemble in the
nineteenth, were associated, included, besides the city of York,
Hull, Wakefield, Leeds, Pontefract and Doncaster. [See Thomas
Sheppard, Evolution of the Drama in Hull and District (1917).]
</p><p>
A few notes are added here on some of the London playhouses,
but most of the additional material concerns the provincial theatres.
I have found particularly useful An Alphabetical List of Theatres
in the United Kingdom, with the Names of Managers, compiled by
John Miller for the Dramatic Authors’ Society in 1833. The only
copy of this list I have been able to locate is in Birmingham
University Library: since it was intended merely as a notebook,
with columns headed ‘‘When heard from,” ‘When Paid” and
“Remarks,”’ presumably not many exemplars are likely to have
been preserved. Its value rests in the facts that it gives a complete
register of theatres operative in 1833 and that its naming of managers
shows well the working of the circuit system at that time. Re-
ferences to the list are given under the date “1833’’: theatres added
to those recorded in the text are marked by an asterisk.
</p><p>
p. 221] “London Bridge. This is recorded, under the management of
Bedford, in 1833.
Lyceum. The house was altered in 1816, and the new structure
of 1834 was refashioned by Bradwell in 1847.
p. 225] Royal Clarence. See M. St Clare Byrne, “Supplement to the
<pb n='240'/>
<!--</p><p>
p. 226]
p. 228]
</p><p>
p. 229]
</p><p>
Pp. 230]
</p><p>
THE THEATRES, 1800-1850
</p><p>-->
Playbill” (Times Literary Supplement, 29/6/1933) and Allan
Wade, “ Royal Clarence Theatre” (id. 6/7/1933).
</p><p>
Royal Panharmonion. See under Royal Clarence, above.
</p><p>
*Vaudeville (Leicester-square). This is recorded, under the
management of W. Chaplin, as a theatre in 1833.
</p><p>
Westminster. See article by M. St Clare Byrne, cited above under
Royal Clarence.
</p><p>
Aberdeen. Manager, F. Ryder: 1833.
</p><p>
* Abergavenny. Managers, Potter and McRoy: 1833.
</p><p>
*Aberystwyth. Manager, J. Potter: 1833.
</p><p>
* Abingdon. Manager, Bullen: 1833.
</p><p>
* Alcester. 1833.
</p><p>
*Alnwick, 1833.
</p><p>
* Andover. 1833.
</p><p>
*Arundel. Manager, Davenport: 1833.
</p><p>
* Ashborne. Manager, G. Stanton: 1833.
</p><p>
* Ashby de la Zouch. Manager, J. Bennett: 1833.
</p><p>
* Atherstine. Manager, M. H. Simpson: 1833.
</p><p>
* Aylesbury. Manager, H. Jackman: 1833.
</p><p>
* Bakewell. Manager, Thornhill: 1833.
</p><p>
*Banbury. Manager, H. Jackman: 1833.
</p><p>
*Barnsley. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
</p><p>
*Barnstaple. Manager, H. Lee: 1833.
</p><p>
*Barton. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
</p><p>
Bath. See Theatre Notebook, (1945), i. 4; and F. T. Woods,
“Theatrical Performances at Bath in the Eighteenth Century”
(N.Q. cxcii. Nov. 1, 1947, pp. 477-8; Nov. 15, pp. 486-90;
Dec. 13, pp. 539-41; Dec. 27, pp. 552-8; cxciii. Jan. 24,
pp. 38-40; March 6, pp. 92-3; June 12, pp. 253-5). In 1833
the manager was E. Barnett.
</p><p>
Beccles. Manager, C. Fisher: 1833.
</p><p>
*Bedford. Manager, H. Jackman: 1833.
</p><p>
Beverley. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
</p><p>
Birmingham. See Percival Hinton, “The Dramatic Library of
the Old Theatre Royal, Birmingham” (Theatre Notebook,
1946, i, 12~13).
</p><p>
*Bishop’s Castle. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
</p><p>
“Blandford. Manager, W. Shalders: 1833.
</p><p>
*Bodmin. Manager, Dawson: 1833.
</p><p>
*Bolton. 1833.
</p><p>
*Boston. Manager, W. Robertson: 1833.
</p><p>
*Bridgenorth. Manager, G. Stanton: 1833.
</p><p>
* Bridgewater. Manager, H. Lee: 1833.
</p><p>
*Bridport. 1833.
</p><p>
*Brigg. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
</p><p>
Brighton, Managers, Vining and Bow: 1833.
</p><p>
Bristol. See Rennie Powell, The Bristol Stage (1919) and G. T.
Watts, Theatrical Bristol (1915).
</p><p>
*Buckingham. Manager, H. Jackman: 1833.
</p><p>
Bungay. Manager, C. Fisher: 1833.
</p><p>
*Burlington Quay. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
</p><p>
*Burton-on-Trent. Manager, G. Stanton: 1833.
</p><p>
*Bury St Edmunds. Manager, J. Smith: 1833.
</p><p>

</p>
 <pb n="241"/>
 <p>
 *Buxton. 1833.
</p><p>
 *Cambridge. Manager, J. Smith: 1833. The Barnwell, Cam-
 bridge, theatre existed in 1745 and was rebuilt in 1816. After
 being used for a mission-hall from 1878, it was refashioned
 in the present century as the Festival Theatre.
</p><p>
 *Canterbury. Manager, J. Dowton: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Cardiff. Manager, H. Collier: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Cardigan. Manager, H. Collier: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Carlisle. Manager, J. H. Alexander: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Carmarthen. Manager, J. Potter: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Chelmsford. Manager, W. Harvey: 1833.
</p><p>
 Cheltenham. Manager, W. A. Spencer: 1823.
</p><p>
 *Chester. Manager, T. Lewis: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Colchester. Manager, J. Smith: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Croydon. Manager, E. Barnett: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Deal. Manager, J. F. Saville: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Derby, Manager, T. W. Manley: 1833.
</p><p>
 Dereham. Manager, J. Coppin: 1833. The Theatre, rebuilt in
 1935, was abandoned in 1938.
</p><p>
 *Devonport. Manager, Mrs Bennett: 1833.
</p><p>
 Doncaster. Manager, W. J. Hammond: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Dover. Manager, J. Sloman: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Downham. Manager, C. Fisher: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Drayton. 1833.
</p><p>
 *Dudley. 1833.
</p><p>
 *Dumfries. Manager, W. Copeland: 1833.
</p><p>
 Dundee. Manager, T. Ryder: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Durham. Manager, H. Beverley: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Eastbourne. Manager, J. Robberds: 1833.
</p><p>
 Exeter. Manager, Mrs Bennett: 1833.
</p><p>
 Eye. Manager, C. Fisher: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Falmouth. Manager, J. Dawson: 1833.
</p><p>
 Faversham. 1833.
</p><p>
 *Folkestone. 1833.
</p><p>
 *Gainsborough. Managers, Huggins and Clarke: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Gosport. Managers, Irish and Wilson: 1833.
</p><p>
 Grantham. Manager, Mrs T. Robertson: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Gravesend, 1833.
</p><p>
 *Greenwich. Manager, J. F. Saville: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Grimsby. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Guernsey. Manager, Mrs Bennett: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Guildford, Manager, E. Barnett: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Haleston. Manager, J. Dawson: 1833.
</p><p>
 Halesworth. Manager, J. Coppin: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Halifax. Manager, T. W. Manley: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Harrogate. Manager, J. E. Parry: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Hastings. Managers, C. Waldegrave and Co.: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Hemel Hempstead. Manager, Bullen: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Hereford. Manager, J. Watson: 1833.
</p><p>
 Holt. Manager, J. Coppin: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Horncastle. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Horsham. Manager, T. Rogers: 1833.
</p><p>
 *Howden. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
 <pb n="243"/> 
  built in 1800 and closed about 1832-3 (Theatre Notebook
  1946, i. 17).
  </p><p>
   *Northampton. Manager, J. Scott: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *North Shields. Manager, H. Beverley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   North Walsham. 1833.
  </p><p>
   Norwich, Manager, J. Smith: 1833.
  </p><p>
   * Nottingham. Manager, T. W. Manley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Oswestry. Manager, G. Stanton: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Oundle. Manager, W. Robertson: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Oxford. Manager, E. Barnett: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Penryn, Manager, J. Dawson: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Penzance. Manager, J. Dawson: 1833.
  </p><p>
   Perth. Manager, T. Ryder: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Peterborough. Manager, Mrs T. Robertson: 1833.
  </p><p>
   Plymouth. Manager, G. Sandford: 1833. See R. Southern, The
   Georgian Playhouse (1948), pp. 56~9.
  </p><p>
   *Pontefract. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   Portsmouth. Managers, S. Maxfield and H. Kelly: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Preston. Manager, W. Burroughs: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Ramsgate. Manager, J. F. Saville: 1833.
  </p><p>
   Reading. Manager, E. Barnett: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Retford. Manager, T. W. Manley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   Richmond (Surrey). Manager, T. W. Jones: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Richmond (Yorks). Manager, J. E. Parry: 1833. On this theatre
   see Theatre Notebook (1948), i. 3.
  </p><p>
   *Rochdale. 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Rochester. Manager, J. Sloman: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Rotherham. 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Ryde. Manager, E. Barnett: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Rye. 1833.
  </p><p>
   *St Albans. Manager, J. F. Saville: 1833.
  </p><p>
   * Salisbury. Manager, W. Shalders: 1833.
  </p><p>
   * Sandwich. Manager, J. F. Saville: 1833.
  </p><p>
   * Scarborough, Manager, H. Beverley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   Sheffield. Manager, W. J. Hammond: 1833.
  </p><p>
   * Shrewsbury. Manager, J. Bennett: 1833.
  </p><p>
   * Sleaford. Manager, Smedley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   Southampton. Managers, S. Maxfield and J. Kelly: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *South Shields. Manager, H. Beverley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Southwell, Manager, Smedley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Spalding. Manager, T. W. Robertson: 1833.
  </p><p>
   * Stafford. Manager, G. Stanton: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Stamford. Manager, 'T. W. Manley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   * Stockdale. 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Stockton-on-Tees. Manager, H. Beverley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Stourbridge. Manager, J. Bennett: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Stratford-upon-Avon. Manager, Raymond: 1833.
  </p><p>
   Sudbury. Manager, C. Fisher: 1833.
  </p><p>
   * Sunderland. Manager, H. Beverley: 1833.
  </p><p>
   Swaffham. Manager, C. Fisher: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Swansea. Manager, J. Woulds: 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Tamworth. 1833.
  </p><p>
   *Taunton. Manager, H. Lee: 1833.</p>
 </div></div>
