<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Biographical Memoranda of Living Dramatic Authors</title>
    <author>Edward Ledger</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>1868, 1869</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Curated by Lou Burnard for the Digital Lacy site</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>OCRd from the Internet Archive copy of <title>The Era Almanac</title> for 1868 and 1869.</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <listChange>
    <change when="2024-11-16T14:50:57Z">First TEI version</change>
   </listChange>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <figure><graphic url="media/eraAlmCover.png"/></figure>
   <pb n="17"/><div xml:id="LDA100">
   <head>BIOGRAPHICAL MEMORANDA OF LIVING DRAMATIC AUTHORS</head><listPerson>
   <person xml:id="LDA101">
    <p>ADDISON, H. R. — passed a considerable portion of his early life in India, of which country
     he has published some interesting reminiscences. Colonel Addison began writing for the stage in
     1830, when he supplied Mrs. Waylett with a number of light pieces, that attained at the time
     considerable popularity. In 1834 he wrote <title>Tam o' Shanter</title> and <title>The King's
     Seal,</title> produced with marked success at Drury Lane, and the drama of <title>Lo Zingaro,
     </title>brought out at the Adelphi. Of late years Colonel Addison has devoted himself more
     assiduously to other forms of literature, and during the time of the French Exhibition of 1867
     he was retained as special correspondent of one of the most influential London newspapers, for
     which responsible post his intimate knowledge of Parisian life, and his fluent style of
     writing, endowed him with peculiar advantages. Colonel Addison has written about sixty pieces
     for the London theatres, many of them <foreign>apropos</foreign> farces, most successfully
     illustrating the popular topic of the time.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA102">
    <p>BERNARD, WILLIAM BAYLE — son of an eminent English comedian and manager, was born in
     Pleasant-street, Boston, U.S., next door to the old house of Dr. Franklin, on tho 27th of
     November, 1809, during his father’s management of the Boston Theatre, and when he was on the
     eve of opening that of Albany and of Quebec and Montreal. Mr. Bayle Bernard came to England
     with his family in 1820, and finished his education at what was then called a “Latin Grammar
     Academy” at Uxbridge, an old proprietary school, kept by a Dissenting minister, Dr. Beaseley.
     He went to Boulogne with his family in 1823, and there at 16 commenced his literary labours as
     amanuensis to Charles Barthelemy, the son of the author of “The Travels of Anacharsis," who
     wrote a history of Boulogne in French, which the young assistant translated into English. In
     1826 he obtained a clerkship in the “Army Accounts Office,” through the interest of Mr.
     Canning, whose mother had been his father’s leading tragedienne at Plymouth, an office that
     unluckily was soon after abolished by the Duke of Wellington. In 1827 he produced his first
     drama, which was at the old Olympic Theatre, when under tho management of Mr. Scott, the first
     manager of the Adelphi. This was a nautical piece, after the fashion of <title>The
     Pilot,</title> and entitled, <title>Casco Bag,</title> for which he was paid the sum of
     <emph>three pounds,</emph> and on the 100th night of its run (it reached 140) he received two
     pounds more, to prompt him to further exertions. In 1828 he produced his first novel, “The
     Freebooter’s Bride,” in five volumes, one of the thousand publications of the old “Minerva
     Press,” which prolonged the school of Mrs. Radcliffe till it slowly died out at the hands of
     Ann of Swansea, Francis Lathom, and others. In 1829 he wrote from memoranda which had been left
     by his father his “Retrospections of the Stage," and joined the metropolitan press, writing for
     tho “Morning Post” and other papers on social and literary topics.</p>
    <p>In 1830 he commenced his toils as a professed dramatist, under the theatrical triumvirate of
     Lee, Melrose, and Chapman, at the Tottenham-street Theatre, producing a drama called <title>The
     Metempsychosis,</title> and a number of farces. In 1831 he wrote for the Strand Theatre, on its
     opening under Lee and Rayner, <title>The Four Sisters,</title> and other pieces for Mrs.
     Waylett. In 1832 he wrote, for Madame Vestris at the Olympic, <title>The Dumb Belle,
     </title> and other pieces, and also furnished the drama of <title>Rip van Winkle</title> to the
     Adelphi. In 1833 Mr. Bayle Bernard wrote several American dramas for Mr, Hackett, the chief of
     which were—<title>The Kentuckian,</title> produced that year at Covent Garden, and a new
     version of <title>Rip van Winkle,</title> which was acted at the Haymarket; together with
     <title>The Mummy,</title> for the English Opera House, and <title>The Nervous Man,</title> for
     Drury Lane. In 1836 he produced <title>Lucille</title> at the Lyceum, which was followed by
     <title>The Parmer's Story, the Middy Ashore,</title> and <title>The Man about Town;</title> and
     the same year he wrote some American farces for Mr. Hill, the comedian, the chief of which was
     <title>The Yankee Pedlar,</title> which was brought out at Drury Lane. In 1837 he furnished
     Madame Celeste with <title>St. Mary's Eve, </title>which was produced at the Adelphi, and was
     followed by <title>Marie Ducange,</title> played at the Haymarket; and in 1839 he wrote for Mr.
     Power <title>His Last Legs</title> and <title>The Irish Attorney,</title> which were acted at
     the same theatre. In 1841 <title>The Boarding School,</title> and in 1846 <title>The Bound of
     Wrong,</title> were performed at the Haymarket; in 1845 the drama of <title>Blanche de
     Valmy,</title> at the Princess's Theatre; and in 1848 the play of <title>The Passing
     Cloud,</title> at Drury Lane. In 1854 and 1856 he wrote for the Haymarket <title>The Balance oj
     Comfort</title> and the comedy of <title>The Evil Genius,</title> followed by that of
     <title>The Tide of Titne,</title> and the drama of <title>A Life's Trial.</title> In 1857 Mr.
     Bernard became the theatrical critic of the “Weekly Dispatch,” and after an eight years’
     cessation from his dramatic labours he returned to them in 1866, furnishing the adaptation of
     <title>Faust</title> to Drury Lane. He has written besides a couple of novels, a mass of
     magazine matter, and contributions of all kinds to the metropolitan prees ; whilst in respect
     to his dramas, many of which were written for America, and not half of them published, we may
     mention that his last production, <title>The Doge of Fenice,</title> forms the 114th!</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA103">
    <p>BLANCHARD, EDWARD L. — born in London, December 11th, 1820, is the son of William Blanchard,
     the comedian, who for thirty-five years was a distinguished member of Covent Garden Theatre,
     under the managemeut of the Kembles and their successors. On the decease of his father, in
     1835, Mr. E. L. Blanchard became associated with literary pursuits, and from that time he has
     been an industrious contributor to newspapers and periodicals. In his seventeenth year he began
     writing for the stage, and some thirty dramas and farces produced before he was twenty, attest
     at least the fertility of a youthful imagination. In 1841 he was retained as the stock
     dramatist of the Olympic Theatre, where, among many other pieces, the farces of <title>Angels
     and Lucifers, The Artful Dodge, Pork Chops,</title> and the drama of <title>The Road of
     Life,</title> were peculiarly successful. Newspaper engagements appear to have soon after
     diverted the exercise of his pen in another direction, but besides supplying Mr. W. S. Woodin
     with “The Carpet Bag,” and a series of similar protean entertainments, and furnishing Miss Emma
     Stanley with her popular “Seven Ages of Woman,” Mr. E. L. Blanchard has contrived to illustrate
     the whole range of fairy mythology in a series of Christmas extravaganzas, which number nearly
     one hundred. As a somewhat remarkable circumstance in the career of a dramatic author, it may
     be recorded that he never adapted a piece from the French, and never dramatised a novel. A
     succession of pantomimes produced under the pseudonym of <title>Francisco Frost</title> gave
     him in early life a reputation for these eccentricities of authorship, and for the last
     seventeen years Mr. E. L. Blanchard has publicly identified his name with the Drury lane comic
     annuals.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA104">
    <p>BOUCICAULT, Dion — was born in Dublin, December 26th, 1820, and was educated under the care
     of his guardian, Dr. Lardner, and at the London University. After some slighter experiments in
     dramatic literature ho established his name by the production of <title>London
     Assurance</title> at Covent Garden Theatre, March 4th, 1841, and this notable success was
     speedily followed by the comedies and dramas of <title>The Irish Heiress, Alma Mater, Old Heads
     and Young Hearts, Lone in a Mase, Used Up, The Willow Copse, Janet Pride, Louis the Eleventh,
     The Corsican Brothers, The Vampire,</title> and <title>Faust and Marguerite,</title> furnished
     to the Haymarket, the Adelphi, and the Princess’s Theatres. In January, 1853, Mr. Boucicault
     married Miss Agnes Robertson, then an esteemed member of Mr. Charles Kean’s company at the
     Princess’s Theatre, and soon after went to America, appearing with his clever wife at Burton’s
     Chambers-street Theatre. At the opening of the Winter Garden Theatre, New York, for the season
     of 1859—1860, Mr. Boucicault was engaged as dramatist to the establishment. On the 18th of
     July, 1860, Mr. and Mrs. Boucicault returned to England and appeared at the Adelphi Theatre
     (September 10th) in <title>The Colleen Bawn,</title> which achieved such remarkable popularity.
     <title>The Colleen Baton</title> attained its 231st representation on its first uninterrupted
     run, but it was played for many nights after at the Adelphi, in conjunction with <title>The
     Octoroon.</title> Mr. Boucicault is the author of about 150 dramas, in all of which he has
     displayed considerable literary power, associated with remarkable constructive skill. Among the
     most prominent of Mr. Boucicault's dramas produced since <title>The Colleen Bawn</title> may be
     mentioned <title>The Fox Chase,</title> a five-act comedy (St. James’s, May 11th, 1864) j
     <title>The Streets of London,</title> drama (Princess’s, August 1st, 1864) <title>Omoo ; or.
     The Sea of Ice,</title> drama (Royal Amphitheatre, Liverpool, Oc*. 30th, 1864); <title>Arrah na
     Pogue; or, The Wicklow Wedding,</title> four acts (originally brought out at the Theatre Royal,
     Dublin, and produced at the Princess's, March 22d, 1865); <title>The Long Strike,</title>
     four-act drama (Lyceum, September 15th, 1866); <title>Flying Scud,</title> four-act drama (New
     Holborn Theatre, October 6tb, 1866); and <title>Hunted Down; or, The Two Lives of Mary
     Leigh,</title> three-act drama (St. James’s Theatre, November 5th, 1866).</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA105">
    <p>BROOKS, SHIRLEY.—This brilliant and versatile writer was born April 29th, 1816, and
     originally intended for the law, but preferred literature. During the Keeley management of the
     Lyceum (1844—1847), Mr. Shirley Brooks produced <title>Our New Governess, </title>a clever
     two-act comedy ; <title>Honours and Tricks,</title> a witty and well-constructed comedy in
     three acts; and the drama of <title>The Creole,</title> a piece of strong interest, based on a
     story of slavery in Mauritius. As a journalist, novelist, and most important contributor to “
     Punch,” Mr. Shirley Brooks has apparently had no leisure lately to extend his fame as a
     dramatist, for which his keen perception of character and power of writing humorous dialogue so
     pre-eminently qualify him.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA106">
    <p>BROUGH, WILLIAM — was born in London on the 28th April, 1826. His first appearance as a
     dramatic author was in the early part of the year 1848, when, in conjunction with his late
     brother Robert, he brought out the <title>Enchanted Isle</title> at the Amphitheatre,
     Liverpool, then under the management of Mr. W. R. Copeland, recently deceased. It happened that
     Mr. Benjamin Webster, manager of the Adelphi Theatre, London, visited Liverpool at the time,
     and saw the <title>Enchanted Isle</title> there. He at once entered into negotiations for its
     reproduction upon the Adelphi boards, where it was brought out November 20,1848. The great
     success of this, their first attempt, at once established the “Brothers Brough ” as comic
     dramatists in London, and for some years they wrote the Christmas and Easter pieces not only
     for the Adelphi but likewise for the Haymarket, that theatre being at the time also under Mr.
     Webster’s management, The "Brothers," however, dissolved their literary partnership, and we
     find the subject of our memoir first appearing single-handed as an author of original fairy
     extravaganza on the stage of the Lyceum (under Madame Vestris's management) at Christmas, 1854.
     We need not follow Mr. William Brough step by step, nor indeed would our space permit our
     giving here a list of his productions were we so inclined. Enough to say he has achieved
     dramatic successes upon nearly every important London stage. He also wrote the first of those “
     Entertainments " with which Mr. and Mrs. German Reed have so long charmed the town; and many
     others of the series, since the first, have also been written for Mr. and Mrs. Reed and Mr.
     John Parry from time to time by William Brough. Early in the year 1851, Mr. William Brough
     married Miss Anne Romer, the celebrated English Opera <title>prima donna.</title> The lady,
     however, did not long enjoy her married happiness, but died directly after the birth of her
     first child. Mr. Brough has since married again, his present wife being entirely unconnected
     with the dramatic profession.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA107">
    <p>BROUGHAM, JOHN — born in Dublin, May 9,1814, was educated at the Preparatory Collegiate
     Institute of the Rev. Dean Hamilton, and passed his examination at Trinity College, Dublin. Mr.
     John Brougham was originally intended for the medical profession, but his tastes led him to the
     stage, and he made his first appearance at the Tottenham- street Theatre, London (now the
     Prince of Wales’s), in July, 1830, sustaining the several parts of a countryman, costermonger,
     sweep, gentleman, sailor, and jockey—the whole in one night—in <title>Tom and Jerry.</title>
     When Madame Vestris took the Olympic he became a member of her company, and was the stock
     Irishman of that theatre. In 1840 he became lessee of the Lyceum Theatre, where he first
     appeared as an author, producing a lively mythological extravaganza called <title>Life</title>
     in <title>the Clouds.</title> In 1842 he sailed for America, and made his <title>debut</title>
     at the Park Theatre, New York, as Tun Moore in <title>The Irish Lion.</title> On the 15th of
     October, 1850, he opened the new theatre on Broadway called Brougham’8 Lyceum (afterwards “
     Wallack's Theatre ”), and then took a lease of the Old Bowery for a short time, opening there
     July 7, 1856. In September, 1860, Mr. Brougham returned to England, and appeared at the Lyceum
     under Mr. Fechter's management, which he had already aided by his skilful adaptation of
     <title>The Duke's Motto.</title> His comedy of <title>Playing with Fire</title>. brought out at
     the Princess's, is a favourable example of his powers as a | dramatist. With a thorough
     knowledge of stage effect, his dialogue is distinguished by a vein of rich humour, and
     occasionally by deep pathos. In 1866 Mr. Brougham returned to the United States, where, as in
     this country, ho is personally as well as professionally i held in tlte highest estimation.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA108">
    <p>BUCKSTONE, John Baldwin — born near London in 1802, and having acquired popularity as an
     actor at the Surrey Theatre, turned his attention to dramatic writing at i the Adelphi, where
     he produced in 1828 his interesting drama of <title>Luke the Labourer,</title> and appeared as
     Bobby Trot. From this period Mr. Buckstone furnished to that theatre a I series of highly
     successful pieces, including <title>John-street, Adelphi; The Wreck Ashore </title>I (October
     21, 1830); <title>Victorine; The King of the Alps; The Rake and His Pupil; </title> <title>The
     May Queen; Henrietta the Forsaken; Isabelle, or Womans Life; The Dream at </title>I
     <title>Hea,</title> Ac. In the meantime Mr. Buckstone’s busy pen had supplied the Haymarket
     with 'if <title>A Husband at Sight; John Jones; Uncle John; Second Thoughts; Married
     </title><title>Life; </title><title> Single Life; A Lesson for Ladies; Rural Felicity; Weak
     Points; The Irish Lion</title><title>; </title><title>। Leap Year;</title> An <title>Alarming
     Sacrifice;</title> and <title>Good for Nothing. The Green Rushes </title>'I (January 27,1845)
     and <title>The Flowers of the Forest</title> (March 11,1847) were two dramas ■ that proved
     immensely popular at the Adelphi when under Madame Celeste’s direction. ' Equally popular as
     author, actor, aud manager, no one has more liberally enriched the stage by his talents than
     Mr. J. B. Buckstone, who has written some 150 comedies, dramas, and farces, several of which
     retain a permanent place on the boards.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA109">
    <p>BURNAND, Francis C.—This popular writer was born in 1836, on the 29 th of November. His first
     piece was written when be was a boy at Eton (as Frank Talfourd’s <title>Macbeth</title> was, by
     the way), and was played publicly at the Worthing Theatre, Sussex, about 1851. The next pieces
     he wrote were two farces, <title>Romance under Difficulies,</title> and <title>In for a
     Holiday,</title> and a burlesque called <title>Villikins and his Dinah.</title> The burlesque
     was first played Nov. 8th, 1855, at the little theatre in the University Amateur Dramatic Club,
     which he founded when an undergraduate of Trinity College, Cambridge. This club, it may be
     mentioned, has since become a fixed institution among the University amusements, and numbers
     among its members H.R.H. the Prince of Wales. <title>Villikins and his Dinah</title> was played
     professionally for thirty nights at the Theatre Royal, Manchester. His next piece was
     <title>Lord Lonely</title> played at Cambridge, November, 1856. Then followed. <title>Alonzo
     the Brace; or, Fautt and the Fair Imogene,</title> played first at Cambridge A. D. C. rooms in
     1857, and becoming very popular, was played again in 1859 and 1861. This piece was played also
     with great success by Mr. Nye Chart’s company at the Brighton Theatre, by Mr. Sidney’s
     companies, and by Mr. Sefton Parry’s when he opened the New Theatre at Greenwich. The first
     piece of his produced in London was the burlesque of <title>Dido</title> at the St. James’s
     Theatre, Feb. 11th, 1860, under the management of Mr. Chatterton, when Mr. Charles Young played
     Dido, Clara St. Casse neas, and Miss Wyndham Anna. It ran for sixty nights, and was afterwards
     revived at the New Royalty in 1865. The next piece was a joint production with Mr. Montagu
     Williams, entitled, <title>B. B.,</title> and produced at the Olympic Theatre, March 22d, 1860.
     This was a farce in which the late Mr. Robson played, inimitably, the part of Benjamin Bobbin,
     mistaken for the great <title>M</title> Benicia Boy.” In December, 1861, he produced at the
     Olympic an extravaganza, with Mr. Palgrave Simpson, entitled, <title>The King of the
     Merrowt.</title> Previous to this a farce, entitled <title>Deerfoot,</title> with Mr. Robson in
     the chief character, Dec. 16, 1861. Then followed <title>Fair Rotamond,</title> another
     Robsonian burlesque, by F. C. Burnand, Easter, 1862, Olympic Theatre; <title>Robin
     Hood,</title> Christmas, 1862, Olympic (management—Robson and Emden). There were several pieces
     of his in the interval at different theatres before <title>Ixion,; or, The Man at the
     Wheel,</title> was produced at the New Royalty Theatre, Sept. 28th, 1863, which ran up to the
     following Easter, when <title>RumpletliUtkin s or, The Woman at the Wheel,</title> was produced
     at the same theatre. At Christmas, 1863, was played his comic drama of <title>Madame Berliot't
     Ball.</title> After this may be mentioned <title>The Deal Boatman,</title> a drama in two acts,
     at Drury I sne, Sept. 21st, 1863. <title>Snowdrop,</title> another " New Royalty" success,
     1864. Farces with Mr. Montagu Williams:—<title>Turkish Bath</title> (Adelphi), <title>Katy
     Shaving </title>(Haymarket), <title>Volunteer Ball</title> (Strand), <title>Carte de
     Vitife</title> (St. James), and the drama of <title>The Isle of St. Tropes,</title> in which
     Mr. Alf. Wigan and Miss Herbert played at the St. James’s. Among the most successful have been
     <title>Windsor Cattle, L'Africaine</title> (opera burlesques), (at the Strand), <title>Patient
     Penelope</title> (Strand), <title>Paris</title> (a Strand success, 1866), <title>Helen
     </title>(adaptation of <title>La Belle Helene,</title> with M. Offenbach’s music, Adelphi),
     <title>The Latest Edition of Black-Eyed Susan; or, The Little Bill that was Taken Up,</title>
     first played at the New Royalty under Miss Oliver’s management, November, 1866, and still
     running (without an interruption since the commencement) in December, 1867. Mr. F. C. Burnand
     played the part of Captain Crosstree himself at Liverpool, Manchester, Brighton, Portsmouth,
     Ryde, Nottingham, Greenwich, Ac. A comic operetta, entitled <title>Cox and Box; or, The Long
     Lost Brothers,</title> music by Arthur Sullivan, was played with the greatest succees at the
     Adelphi on the occasion of the “Bennett” benefit in May, 1867. Mr. Burnand is one of the most
     prominent writers on the staff of “Punch.”</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA110">
    <p>BYRON, Henry James — is the son of Henry Byron, Esq., the British Consul at Port au Prince,
     Hayti, and was born at Manchester in January, 1834. To the fertility of Mr. Byron’s pen the
     town is indebted for a long series of those most amusing burlesques which date from the first
     season of Miss Swanborough at the Strand, in 1858. His comedies of <title>War to the
     Knife</title> and <title>A Hundred Thousand Pounds,</title> produced at the Prince of Wales's
     Theatre, 1865 and 1866, show the possession of talents of a far higher order, and his novels
     have attained a wide and deserved popularity. To give a list of Mr. Byron’s burlesques would be
     impossible within reasonable limits, but nearly every theatre in London has profited by their
     production. Since the autumn of 1866 Mr. Byron has undertaken the management of the Theatre
     Royal, and the Amphitheatre, Liverpool, where he produced, in November, 1867, a
     <title>very</title> effective drama of the sensation kind, under the title of <title>The
     Lancashire Lass.</title></p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA111">
    <p>CARPENTER, Joseph Edwards — born in London, November 2,1813, though chiefly known as a
     song-writer and lecturer, has contributed successfully to the stage. In 1854 Mr. J. E.
     Carpenter produced a musical drama in two acts called <title>The Sanctuary,</title> and another
     drama in three acts, entitled <title>Love and Honour,</title> at the Surrey Theatre. In 1862
     Another three-act drama, called <title>Adam Bede,</title> adapted from the novel, was brought
     out at the same establishment. Mr. Carpenter has published upwards of 2,500 songs and duets,
     and his editorship of ten volumes of “Penny Readings in Prose and Verse” will attest the
     excellence of hie literary taste and critical judgment.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA112">
    <p>CHELTNAM, CHARLES Smith — born February 12, 1823.—Mr. C. S. Cheltnam adopted the profession
     of wood-engraving at the age of fifteen, and for many years was largely employed on the “
     Illustrated London News.” During the whole of this period he contributed to various periodicals
     reviews and miscellaneous papers in prose and verse. Encouraged by success in his literary
     pursuits he finally adopted journalism as his vocation in 1857, and in the following year was
     engaged on the “Leader,” writing for a considerable period the weekly political and general
     summary. In 1860 he was appointed general manager of the “Spectator,” and in 1861 became
     general manager and fine art critic of the “Morning Chronicle.” Afterwards was theatrical
     critic of the “Reader " from April, 1863, to the autumn of 1864, when that paper ceased to be
     edited by Professor Masson. Mr. Cheltnam, who has produced eleven dramatic works, is at the
     present time the working editor of “Belgravia."</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA113">
    <p>COYNE, JOSEPH Stirling — born in 1805 at Birr, King’s County, Ireland, is the son of an
     officer in the Irish Commissariat, and, educated for the law, gave early evidence of his
     preference for literature. His first farce, called <title>The Phrenologist,</title> was brought
     out at the Theatre Royal, Dublin, in 1835, and further contributions to the Irish stage
     followed. In 1837 Mr. Stirling Coyne brought out at the Adelphi a capital farce called
     <title>The Queer Subjeet,</title> in which Mr. John Reeve played the principal part, and from
     that time ho settled in England and became rapidly acknowledged as a dramatist of increasing
     repute. The dramatic works of an author who has furnished such a number of pieces supplied to
     all the principal theatres of London, but chiefly the Haymarket and the Adelphi, can only be
     here briefly indicated. Among Mr. Coyne’s most popular comedies may be mentioned
     <title>Presented at Court, The Hope of the Family, The Secret Agent, Man of Many
     Friends,</title> and <title>Black Sheep.</title> His admirable farce, <title>How to Settle
     Accounts with your Laundress, </title>has been translated both into French and German. Mr.
     Stirling Coyne has been for many years a very active contributor to magazines, newspapers, and
     periodicals, and since 1856 has been the Secretary of the Dramatic Authors’ Society, a position
     in which he has shown the very highest qualifications for a most responsible office.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA114">
    <p>CRAVEN, Henry T. —born in London February 26,1821, received when a youth a letter of
     encouragement from Mr. Macready in reference to a submitted tragedy, and the fostered idea of
     uniting the callings of dramatist and actor was realised in 1840 by his obtaining an engagement
     with Mr. Hooper at York. After numerous other provincial removes Mr. Craven appeared as a
     youthful tragedian at Drury Lane (1850), playing Orlando to the Rosalind of Mrs. Nesbitt, Azel,
     &amp;c. The following year he wrote and performed in a very successful operetta produced at the
     Strand called <title>The Village Nightingale,</title> in which the heroine was represented by
     Miss Eliza Nelson, a daughter of the composer. This lady, in May, 1852, became Mrs. Craven, and
     they resolved to try their united fortunes in Australia, where they arrived in October, 1854.
     After a professional visit to New Zealand in 1856, Mr. Craven returned to Sydney and became a
     partner in the Lyceum Theatre, but disposing of his interest in the property he returned, after
     visiting Melbourne and the Gold Fields, to England, where he appeared as a light comedian at
     the St. James’s Theatre in 1859. In 1860 he retired from the stage, but the death of Mr.
     Robson, for whom he had prepared the character of “Milky White,” induced him to accept an
     engagement at the Strand Theatre in 1864 to realize his own conception of the eccentric
     milkman. As an author Mr. H. T. Craven has been distinguished by his originality, his pieces
     being to all intents creations. Amongst the number may be mentioned <title>Our Nelly</title>
     (Surrey, 1853), <title>The Post Boy</title> (Strand, Oct. 31, 1860), <title>The Chimney
     Corner</title> (Olympic, Feb. 21,1861), <title>Miriam's Crime</title> (Strand, Oct. 9, 1863),
     <title>Milky White</title> (Strand, Sept. 28, 1864), <title>One Tree Hill</title> (April 17,
     1865), and <title>Meg's Diversion</title> (New Royalty, Oct. 17, 1866), which enjoyed an
     uninterrupted run of 330 nights. The last representation, without the comedy having been once
     removed from the bills, took place Tuesday, Nov. 12,1867.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA115">
    <p>FALCONER, Edmund.—As actor, manager, and dramatist Mr. Falconer, by which name he is
     professionally known, began his career in the provinces in 1837. Being a native of Ireland he
     found Hibernian comedy best suited to his theatrical predilections, and when he became a
     country manager he quickly applied his literary ability to dramatic writing. Mr. Falconer’s
     first drama of any pretension, brought out in London, was a five-act play called <title>The
     Cagot, or </title><title>Heart </title><title>for Heart,</title> produced at the Lyceum under
     Mr. Charles Dillon’s manageraent in November, 1856. This was followed by <title>A Husband
     </title><title>for an Hour</title> (Haymarket, June 1, 1857), the comedy of
     <title>Extremes</title> (Lyceum, August 26, 1858), the play of <title>Francesca</title>
     (Lyceum, March 31,1859), <title>The Master Passion</title> (Princess’s, Nov. 2,1859), the
     comedy of <title>Dornan, or Looe Against the World</title> (Lyceum, August 19, 1861), and the
     Irish drama <title>Peep o' Dag</title> (Lyceum, Nov. 9,1861). This piece proved a remarkable
     success, and its run extended to December, 1862. Mr. Falconer then joined Mr. Chatterton as
     lessee of Drury Lane, and here he produced <title>Bonnie </title><title>Dundee</title> (Feb.
     23, 1863), <title>Nature's Above Art</title> (Sept. 12, 1863), <title>Night and Morn</title>
     (Jan. 9, 1864), and <title>Love's Ordeal, or the Old and New Regime</title> (May 4, 1865). In
     1866 Mr. Falconer seceded from the management of Drury Lane Theatre, and on the 19th of
     November, 1866, opened Her Majesty’s Theatre with a five-act Irish drama called <title>Oonah,
     </title><title>or </title><title>the Lovers of Lisnamona.</title> The piece was not successful,
     the season suddenly terminated on the 30th of November, and Mr. Falconer shortly after went on
     a professional tour to America.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA116">
    <p>FITZBALL, Edward.—Mr. Fitzball, according to his own statement published in an autobiography
     called “Thirty-five Years of a Dramatic Author’s Life,” was born at the village of Burwell, in
     Cambridgeshire. His mother’s maiden name was Fitz, and this he added in the course of his
     career as a dramatic author to his original patronymic of Ball. Family misfortunes deprived him
     of the prospect of an inheritance, and he entered a printing-office at an early age, during
     which time he formed a happy matrimonial alliance. After a vain attempt to establish a
     printing-office of his own at Norwich, and with greater effect having produced a drama on the
     boards of the Norwich Theatre, he came to London, where he commenced writing for the stage,
     encouraged by the success of a melodrama called <title>Edda</title> which he had sent to the
     Surrey Theatre, then under the management of Tom Dibdin. Then followed <title>The Innkeeper of
     Abbeville, The </title><title>Floating Beacon, The Inchcape Bell, The Flying Dutchman, The
     Pilot,</title> and a number of dramas - which have maintained their position on the stage. As a
     librettist Mr. Fitzball has been remarkably successful, and most of our popular composers have
     in that capacity been glad to engage his services. All the books of the early operas composed
     by Balfe were written by Mr. Fitzball.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA117">
    <p>HALLIDAY, Andrew, born in Banffshire, Scotland, in 1831. Educated at Marischal College and
     University, Aberdeen. Began his literary career as a journalist on the “Morning Chronicle.” In
     1861 became a member of Mr. Dickens’s staff on “AU the Year Round,” and wrote for that journal
     numerous essays, which have since been collected in volumes under the titles of “Every-day
     Papers,” “Sunny-side Papers,” and “Town and Country.” He contributed at the same time to the “
     Cornhill Magazine,” “Temple Bar,” and other serials. Mr. HaUiday’s first dramatic piece was the
     now celebrated extravaganza of <title>Kenilworth,</title> produced at the Strand Theatre under
     the management of Miss Swanborough on the 26th December, 1858. The burlesque ran for 100 nights
     on its first production, and has since been frequently revived. A travestie of <title>Romeo and
     Juliet</title> foUowed at the same house, and his latest, and we understand <title>last,
     </title>effort of this kind was <title>Mountain Dhu,</title> a travestie of <title>The Ladg
     </title><title>of the Lake,</title> produced at the Adelphi last Christmas. With Mr. William
     Brough he wrote a number of original farces—<title>The Census, The </title><title>Pretty
     </title><title>Horsebreaker, The Shilling </title><title>Day at the Exhibition,
     </title><title>The Area Belle, Actors' Retreat, A Valentine, Colleen Baton Settled,
     </title><title>An April Fooli </title><title>doing to the Dogs, Upstairs and Downstairs, Doing
     Banting, </title><title>Mudborough Election, </title>and a domestic drama in one act, entitled
     <title>The Wooden Spoonmaker.</title> His latest and most important work was <title>The Great
     City,</title> produced on Easter Monday last at the Theatre Royal, Drury Lane, achieving a run,
     unprecedented at this house, of 102 nights. <title>The Great City</title> has since been played
     with extraordinary success in most of the large theatres of the provinces.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA118">
    <p>HERAUD, John A. — born in London 1799, was known as an epic poet and magazine writer in 1820.
     His tragedy of <title>Videna</title> was acted at the Marylebone Theatre with success in 1854,
     and <title>Wife or no Wife</title> and a version of M. Legouv's <title>Medea</title> have been
     since produced with equal favour. Mr. J. A. Heraud, whose numerous works in other departments
     of literature have obtained for him an acknowledged reputation, is the father of Miss Edith
     Heraud, the accomplished actress.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA119">
    <p>JOHNSTONE, John Beer.—This very industrious writer for the stage, whose practical knowledge
     of the art of construction has rendered many of his productions highly popular with
     transpontine playgoers, is the author of about eighty pieces, produced chiefly at the Surrey
     and at the East-end theatres. His first piece was the <title>Gipsy Farmer</title>, brought out
     at the Surrey in 1841. This was followed by <title>The Old Mint,</title> and the next year by
     <title>Oale Breezely</title> and <title>Ratt of Rat's Castle.</title> For the Surrey Theatre
     Mr. J. B. Johnstone also wrote <title>How we Live in the World of London, The Seven Toor
     Travellers, </title>and <title>Brother Bob,</title> whilst the Strand, the Victoria, and other
     theatres have been constantly supplied by him with dramas peculiarly suitable to audiences
     requiring strength of situation rather than neatness of dialogue.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA120">
    <p>LEE, NELSON — was born at Kew on the 8th of January, 1806. His father, LieutenantColonel Lee,
     was on the above day doing duty at Nelson’s funeral, and thus he acquired his distinguishing
     name. He was originally intended for the naval profession, but accident turned his attention to
     the stage, and he soon began to figure as an amateur. When Ramo Samee appeared at the old
     Coburg before the glass curtain Mr. Nelson Lee was so delighted with the juggler’s tricks that
     he strove hard to rival him, and at last acquired such proficiency that he was enabled to join
     the great conjuror Gyngell, and perform through England all the balancing and juggling of the
     nimble-handed Indian. Richardson’s Show was then the great attraction of our country fairs, and
     Mr. Nelson Lee became a member of the celebrated itinerant company. Afterwards he gave
     entertainments on his own account, and in 1828 he played Harlequin in the Christmas Pantomime
     at the Surrey Theatre, where he was engaged by Elliston for general utility. For seven years he
     remained at this theatre, and then Yates engaged him for the Adelphi, where in 1831 he played
     Harlequin in a pantomime of his own writing. In 1837 he managed Sadler’s Wells for Mr.
     Osbaldiston, and this giving him a taste for theatrical speculations he joined the late Mr.
     Johnson, and they became the proprietors of Richardson’s Travelling Theatre, whilst for a
     season they tried their fortunes also at the Maryle- bone. Messrs. Lee and Johnson in 1845 took
     a lease of the New Standard, and then became lessees of the City of London Theatre, which they
     prosperously conducted for some fifteen years. After the death of his partner, Mr. Johnson,
     which occurred about four years ago, Mr. Nelson Lee continued for three seasons the management
     on hit own account, but he has recently retired from the theatre, and has confined himself to
     the direction of the Crystal Palace and other holiday ftes, for the arrangement of which he has
     singular tact. Besides many pieces which he has furnished to the minor theatres, Mr. Nelson Lee
     has written above two hundred pantomimes, all 'displaying considerable fertility of
     invention.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA121">
    <p>LEMON, Mark — now more especially known as Editor of “Punch,” was at one time a very
     industrious dramatist. Born in London, November 30th, 1809, Mr. Mark Lemon brought out his
     first drama, <title>Arnold of Winkelried,</title> at the Surrey Theatre, in 1835. This was
     followed by a succession of pieces, chiefly produced at the Lyceum, Adelphi, and Olympic, and
     amongst the sixty associated with his name may be mentioned, <title>Camp at Chobham, Domestic
     Economy, the Ladies' Club, School for Tigers,</title> and a five-act comedy, produced at Covent
     Garden in October, 1841, and called, <title>What Will the World Say I</title></p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA122">
    <p>LESLIE, HENRY — was born at Wisbech, Cambridgeshire, on the 6th of January, 1830; made his
     first appearance on the stage at Ipswich, in August, 1847; underwent the usual vicissitudes of
     a country actor’s life, visiting in the course of two years, Durham, North Shields,
     Newcastle-on-Tyne, Plymouth, Birmingham, Worcester, and Edinburgh, of the Theatre Royal of
     which city he was lessee for one season, 1852 and 1853. Made his first appearance in London as
     Roderigo, at Drury Lane, in September, 1853. Was immediately engaged by Mr. Alfred Wigan for
     the Olympic, in which establishment he played a varied line of business for five years. Then
     temporarily retired from the stage, and became a contributor to various magazines and
     periodicals. His first drama, <title>Adrienne</title>, was produced at the Lyceum, in November,
     1860; <title>The Family Secret,</title> a two-act domestic drama, at Theatre Royal, Manchester,
     in March, 1861; <title>The Trail of Sin,</title> at the Victoria Theatre, in September, 1863;
     <title>The Orange Girl,</title> at the Surrey, October, 1864; <title>The Mariner's
     Compass,</title> at Astley’s, March, 1865; <title>Sin and Sorrow,</title> at the Grecian, 1866;
     <title>Time and Tide,</title> at the Surrey, March 9th, 1867. Mr. Leslie has now returned to
     the stage, and is starring in the provinces with his various pieces, which are all entirely
     original, and display remarkable skill in construction.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA123">
    <p>LOVER, Samuel — born in Dublin, 1797, is the son of a member of the Stock Exchange of that
     city, where he first distinguished himself as an artist. In 1837 Mr. Samuel Lover furnished the
     lamented Tyrone Power with three of his best Irish parts in <title>Rory</title> 0‘
     <title>Moore, The Happy Man,</title> and <title>The White Horse of the Peppers.</title> The
     songs and prose tales of Mr. Samuel Lover have long won for him the firm favour of the
     public.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA124">
    <p>LYTTON, LORD BULWER.—As a statesman, orator, poet, and novelist Lord Lytton has attained high
     distinction, but it will be here specially remembered that it was chiefly owing to hie untiring
     advocacy that the Act was obtained conferring a copyright on dramatic authors. Lord Lytton is
     the third and youngest son of the late General William Erie Bulwer, and was born in May, 1805.
     His first dramatic work, produced at Covent Garden in 1836, was <title>The Duchess de la Pal
     lie re,</title> in five acts. In 1838 was brought out, at the same theatre, his most successful
     play of <title>The Lady of Lyons; </title><title>or</title><title>t </title><title>Lore and
     Pride.</title> This was followed by the historical drama of <title>Richelieu; or, The
     Conspiracy</title> (1839); <title>The Sea-Captain; or, The Birthright</title> (1839); the
     comedy of <title>Money</title> (1840); and <title>Not so Bad as we Seem; or,
     </title><title>Many </title><title>Sides to a Character.</title> The last-named play was
     written in 1851, and first represented in that year before the Queen and Prince Albert, in a
     temporary theatre constructed in the late Duke of Devonshire’s town house, in Piccadilly, in
     aid of “The Guild of Literature and Art."</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA125">
    <p>MARSTON, WESTLAND, LL.D.,— born at Boston, Lincolnshire, January 30th, 1820, was articled to
     his uncle, a solicitor in London, but, as with so many of our dramatic writers, speedily
     relinquished law for literature. His five-act play of <title>The Patrician's Daughter,</title>
     brought out by Mr. Macready, at Drury Lane (December 10th, 1842), first gained him an
     acknowledged position as a dramatic poet. <title>The </title><title>Heart </title><title>and
     the </title><title>IPorld, </title>a play ; <title>Strathmore,</title> a tragedy; <title>Philip
     of France,</title> a tragedy; <title>Ann Blake,</title> a play; <title>A Life's Ransom,</title>
     a play ; and a one-act drama, called <title>A Hard </title><title>Struggle,</title> followed.
     His more recent productions are—<title>Pure </title><title>Gold,</title> produced at Sadler’s
     Wells (1865); <title>The </title><title>Wife's Portrait; Donna </title><title>Diana,</title>
     from the German (Princess’s, 1864); and <title>The </title><title>Favourite of Fortune,</title>
     written for Mr. Sothern, and brought out at the Haymarket, in April, 1866. Mr. Westland Marston
     has successfully shown that the conventionalities and the spirit of the age are available for
     the incidents and the passion of tragedy, and his dramatic works, full of fine poetic passages,
     are all of a noble and elevating character.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA126">
    <p>MATHEWS, CHARLES JAMES.—This popular comedian, son of that distinguished actor, Mr. Charles
     Mathews, was boro Dec. 26th, 1803. Originally intended for the Church, and eventually brought
     up as an architect, Mr. C. J. Mathews ultimately adopted the stage as a profession, appearing
     for the first time in public at the Olympic ' Theatre, Dec. 7th, 1835. His career as an actor
     has been a series of successes in every character he has undertaken, but it does not fall
     within the scope of this article to follow him through the long list of his histrionic
     triumphs. Mr. Charles Mathews is the author of numerous amusing pieces which have attained
     great popularity. <title>My Wife's </title><title>Mother,</title> first played at the
     Haymarket, in 1833, and a romantic drama, called <title>Truth; </title><title>or,
     </title><title>A Glass too Much,</title> brought out at the Adelphi, with a remarkably strong
     cast, March 10th, 1834, were the earliest of his contributions to the stage. Mr. C. J. Mathews
     has neatly adapted some of the most sparkling pieces of the Parisian dramatists to the English
     boards, and his clever adaptation of Foote’s comedy of <title>The Liar</title> (Olympic, 1867),
     which ran upwards of 100 nights, attests the practical skill of a dramatist who is unrivalled
     as a comedian.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA127">
    <p>MAYHEW, Henry, born in 1812, and educated at Westminster School, took a voyage to Calcutta,
     and on his return was articled for three years to his father, a solicitor in large practice.
     His first farce, called <title>The Wandering Minstrel,</title> afterwards made so popular by
     the acting of Mr. Robson, was brought out at the Fitzroy Theatre, in Tottenham-street (January,
     1834), when Mr. Mitchell was the original Jem Baggs. Mr. Henry Mayhew was one of the original
     promoters of “Punch," and has written numerous works, of which perhaps the most important is “
     London Labour and the London Poor."</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA128">
    <p>MORTON, John Maddison, youngest son of the celebrated dramatist, Thomas Morton, author of
     <title>Speed the Plough, Cure for the </title><title>Heartache, </title><title>School
     </title><title>of Reform, </title><title>Secrets worth Knowing, Way to get Married, Town and
     Country,</title> &amp;c., &amp;C, was born in 1811. His first piece was <title>My First Fit of
     the Gout,</title> produced at the Queen’s Theatre, under the management of the Messrs. Bond, in
     1835, when the principal parts were acted by Wrench, Morris Barnett, and Miss Mordaunt
     (afterwards Mrs. Nesbitt). The following list of his dramatic pieces, and where produced, will
     give an idea of this writer’s remarkable industry:—Covent GARDEN—<title>The Original, Chaos is
     </title><title>Come Again, Brother </title><title>Ben, Cousin Lambkin, Sayings and Doings, Guy
     Earl of Warwick</title> (pantomime). Drury Lane—<title>The Attic Story, </title><title>A
     </title><title>Thumping Legacy, My Wife's Come, The </title><title>Alabama,
     </title><title>William Tell</title> (pantomime), <title>Valentine and Orson</title>
     (pantomime), <title>Gulliver</title> (pantomime), <title>St. George and the Dragon</title>
     (pantomime), <title>Hogarth</title> (pantomime). Haymarket—</p>
    <p><title>Milliners' Holiday, Wedding Breakfast, Double-bedded Room, King and </title><title>I,
     Young </title><title>England, Who's the Composer 1 Woman </title><title>I Adore,
     </title><title>Three Cuckoos, Trumpeter's </title><title>Wedding, </title><title>Old Honesty,
     Irish Tiger, </title><title>Whom </title><title>do they take me for ? Two Bonny castles, Lend
     me 5s.,</title> ><title>To </title><title>Paris </title><title>and </title><title>Pad
     </title><title>for 51., Your Life'» in "Danger! </title><title>Who's </title><title>my Husband
     ? </title><title>A </title><title>Capital Match, Take Care of Dowb, Fitssmythe of Fittsmythe
     Hall, On the Sly, Rights and Wrongs of Women, Grimshaw Bagshaw and Bradshaw, Writing on the
     Wall</title> (with T. Morton), <title>Corporal's Wedding, </title><title>My
     </title><title>Precious Betsy, Going to the Derby, Slasher and Crasher, Whitebait at Greenwich,
     Desperate Game, Who Stole the Pocket-book I Waiting for an Omnibus, </title><title>A Most
     </title><title>Unwarrantable Intrusion, Aunt Charlotte's Maul, Love and Hunger, Margery Daw,
     Steeplechase, Slice of Luck.</title> PRINCESS’s—<title>Wife's Second Floor, Betsy Baker, Sent
     to the Tower, Away with Melancholy, How Stout you're Getting, From Village to Court, Muleteer
     of Toledo, </title><title>Our Wife, </title><title>Prince for an Hour, </title><title>A
     </title><title>Game of Romps, Don't Judge by Appearances, Thirty-three Next Birthday, An
     Englishman's </title><title>Home </title><title>is his Castle, Dying for Love, Blue
     </title><title>Beard</title> (pantomime), <title>Aladdin </title>(pantomime), <title>MHler and
     his </title><title>Men</title> (pantomime), <title>White Cat</title> (pantomime). Lyceum—
     <title>The Spitfire, </title><title>Box </title><title>and Cox, </title><title>Poor
     </title><title>PilHcoddy, Done on </title><title>Both </title><title>Sides.</title>
     STRAND—<title>Where there's a </title><title>Will </title><title>there's a </title><title>Way,
     A Hopeless </title><title>Passion, </title><title>John </title><title>Dobbs, Friend Waggles,
     </title><title>A </title><title>Little Savage, Which of the Two, Catch a Weasel.</title>
     OLYMPIC—<title>All that Glitters is not Gold, Ticklish Times, </title><title>A Regular Fix,
     </title><title>Wooing one's </title><title>Wfe, A Husband </title><title>to Order, My Wife's
     Bonnet. </title>St. James's—<title>Pacha of Pimlico, </title><title>He Would </title><title>and
     She Wouldn't, Pouter's Wedding, Newington </title><title>Butts, </title><title>Woodcock’s
     Little Game.</title> Mr. Morton is -now engaged in giving public readings, which are as
     humorous aud promise to be as popular as his pieces.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA129">
    <p>OXENFORD, John — born in the year 1812, at Camberwell, was educated for the law, which he
     soon abandoned for dramatic literature. His earliest farces were, <title>My Fellow Clerk,
     </title><title>I and my Double,</title> and <title>A Dag Well Spent,</title> brought out nt the
     Lyceum, in 1835, and since that period Mr. Oxenford has contributed about eighty pieces to the
     principal metropolitan theatres. There are few dramatists who have so cleverly adapted French
     subjects to the English stage, and amongst many others <title>The Porter's Knot</title> may be
     cited as a notable example of skilful manipulation in this respect. One of the best of his
     early original productions, <title>Twice </title><title>Killed,</title> has been played both as
     a drama and as an opera, in various languages. Mr. Oxenford is a scholar of the very highest
     attainments, and is justly recognised as the best dramatic critic of his time. Besides having
     enriched the literature of this country with numerous works displaying great research, and an
     intimate knowledge of German, Spanish, and Italian authors, Mr. Oxenford is a singularly fluent
     and graceful lyrical writer, and numerous songs and operatic <title>libretti</title> attest the
     fertility of his fancy, and the extreme polish of his versification. In the autumn of 1867 Mr.
     Oxenford visited New York, the dramatic amusements of which city he described in * series of
     graphic articles contributed to the “Times.”</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA130">
    <p>PHILLIPS, Watts — born in London towards the close of 1829. Mr. Watts Phillipa was brought up
     as an artist, and after being the only pupil of George Cruikshank, was a student in Paris for
     many years. While residing in London was connected with several comic periodicals. When engaged
     upon “Diogenes” wrote, under the signature of “The Ragged Philosopher,” a series of papers,
     entitled “Thoughts in Tatters,” also another series of articles, called “The Wild Tribes of
     London.” From this time Mr. Watts Phillips almost entirely dropped the pencil for the pen. An
     accident placed his first drama of <title>Joseph </title><title>Chavigny</title> in the hands
     of Mr. Benjamin Webster, who immediately purchased the piece, and produced it at the Adelphi
     Theatre, in May, 1856. This drama was quickly followed by <title>The Poor Strollers,
     </title><title>The Dead </title><title>Heart,</title> and the comedy of <title>Paper
     </title><title>Wings.</title> After the great success of <title>The Dead Heart,</title> Mr.
     Watts Phillips was <title>specially </title>engaged to write for Mr. Webster, and several
     unacted dramas and farces, written at that period, are still in that gentleman’s possession.
     Mr. Phillips again appeared before the public at Drury Lane in the drama of <title>A Story of
     the Forty-five,</title> in which Mr. Webster sustained the principal r61e. This was followed by
     the production of <title>Camilla.'s Husband, </title>nt the Olympic, under the management of
     Messrs. Emden and Robson; <title>A </title><title>Ticket of Leave,</title> at the Adelphi;
     <title>His Last </title><title>Victory,</title> at the St. James’s ; and the comedy of
     <title>Paul's Return,</title> in the first year of Mr. George Vining’s management, at the
     Princess’s ; <title>The Woman in </title><title>Mauve,</title> a burlesque drama, at the
     Haymarket; <title>Theodora,</title> a five-act play, at the Surrey ; <title>The
     </title><title>Huguenot Captain,</title> at the Princess’s; <title>Lost in London,</title> at
     the Adelphi; <title>Nobody's Child,</title> at the Surrey, Sept. 14th, 1867; and <title>Maud's
     </title><title>Peril,</title> a four-act play, with Miss Herbert and Garstin Belmore in the
     principal parts, produced at the Adelphi, in October, 1867. Mr. Phillips has also written
     several novels, both under his own name and a <foreign>nom de plume</foreign> which he has
     assumed in a well-known periodical.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA131">
    <p>PLANCHE, JAMES ROBINSON — born in Old Burlington'street, London, Feb. 27th, 1796, is
     descended from a French family, who sought refuge in England after the revocation of the Edict
     of Nantes. His first contribution to the stage was a clever burlesque, called <title>Amoroso,
     Kinrj of Little Britain,</title> produced at Drury Lane Theatre, in May, 1818. Since then Mr.
     J. R. Planch has produced nearly two hundred pieces. He wrote the libretto of the opera of
     <title>Oberon</title> for Weber, completely re-organised the decorative department of Covent
     Garden Theatre by securing correctness of costume and propriety of archological illustration on
     the occasion of Shaksperian and other revivals, and furnished a long series of the wittiest
     fairy extravaganzas which the playgoing world had then enjoyed, for the Olympic and the Lyceum,
     under the Vestris managements. In 1854 Mr. Planch was created Rouge Croix Pursuivant at Arms in
     connexion with the Herald's College. The history of “British Costume," originally published in
     1834, remains a standard authority.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA132">
    <p>READE, CHARLES, D.C.L. — is the youngest son of the late John Reade, Esq., of Ipsden House,
     Oxfordshire. Mr. Charles Reade was born in 1814, educated at Magdalen College, Oxford, where he
     graduated B.A. in 1835, and in 1843 was called to the bar at Lincoln’s-inn. Mr. Charles Reade
     has written many successful pieces, ineluding <title>Masks </title><title>and
     </title><title>Faces,</title> in conjunction with Mr. Tom Taylor (Haymarket, Nov., 1852),
     <title>Never </title><title>Too </title><title>Late </title><title>to Mend</title> (Princess’s,
     Oct. 4, 1865), and <title>Dora</title> (Adelphi, 1867). His Latest drama of <title>The Double
     Marriage</title> inaugurated the first season of the New Queen’s Theatre under Mr. Alfred
     Wigan's management.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA133">
    <p>REECE, ROBERT — born in Barbadoes, West Indies, May 2, 1838. Educated at Balliol College,
     Oxford ; B.A. I860, M.A. 1863. Clerk in the Colonial-ofiice (Emigration Branch); Member of the
     Dramatic Authors’ Society ; author of “Tale of a Moderator,” Leamington, March, 1862 ;
     <title>Castle Grim</title> (opera), New Royalty, London, Sept. 2,1865;
     <title>Prometheus</title> (burlesque), <title>ibid.,</title> Dec. 23, 1865; <title>Love's
     </title><title>Limit</title> (opera), <title>ibid.,</title> Jan. 5,1866 ; <title>Ulf the
     </title><title>Minstrel</title> (burlesque), <title>ibid.,</title> March 31, 1866 ; <title>Lady
     of </title><title>the </title><title>Lake</title> (burlesque), <title>ibid., </title>Sept. 8,
     1866; <title>Guy Mannering</title> (burlesque), Edinburgh, Dec., 1866; <title>A
     </title><title>Game of </title><title>Dominoes,</title> Ryde, Aug., 1867; <title>A
     </title><title>H7M Cherry</title> (opera), Reigate, Sept. 2, 1867; <title>Jioneydore's
     Troubles</title> (farce), Theatre Royal, Manchester, Sept. 19, 1867; <title>Farewell of
     </title><title>the Fairies</title> (pantomime), Edinburgh, Dec., 1867; and of <title>Knights of
     the Cross </title>(cantata) ; <title>Wicklow </title><title>Som;</title><title> Gullirer in
     Lilliput,</title> &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA134">
    <p>ROBERTSON, Thomas William — was born June 9,1829, at Newark-upon-Trent in Nottinghamshire. Of
     entirely theatrical parentage and antecedents he first adopted the stage, which he finally
     abandoned for the career of literature, in 1860. His first original production was a drama
     called <title>A </title><title>Night's Adventure,</title> at the Olympic, when under the
     management of Mr. Farren, in 1851. In 1861 he produced an original farce called <title>The
     </title><title>Cantab</title> at the Strand. In 1864 he produced <title>David Garrick</title>
     at the Haymarket. In 1865 he produced <title>Society</title> (which had been previously acted
     in Liverpool) at the Prince of Wales’s, and he this year also wrote the libretto of an opera
     called <title>Constance </title>for Covent Garden. In 1866 Mr. Robertson produced
     <title>Ours</title> at the Prince of Wales’s, previously brought out at Liverpool. In 1867 he
     produced <title>Shadow </title><title>Tree </title><title>Shaft </title>at the Princess’s,
     <title>A Bapid Thaw</title> at the St. James’s, and <title>Caste</title> at the Prince of
     Wales’s. He the same year also wrote an entertainment for Mr. German Reed called <title>A
     Dream</title> in <title>Venice,</title> and <title>For Lore</title> at the Holborn Theatre. Mr.
     Robertson has been active as a journalist on several daily and weekly papers, a contributor to
     “Fun,’’ and a writer of numerous articles, stories, and essays for magazines.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA135">
    <p>SAWYER, William — born at Brighton in 1828, began writing for the stage in his twenty-fifth
     year, when two farces called <title>Wanted to Marry</title> and <title>Eight Hours at the
     Seaside</title> were produced at the Brighton Theatre. A very successful drama from his pen,
     entitled <title>Jessie Ashton,</title> was brought out at the Surrey Theatre, Christmas, 1862.
     Mr. William Sawyer is an active contributor to the various magazines and periodicals, and is
     the author of a volume of poems published under the title of “Ten Miles from Town,” bearing
     evidence of high poetic talents.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA136">
    <p>SIMPSON, John PALGRAVE — is a native of the county of Norfolk. In early years he was destined
     for the Church, was entered at Corpus Christi College, Cambridge, and at that University took
     his Bachelor’s, and subsequently his Master’s, degree. He never, however, accepted the vocation
     for which he was intended, and for many years was a traveller on the Continent, residing at
     different foreign courts, and flitting from one country to another without occupation. The
     failure of a bank, by which he suddenly found himself deprived of his fortune,SIM aroused him
     to adopt literature as a profession. He soon became a constant contributor to Blackwood’s,
     Fraser’s, and Bentley’s Magazines, wrote tales and novels, and other miscellaneous works, the
     most notable of which were his “.Letters from the Danube” and “Pictures from Revolutionary
     Paris.” An intense love of the stage afterwards urged him to try his fortune at the theatres.
     His first effort was a' little drama, called <title>Poor Cousin Walter,</title> produced at the
     Strand Theatre, then under the management of the late Mr. William Farren, on the 8th of April,
     1850, with Mrs. Stirling and Mr. Leigh Murray in its principal characters. His success on this
     occasion induced him to add further dramatic efforts to his other literary occupations. Since
     that time he lias been one of the most prolific of our dramatic authors, and his productions
     have been played at almost every West-end theatre in London. Of his original pieces the most
     successful have been <title>Second Love,</title> produced at the Haymarket Theatre,
     subsequently a favourite stock piece in the United States, and translated into several foreign
     languages for the continental theatres; <title>The World and the Stage,</title> also produced
     at the Haymarket Theatre, and <title>Sybilla, or Step by Step,</title> played by Mr. and Mrs.
     Charles Mathews at St. James’s Theatre, under the brief management of Mr. Benjamin Webster. Mr.
     Palgrave Simpson has produced, moreover, several other original works, as well as opera-books
     for Balfe and other composers. Of his numerous adaptations from foreign sources the best
     remembered will probably be <title>Daddy Hardacre,</title> in which the lamented Robson made so
     profound a sensation, and <title>A Scrap of Paper,</title> written for those accomplished
     artistes, Mr. and Mrs. Alfred Wigan. </p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA137">
    <p>SKETCHLEY, ARTHUR.—Mr. George Rose, who adopted this name when he commenced a literary
     career, has obtained extensive celebrity as the originator of “Mrs, Brown,” of whose adventures
     and domestic experiences the world has, since 1863 acquired an intimate knowledge through the
     pages of “Fun ” and other periodicals, to which Mr. Arthur Sketchley has been an active
     contributor. In February, 1864, he commenced as an “Entertainer" at the Egyptian Hall, giving a
     monologue called <title>Paris, </title>and repeating, to the great delight of his audiences,
     the memorable adventures of “Mrs Brown at the Play.” Mr. Arthur Sketchley is also the author of
     some successful dramas, of which the principal are <title>The Dark Cloud</title> (St. James’s,
     January 3,1863), and <title>How will they Get out of It,</title> a lively comedy, brought out
     also at the St. James’s, August 12, 1861 In the summer of 1867 Mr. Arthur Sketchley took “Mrs.
     Brown” to America, and of her misadventures in New York some diverting accounts have been since
     published. Mr. George Rose was educated at Magdalen College, Oxford, where he took a high
     degree, and was educated fur the Church. </p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA138">
    <p> SLOUS, A. R.—This dramatist has the special distinction of being the author of the first
     drama which gained the prize of one hundred pounds awarded according to the following
     conditions specified in the will of the late Mr. T. P. Cooke:—“Now I give the sum of two
     thousand pounds New Three Pounds per Cent. Annuities, part of a larger amount of such annuities
     standing in my name in the Bank books, to the Master, Deputy-Master, and Wardens of the Royal
     Dramatic College, to be held by them and their successors for the time being in perpetuity, for
     giving a prize for the best drama on a nautical or national subject, to be called ' T. P.
     Cooke’s Nautical or National Dramatic Prize,’ and to be competed for on the terms and
     conditions hereinafter mentioned; and I hereby direct that the terms and conditions upon which
     the said prize shall be competed for shall be as follows:—Each candidate or author shall, on or
     before the 1st of January in each year in which a prize shall be given, send in to the Master
     of the Royal Dramatic College his work or drama, under a sealed cover, which cover shall bear
     some motto or inscription, and his name and address under another sealed cover, bearing the
     same motto or inscription, and no cover containing a name and address shall be opened except
     the one bearing the same motto or inscription as the cover of the work or drama to which the
     prize shall have been adjudged ; the successful candidate or author shall assign and make over
     to the College all his interest in the copyright of his prize work or drama; and for the
     purpose of determining the work or drama to which the prize shall be adjudged some
     disinterested person, of competent taste and judgment, shall be chosen by the Master,
     Deputy-Master, and Wardens of the said College to select the six best pieces offered for
     competition, and those six selected pieces shall be read to a Committee of the College, to be
     chosen by the said Master, Deputy-Master, and Wardens, and such Committee shall determine and
     award the prize.” The prize was awarded at Maybury, on the 23d of April, 1866, to Mr. A. R.
     Slous, as the author of <title>True to the Core,</title> and on the 8th of September, 1866,
     that drama was produced with great success at the Surrey Theatre, under the management of
     Messrs. Shepherd and Creswick. Mr. Slous is also the author of <title>The Borgia King, The
     Duke's Wager, Hamilton of Bolhwellhaugh, Light and Shadow,</title> and <title>The
     Templar,</title> dramas which have been received with great favour by the public, and which
     testify to the highly refined taste of the author.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA139">
    <p>STIRLING, EDWARD — born at Oxford, in 1811. Made his first appearance as an actor at the
     Pavilion, in 1828, then under the management of Messrs. Cooke and Campbell. Alter undertaking a
     series of provincial engagements he went to Birmingham and Manchester, where he produced his
     first piece, <title>Sadak and Kalasrade,</title> a spectacular drama, for which Mr. William
     Beverley painted the scenery, and in which Mrs. Stirling and the author played the principal
     characters. In 1837 Mr. Stirling became installed stage-manager at the Adelphi, where he
     brought out a series of most attractive adaptations from the novels of Mr. Charles Dickens and
     Mr. Harrison Ainsworth. Since this period Mr. Stirling has written and adapted about 190
     pieces, which have been produced at nearly every theatre in London. Mr. Edward Stirling is now
     the stagemanager at Drury Lane Theatre, a position which he has filled at various theatrical
     establishments with the greatest advantage to the lessees.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA140">
    <p>TAYLOR, Tom — born at Sunderland, in 1817, was educated at the Grange School there,
     afterwards went through two sessions at Glasgow University, and in 1837 proceeded to Trinity
     College, Cambridge, where he was subsequently elected a fellow. For two years Mr. Tom Taylor
     heid the professorship of English Language and Literature at University College, London; he was
     then called to the Bar of the Inner Temple in November, 1845, and went the Northern Circuit
     till appointed Assistant-Secretary of the Board of Health in March 1850. On the reconstruction
     of that Board, in 1854, Mr Tom Taylor was apppointed Secretary, with na salary of 1,000l. per
     annum. His first piece was <title>A Trip to Kissengea</title>, produced at the Lyceum (1846)
     and among his numerous popular pieces may be cited, <title>Still Waters Run Deep</title>
     (Olympic, May 14th, 1855) ; <title>An Unequal Match</title> (Haymarket, Nov. 7th, 1857) ;
     <title>The Fool's Revenge</title> (Sadler’s Wells, Oct. 18th, 1859) ; <title>The Overland
     Route</title> (Haymarket, Feb. 23d, 1860); and <title>The Ticket-of- Leave Man</title>
     (Olympic, May 27th, 1863), which was represented uninterruptedly for 406 nights. Mr. Tom
     Taylor, who is the author of nearly 100 pieces, has since produced <title>Settling Day,</title>
     a comedy (Olympic, March 4th, 1865); <title>Henry Dunbar</title> (Olympic, Dec. 9th, 1865) ;
     and <title>A Sister's Penance,</title> in conjunction with Mr. A. W. Dubourg (Adelphi, Nov.
     26th, 1866). It may here be convenient to record that Mr. Tom Taylor’s drama of <title>Our
     American Cousin,</title> through the great success of Mr. Sothern’s impersonation of Lord
     Dundreary, has had the longest run ever known. After being played in America over 800 nights,
     it was brought out at the Haymarket Theatre (11th of November, 1861), where, after being
     represented thirty-five times, it was unavoidably withdrawn in consequence of previous
     engagements. It was reproduced on the 27th of January, 1862, and it then reached, without
     further interruption, its 496th representation. In the autumn of 1867 the piece was again
     revived on the return to the Haymarket of Mr. Sothern, who had acted Lord Dundreary in Paris
     through the summer.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA141">
    <p>WEBSTER, Benjamin — born at Bath, September 3d, 1793, was educated for the Navy, but in
     preference to a sailor’s life he first preferred that of a musician, and afterwards that of an
     actor, frequently in his early career combining both pursuits, and times appearing as a dancer.
     His success on the stage of the Warwick Theatre induced him to come to London, where he
     appeared at several of the smaller theatres with great credit in slight parts. In 1825 be
     became a member of the Drury Lane company, and soon after this period prepared some pieces for
     the Coburg and the Surrey. Since the production of <title>The Golden Farmer</title> at- the
     Coburg (Dec. 26th, 1832), Mr. Benjamin Webster has greatly distinguished himself as a dramatic
     author, and numerous dramas and light pieces, many of them founded on French plots, attest his
     literary ability and perfect command of the resources of the stage. Mr. Benjamin Webster, jun.,
     has also adapted, with considerable tact, several pieces from the French stage successfully
     produced at the Adelphi.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA142">
    <p> WIGAN, ALFRED — born at Blackheath, Kent, on the 24th of March, 1818, is not only known as
     an excellent actor and an honourable manager, but as a successful dramatic author. He opened
     the Olympic Theatre, Oct. 17, 1853, and after four years of management retired from the stage
     on account of ill-health in July, 1857. Subsequently he resumed his professional engagements,
     and on the 29th of October, 1860, he became tho manager of the St. James’s Theatre, from which
     he seceded in 1863. In October, 1867, Mr. Alfred Wigan opened the New Queen’s Theatre, Long
     Acre. <title>Five Hundred Pounds Reward, Luck's All, The Model of a Wife, Watch and
     Ward,</title> and <title>My Wife's Journal</title> may be enumerated among some fifty pieces,
     most of which are adaptations from the French. His brother, Mr. Horace Wigan, has also
     furnished about thirty comediettas and dramas to the stage, chiefly produced at the Olympic and
     the Strand. </p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA143">
    <p>WILLIAMS, Thomas J. — born July 19,1824, at Hampton Court, Middlesex. The greater portion of
     his youth was spent on the Continent. At school he was always remarked for a singular love and
     aptitude for the study of languages, and before the age of eighteen he had not only achieved “
     honours” in the classics, but had thoroughly mastered the Italian, Spanish, French, and German
     languages. Indeed, the acquisition of a “new speech” had all his life long been a favourite
     recreation, and as a linguist Mr. T. J. Williams has always taken high ground. His first
     attempt at literary composition was a tale entitled “The Death of Darnley,” written when he was
     sixteen, and published in the columns of the "Mirror.” He had been anonymously connected with
     the stage as a dramatic author for some years before his name appeared in the “bills,” but his
     first acknowledged contribution to dramatic literature was a farce entitled <title>I've Written
     to Brown,</title> produced at the Olympic in February, 1859. He is the author of two or three
     dramas and more than thirty farces, nearly all of which have “made their mark.” Among the most
     successful have been <title>Turn Him Out</title> (Strand, 123 nights) ; <title>Nursey Chickweed
     </title>(Princess’s) ; <title>Jack's Delight</title> (Strand, 100 nights) ; <title>Pipkin's
     Rustic Retreat</title> (Adelphi) ; <title>Id on Parle Francais</title> (Adelphi, 300 times at
     that theatre) ; <title>An Ugly Customer</title> (Adelphi, 95 nights) ; <title>My Turn
     Next</title> (New Holborn, 116 consecutive nights) ; <title>On and Off</title> (Strand, 90
     nights), &amp;c., &amp;c. As a statistical fact, it may be mentioned that his one-act pieces,
     taken collectively, have averaged longer “runs ” than any other farces produced within the last
     ten years.</p>
   </person>
   <person xml:id="LDA144">
    <p>YATES, Edmund Hodgson — son of the late eminent actor and manager, Frederick Yates, was born
     in July, 1831. Mr. Yates, who is now well known as a novelist of established repute, brought
     out, chiefly in connexion with Mr. Harrington, some popular farces at the Adelphi and Lyceum,
     in 1856 and 1857. Since that period he has devoted himself, with the greatest success, to other
     branches of authorship.</p>
   </person></listPerson></div>
    
   <div xml:id="LDA200">
    <head>BIOGRAPHICAL MEMORANDA OF LIVING DRAMATIC AUTHORS.</head>
    <head> [SECOND SERIES.]</head><listPerson>
    <person xml:id="LDA201">
     <p>BRADDON, Miss MARY ELIZABETH.—This popular novelist, daughter of the solicitor who
      contributed to “The Old Sporting Magazine ” under the pseudonym of “Gilbert Forrester," was
      born in Soho-square in 1835. Although her numerous novels, which have acquired such
      well-deserved popularity, have furnished an abundance of material to adapters, the principal
      piece Miss Braddon has as yet contributed to the stage is a neat two-act comedy, called Lores
      of <title>Arcadia,</title> produced at the Strand Theatre, March 12,1860, and which met with a
      most favourable reception. A slight comedietta from her pen, called <title>The Model
      Husband,</title> was revived at the Surrey, in October, 1868, and acted with success.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA202">
     <p>COLLINS, WILKIE — eldest son of the late well-known artist, W. Collins, R.A., was born in
      London in 1824. His earliest essay as a dramatist was a two-act drama called <title>The
      Lighthouse,</title> first played in private, and produced at the Olympic, August 10,1857. It
      met with a decided success, and enjoyed a run of some weeks’ duration. On January 6,1857,
      <title>The Frozen Deep,</title> a drama in three acts, was represented by the literary
      amateurs, including Mr. Charles Dickens, Mr. Mark Lemon, and the author, with scenic
      illustrations by the late Clarkson Stanfield, Mr. Danson, and Mr. Telbin, at Tavistock House.
      It was afterwards brought out, with the same cast, at the “Gallery of Illustration,” for the
      benefit of the Jerrold Fund, the Queen having previously witnessed a private representation at
      the same place, and on October 27, 1866, it was publicly performed at the Olympic Theatre. A
      remarkable drama, called <title>The Red Vial,</title> produced at the Olympic, October
      11,1858, and, in conjunction with Mr. Charles Dickens, a dramatic version of the story of
      <title>No Thoroughfare,</title> brought out at the Adelphi, December 26, 1867, will be
      remembered in evidence of the powers of Mr.Wilkie Collins as a dramatist. The last-named piece
      enjoyed a run of 151 consecutive nights, the final representation taking place June 20,
      1868.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA203">
     <p>DALY, JOHN.—The clever young dramatist who adopted this pseudonym, was Mr. John Besemeres,
      the head of a commercial firm of long standing. His first piece was a charming sketch, called
      <title>Broken Toys,</title> produced at Sadler’s Wells in 1850. This was followed by the
      capital two-act comedy of <title>Young Husbands,</title> performed at the same theatre in
      August, 1852. A singularly original drama, called <title>The Times,</title> was his next
      success, brought out at the Olympic in July, 1853. Commercial pursuits soon after withdrew Mr.
      "John Daly’s” attention from the stage, but he has since furnished a cleverly written drama,
      called <title>Old Salt,</title> produced at the Strand Theatre in January, 1868. For some
      years past Mr. Besemeres has resided in Calcutta, where he occupies a high mercantile
      position.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA204">
     <p>DICKENS, CHARLES.—This distinguished novelist, the son of Mr. John Dickens, of the Navy Pay
      Department, was born at Portsmouth in 1812. A few years afterwards his father retired on a
      pension, and came to London as a Parliamentary reporter. At an early age Mr. Dickens was
      removed from school and placed in the office of a barrister of eminence—Mr. Chitty, we
      believe. In the year 1834, he began to contribute to the " Old Monthly Magazine,” his first
      paper in that periodical being “Mrs. Joseph Porter over the way.” This was followed by
      “Horatio Sparkins," and “The Boarding House," but it was not until the publication of the
      second paper under the last title that he assumed the pseudonym of “Boz,” as may be found by
      reference to the “Old Monthly ” for August, 1834. Engaged as a parliamentary reporter on the
      <title>Morning Chronicle,</title> then edited by Mr. John Black, he published in the evening
      edition of that paper a series of sketches— the first being “Meditations in Monmouth Street.”
      These were republished in three volumes, with illustrations by Cruikshank, early in 1836.
      Immediately after, he commenced the popular “Pickwick Papers,” completed in October, 1837,
      when the sale which originally was three thousand, had extended to thirty thousand copies.
      While writing the " sketches,” a strong inclination towards the stage induced Mr. Charles
      Dickens to test his powers as a dramatist, and his first piece, a farce called <title>The
      Strange Gentleman</title>, was produced at the St. James’s Theatre on the opening night of the
      season, September 29,1836. The late Mr. Harley was the hero of the farce, which was received
      with great favour. This was followed by an opera, called <title>The Village Coquettes,</title>
      for which Mr. Hullah composed the music, and which was brought out at the same establishment,
      Tuesday, December 6,1836. The quaint humour, unaffected pathos, and graceful lyrics of this
      production found prompt recognition, and the piece enjoyed a prosperous run. <title>The
      Village Coquettes</title> took its title from two village girls, Lucy and Rose, led away by
      vanity, coquetting with men above them in station, and discarding their bumble, though worthy,
      lovers. Before, however, it is too late they see their error, and the piece terminates
      happily. Miss Rainforth and Miss Julia Smith were the heroines, and Mr. Bennett and Mr.
      Gardner were their betrothed lovers. Braham was the Lord of the Manor, who would have led
      astray the fair Lucy. There was a capital scene where he was detected by Lucy’s father, played
      by Strickland, urging an elopement. Harley had a trifling part in the piece, rendered highly
      amusing by his admirable acting. On March 6,1837 was brought out at the St. James's Theatre a
      farce, called <title>Is She His Wife; or Something Singular</title> in which Harley played the
      principal character, Felix Tapkina, a flirting bachelor, and sang a song in the character of
      Pickwick, “written expressly for him by Boz.” The name of the author was not given in the
      playbill. The celebrity so rapidly acquired by Mr. Charles Dickens in other departments of
      literature, kept his pen from this time too constantly in request to enable him to follow up
      his early dramatic ventures, but the vivid portraitures of characters in his numerous novels
      have supplied adapters with a rich store of material for the stage</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA205">
     <p>DILLEY, JOSEPH.—In association with Mr. Albery, the adapter of a neat comedietta from the
      French, called <title>Doctor Davy,</title> Mr. Joseph Dilley has written a nautical drama,
      entitled <title>The Mate of the Mountjoy,</title> for which the T. P. Cooke prize, in
      connection with the Dramatic College, was awarded in April, 1867. A farce, called
      <title>Alexander the Great</title>, is another joint production of these gentlemen, who are
      understood to hold appointments in the Civil Service.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA206">
     <p> GILBERT, William SCHWENCK, B.A. — born in London, 18th November, 1836. Called to the Bar of
      the Inner Temple, November, 1864. Author of <title>Dulcamara’, or, the Little Duck and the
      Great Quack,</title> produced at St. James’s Theatre, 29th December, 1866 3 <title>Allow Me to
      Explain,</title> produced at Prince of Wales’s Theatre, November Sth, 1867 ; <title>Highly
      Improbable,</title> produced at New Royalty Theatre, 6th December,1867; <title>Harlequin Cock
      Robin,</title> produced at the Lyceum, Christmas, 1867 ; <title>La Vivandiere or, True to the
      Corps,</title> produced at the New Queen’s Theatre, 23rd January, 1868; <title>The Merry
      Zingara or, the Tipsy Gipsy and the Pipsy Wipsy,</title> produced at the New Royalty, 21st
      March, 1868. A contributor to periodical literature since 1862, dramatic critic of the
      "Illustrated Times,” a member of the Northern Circuit, and a captain in the Royal
      Aberdeenshire Highlanders (Militia), &amp;c.</p>
    </person>

    <person xml:id="LDA207">
     <p>GORDON, WALTER.—Born at Norwich, the son of a medical gentleman of that city, was intended
      for that profession, and entered as a student at St. Bartholomew’s Hospital. Medicine,
      however, being distasteful to him, he resolved to throw physic to the dogs, and pursue the
      bent of his inclinations in following an art which he had always loved and watched with so
      much interest. His dramatic taste became fostered by his intimacy with some of the leading
      actors and authors, and after some contributions to the Press, he resolved to make his
      appearance as an actor and author. As the former, his debut was made at Drury Lane Theatre,
      under the fostering care of his old friend, Charles Mathews. As an author, he made his first
      attempt in an adaptation from the French, entitled <title>Dearest Mamma;</title> this enjoyed
      a long run, and was speedily followed by several other one-act pieces, but an original drama,
      <title>Through Fire and Water,</title> produced at the Adelphi Theatre, with great success
      (June, 1865), and acted throughout the provinces by Mr. Toole, has considerably added to Mr
      Walter Gordon’s reputation.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA208">
     <p>HAZLEWOOD, COLIN HENRY — first turned his attention to authorship in 1850, producing a farce
      at the City of London Theatre, entitled <title>Who's the Victim,</title> which, received with
      favour, prompted him to further efforts. He had been for some time previously the low comedian
      in the Lincoln, York, and Western Circuits. In 1851 he was engaged at the Surrey Theatre,
      appearing as Bobby Blackberry, in <title>The Rover's Bride,</title> and was next engaged by
      Messrs. Nelson Lee and Johnson for the City of London Theatre as low comedian. Here he
      remained ten years, producing dramas, farces, burlesques, &amp;c., in rapid succession. A
      farce, called <title>The Bonnet Builders Tea Party,</title> was brought out at the Strand
      Theatre, then under the, management of the late J. H. Tully, and its success stimulated him to
      continue writing. <title>Jenny Foster</title> and <title>The Return of the Wanderer</title>
      were then written for the Britannia Theatre, and had a long run. These were followed by
      <title>Waiting for the Verdict,</title> produced at the City of London Theatre, and which drew
      crowded houses for many weeks. The New Britannia Theatre has brought out the greatest number
      of Mr. Hazlewood’s dramas: the most noticeable are <title>Our Lot in Life , Cast on the Mercy
      of the World, The Downfall of Pride, Rescue of the Orphans, The Castaway,</title> <title>The
      Life of a Weaver,</title> &amp;c., His son, Mr. Hazlewood, junior, is also known as the author
      of various burlesques, chiefly produced at the Alexandra Theatre.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA209">
     <p>HOLLINGSHEAD, John.—This energetic writer is the son of Mr. Henry R. Hollingshead, of the
      Irish Chamber, whose family had long been connected with commerce in the city of London. He
      was born within the sound of the “Bow Bells ” he has so graphically illustrated in various
      volumes, on the 9th of September, 1827. Hie only contribution to the stage, an admirable farce
      called <title>The Birthplace of Podges,</title> which furnished Mr. J. L. Toole with one of
      his most popular personations, was produced for Mr. Toole’s benefit at the Lyceum, when under
      Mr. Charles Dillon’s management, March, 1858. Mr. Hollingshead is a frank, outspoken dramatic
      critic, and his vigorous, trenchant pen has been actively employed in all the best magazines
      and periodicals of the last dozen years.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA210">
     <p>LEWES, GEORGE H.—This accomplished author was born in London, April 18th, 1817, and was
      educated partly abroad and partly by the late Dr. Burney, at Greenwich. His first play was
      <title>The Noble Heart,</title> a five-act tragedy, produced at the Olympic in 1850. His
      second piece was <title>The Game of Speculation,</title> brought out with much success at the
      Lyceum, Oct. 2nd, 1851. This was followed by <title>The Chain of Events,</title> a drama in
      eight acts ; <title>Taking bg Storm, The Lawyers, A Strange History,</title> in nine acts ;
      <title>Wanted, a She- Wolf, Give a Dog an Ill-Name, Sunshine Through the Clouds, Stay at
      Home,</title> and <title>The Cosy Couple,</title> all produced at the Lyceum, and acknowledged
      as adaptations from the French originals. The dramatic works of Mr. G. H. Lewes thus produced
      have not been identified with his own name, but are associated with the pseudonyms of Slingsby
      Lawrence and Frank Churchill. The brilliant dramatic criticisms signed “Vivian,” which
      appeared some fourteen years ago in a newspaper called “The Leader,” were from the same
      pen.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA211">
     <p>LOVELL, GEORGE W.—This gentleman, who has cultivated with so much success the higher region
      of the drama, has, fortunately for himself, always enjoyed a position which has rendered him
      independent of literary pursuits for a subsistence, but as his pen might otherwise have been
      more industriously employed, we may, perhaps, regret the circumstance for the sake of the
      stage. Mr. Lovell’s first play was <title>The Avenger,</title> produced at the Surrey Theatre,
      under the management of Mr. Davidge, in 1835, when Mr. Butler sustained the principal
      character. This was followed by the <title>Provost of Bruges,</title> brought out, with Mr.
      Macready as the hero, at Drury Lane, under Bunn’s management, February 10th, 1836. The plot
      was founded on the story of “The Serf,” related in Leitch Ritchie’s “Romance of History,” and
      the piece attained a great success. A novel, called " The Trustee,” published by Colburn,
      further advanced Mr. Lovell’s literary fame, and this was succeeded by another five-act play,
      <title>Love's Sacrifice,</title> brought out at Covent Garden during the management of Mr.
      Charles Kemble (12th September, 1842), with Mr. Vandenhoff. Then followed the comedy,
      <title>Look Before You Leap,</title> produced by Mr. Webster at the Haymarket, 29th October,
      1846, and the famous play of <title>The Wife's Secret,</title> purchased by Mr. Charles Kean,
      who fully relied on the talent of the author, for four hundred pounds, before a line was
      written, originally acted in America, and brought out at the Haymarket, 17th January, 1848.
      <title>The Wife's Secret</title> ran thirty-six nights with undiminished effect, and the
      engagement of the Keans, originally for thirty nights, was consequently extended to sixty. Mr.
      Lovell’s latest production was <title>The Trial of Love,</title> produced at the Princess’s,
      January 7th, 1852, which ran for twenty-three nights, with Mr. and Mrs. Kean in the principal
      characters. Mrs. Lovell, formerly Miss Lacy, an esteemed tragic actress of Covent Garden
      Theatre, is also known to the public as the authoress of <title>Ingomar</title> (Drury Lane,
      1851), and <title>The Beginning and the End</title> (Haymarket, 1854).</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA212">
     <p>PAUL, HOWARD — born at Philadelphia, U.S., America, December, 1830. Was designed as a
      journalist, and visited England, as a correspondent of the <title>New York Times,</title> in
      1851. His first piece was a three-act drama, founded on incidents of the American
      revolutionary war, and it had a great run in his native city. He was then sixteen years of
      age. Mr. Paul of late years has been so actively and profitably employed with his popular
      entertainment (being author, actor, and his own manager), that he has done little with his pen
      in the dramatic way. His best known plays are <title>Thrice Married,</title> which ran one
      hundred nights at the Princess’s, <title>The Mob Cap,</title> played at Drury Lane in 1863,
      <title>Opposite Neighbours</title> (Strand), <title>Bappings and Table-Movings</title>
      (Haymarket), <title>A Lucky Hit</title> (Princess’s), and the <title>Old Folks,</title>
      produced at the Strand, 1867. Mr. Paul has written a short piece for Mr. Toole, entitled
      <title>A Row in the Family,</title> and he is the author of many popular songs and scenes
      which have served us vehicles for the united talents of himself and his wife in their
      entertainments.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA213">
     <p>POOLE, John.—Born in 1792, Mr. John Poole at an early age distinguished himself in
      literature by the burlesque of “Hamlet Travestie," which was published in 1813. His first
      farce, entitled <title>Who’s Who,</title> was represented at Drury Lane, in 1815. As a useful
      hint to aspiring dramatists, it may be mentioned that this piece, as originally written,
      consisted of ninety pages. Its unconscionable length drew from the theatrical copyist Who was
      doomed to the labour of transcribing it, this pathetic appeal—" Oh, sir, your two-act farce is
      as long as <title>The School for Scandal.</title> If you could but cut it beforehand and save
      me a little trouble.” This hint the dramatist then declined taking, though to this necessity
      he was in the end reduced, more than half the dialogue being expunged. His next farce,
      <title>Deaf at a Poet,</title> produced at Drury Lane in 1823, owes much of its original
      popularity to the humour of Liston, who made the character of Tristram Sappy his own. It was
      first of all in two acts, but was subsequently reduced to one. Among the pieces Mr. John Poole
      afterwards contributed to the stage, most of them being derived from French sources, there
      were produced at Covent Garden <title>A Short Reign and a Merry One, The Two Pages of
      Frederick the Great, The Scapegoat, A Nabob for an Howr,</title> and <title>The Wife's
      Stratagem,</title> a comedy altered from Shirley. At Drury Lane were brought out
      <title>Simpson and Co., Intrigue, The Wealthy Widow, Past and Present, My Wife, What Wife, A
      Soldier's Courtship, Turning the Tables,</title> and <title>The Patrician and the
      Parvenu.</title> The Haymarket received from him <title>Match Making, Married and Single,
      Tribulation, Paul Pry, ’ Twould Puzzle a Conjuror, 'Twixt the Cup and the Lip, Gudgeons and
      Sharks,</title> and <title>Lodgings for Single Gentlemen.</title> This list will be found to
      include some of our most popular pieces, and will suficiently indicate the high position which
      Mr. Poole has held in the field of modern dramatic authorship. For many years past Mr. Poole
      has lived in retirement at Paris, from which city he had borrowed most of his plots.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA214">
     <p>RICHARDS, ALFRED BATE.—This gentleman, so well known as the earliest and chief promoter of
      the volunteer movement, is the eldest son of the late John Richards, Esq., M.P. for
      Knaresborough, and was born in 1820. He has written <title>Croesus, King of Lydia,</title> a
      tragedy, originally published by Pickering, in 1845; and republished by Longman &amp; Co., in
      1861; <title>Cromwell,</title> published in 1817 ; <title>Vandyck, a Play of Genoa,</title>
      .published 1850 5 and <title>The Prisoner of Toulon,</title> produced at Drury Lane Theatre,
      March 2nd, 1868, and which ran to the end of the season. Colonel Richards is besides a
      distinguished poet and a journalist of high position.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA215" corresp="#W0264">
     <p>ROBERTS, George.—Robert Walters, who assumed this <foreign>nom de plume,</foreign> was born
      in London, April 9, 1832, and educated at Eton and Oxford, where he graduated B.A. in 1855,
      and M.A. in the following year. In 1857 he was called to the Bar of the Inner Temple, and
      for some time practised on the Oxford Circuit. In 1860, shortly before the outbreak of the
      American war, Mr. Walters made a lengthened tour through the United States, and on his return
      proclaimed his sympathies with the Confederate cause in a pamphlet which was favourably
      received, not only in England, but in many of the cities of the Union. His first dramatic
      venture, <title>Under the Rose,</title> a free adaptation of a popular Palais Royal
      vaudeville, was produced at the St. James’s Theatre, during Mr. George Vining’s management,
      March 24,1862. This was followed, June 2, at the same theatre, by <title>Forty Winks,</title>
      a duologue comedietta, which ran the whole of the summer season, and,soon after, Mr. Walters,
      still under the pseudonym of George Roberts, was brought more prominently into public favour
      by his very effective adaptation of Miss Braddon’s popular novel," Lady Audley’s Secret.” This
      version, specially sanctioned by the authoress,brought out under Mr. Frank Matthews’s
      management at the St. James’s (February 28th, 1863), had a run of 104 nights at that theatre,
      was frequently reproduced, was translated into the French for Mdlle. Duverger, and has become
      a favourite stock-piece on the provincial stage. Among Mr. Walters's later productions may be
      mentioned <title>Cousin Tom </title>(Princess’s, June 8, 1863), <title>Ample Apology</title>
      (Princess’s, March 13th, 1865)—this farce was on the bills for more than 150 consecutive
      nights,—<title>Three Furies</title> (March 13,1865), and <title>Idalia</title> (St. James’s,
      April 22, 1867), a three-act drama, which, though partly founded on the novel of that name,
      was original in treatment of plot, situation, &amp;c.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA216">
     <p>SERLE, Thomas James — was born in Gracechurch-street, October 28,1798, and educated for the
      Bar. Between the age of sixteen and eighteen, Mr. Serle wrote four five-act plays which were
      presented to Drury Lane by Peter Moore, M.P. for Coventry, then one of the committee of the
      theatre, and of course refused; but the notice taken served for encouragement. At the age of
      eighteen he played Romeo at the Theatre Royal, Liverpool— Vandenhoff, Mercutio ; and soon
      after (1820 and 1821) played Hamlet at Cambridge, Croydon, and seven times at the “Regency”
      Theatre, Tottenham-court-road—brought out a five-act play there, and acted the principal
      character, Rupert Duval, three nights. Mr Serle next played a season at the Old Royalty,
      opening in Hamlet—C. Stanfield then painted the scenery there. In 1819, published a play,
      <title>Raffael Cimaro,</title> five acts, and wrote the paper on Ben Jonson, second article,
      in No. 2 of the “Retrospective Review.” In 1823, published <title>Fulvius Valeus,</title> in
      five acts. Played in the country, bringing out <title>Waltheoff the Saxon,</title> five acts,
      at Exeter, and <title>The Parricide,</title> five acts, at Dover—which-- theatre be managed
      two seasons for the committee of the townspeople, playing at Boulogne in the summer of 1824.
      In the spring of 1825, he played at the Theatre Royal du Parc, Brussels, Talma playing at the
      Theatre de la Monnaie. Talma introduced himself to the young actor and author behind the
      scenes, and mentioned him at the British Embassy favourably, which introduced him to notice in
      London. The celebrated Mme. Tallien, “Goddess of Reason ” in the French Revolution, then
      Princess de Chimaye, bespoke <title>Hamlet</title> the second time. Came over to England,
      played at Lincoln, &amp;c., &amp;c. Engaged at Covent Garden Theatre, and opened in
      <title>Hamlet,</title> November, 1825, and repeated it with <title>Jaffier, Othello,</title>
      &amp;c.; remained three seasons, playing with Edmd. Kean, Young, C. Kemble, &amp;c. Played at
      Norwich, and then at the Old Coburg, with E. Kean, &amp;c.; translated and adapted
      <title>Dominique, Victim of St. Vincent:</title> and <title>Man in the Iron Mask,</title>
      playing the principal characters. When the attempt was made on the part of the great houses to
      close all the minor theatres, Mr. Serle took his full share in the resistance. There was a
      majority in the House of Commons for abolishing the monopoly, but the Lords threw out the
      Bill. Afterwards, however, a jury refused to convict in the case of Osbaldiston, then manager
      of the Surrey. Mr. Serle then wrote the <title>Merchant of London,</title> a play in five
      acts, produced nt Drury Lane in the spring of 1832; <title>House of Colberg,</title> in five
      acts, autumn of same year, Mr. Macready acting in both. Mr. Serie about this time called
      together the Dramatic Authors, by advertisement signed by himself and Douglas Jerrold, and so
      helped to found the Dramatic Authors’ Society, of which he was Honorary Secretary for some
      years. His next production was <title>The Yeoman's Daughter,</title> a domestic drama, in two
      acts, in which, with the Lyceum Company, at the Adelphi, he played the principal character. In
      1833 was produced <title>The Ghost Story,</title> two acts, under Bond’s management at the
      Adelphi. Mr. Serle became in 1834 stage-manager at the English Opera, Lyceum Theatre, and
      opened it with an address written and spoken by himself, <title>The Yeoman's Daughter</title>
      being the first piece. In this year he wrote and spoke the Prologue to Miss Mitford’s tragedy
      of <title>Charles II.,</title> produced at the Victoria, under Abbott and Egerton. In 1835 he
      produced and acted in <title>The Shadow on the Wall,</title> at the Lyceum, two acts; and
      <title>Widow Queen,</title> comedy, two acts. In 1836, spoke the Prologue to the tragedy of
      <title>Ion,</title> on its first representation at Covent Garden, for Macready’s benefit, and
      wrote <title>The Witch's Son,</title> two acts. Lectured on the plays of Shakspeare and
      dramatic subjects at almost all the Institutions in London, at Liverpool, and Manchester, till
      he had exhausted the repertory. About this period Mr. Serle married Cecilia, daughter of
      Vincent Novello, the composer, and sister of Mrs. Cowden Clarke and Clara Novello, now
      Countess Gigliucci. Joined the Covent Garden company under Mr. Macready in the autumn of 1837.
      Produced <title>Afrancesado,</title> two acts; <title>Parole of Honour,</title> two acts; and
      <title>Joan of Arc,</title> two acts; was acting manager, season 1838-9. Produced <title>Agnes
      Bernauer,</title> two acts. Altered, arranged, &amp;c., as acting-manager and reader. Read
      through every MS., above 200 in the season, that were not palpably unfit. In 1838 and 1839
      went over all the parts of France connected with the history of Joan of Arc, and wrote a novel
      and a romance, published by Colburn, called “The Players” and “Joan of Arc.” In 1810, brought
      out <title>Master Clarke,</title> a play in five acts, on the subject of Richard Cromwell, at
      the Haymarket —Richard Cromwell, Mr. Macready. In autumn of 1840, wrote four plays on the
      History of France, to be read as lectures, and read them at almost all the London
      Institutions— <title>The Proscribed, The Jacquerie, The Queen and the Minister,</title> and
      <title>Gaston de Foix,</title> each in five acts, occupying about an hour and a half in
      reading. In autumn of 1841, resumed acting management with Mr. Macready, at Drury Lane;
      translated and adapted <title>Sappho,</title> opera from the Italian, and remained
      acting-manager to the close of the season 1842-3, when Mr. Macready’s tenure expired. After
      this time other avocations began to take up the greater part of his attention, which finally
      was engrossed by them. Mr. Serle managed for Mitchell the English Company in Paris, 1844-5,
      when Mr. Macready and Miss Helen Faucit played there, and wrote the opening address for
      Sadler’s Wells (the Warner and Phelps management); produced there <title>The Priest's
      Daughter,</title> tragedy, in five acts. Adapted Beaumont and Fletcher’s <title>Scornful
      Ladg,</title> and <title>Double Marriage,</title> for Mrs. Warner’s management at the
      Marylebone Theatre. A three-act domestic drama, at the Surrey, <title>A Village Story,</title>
      and a one-act comedy, <title>Tender Precautions,</title> at the Princess’s, which was played
      at Windsor Castle the last time any theatrical performance was given there, may be said to
      include all the works of this prolific dramatist.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA217">
     <p>SOUTAR, ROBERT — eldest son of the late Mr. Robert Soutar, for many years a prominent member
      of the literary profession, and long associated with the critical department of “The Morning
      Advertiser ” and “Literary Gazette.” At an early period of his life turned his attention to
      the stage, on which he has since gained an established position as a comedian. His first piece
      was a farce, called <title>The Fast Coach,</title> produced at the Olympic Theatre, June 9th,
      1851. This was followed by another farce, entitled <title>A Deed without a Name,</title>
      brought out on the same boards; <title>Never Taste Wine at the
      Docks—</title>Strand; <title>Quicksand and Whirlpools</title>—Victoria; and <title>The Chinese
      Giant</title>—Marylebone. Mr. Robert Soutar is also the author of several pantomimes, produced
      with success at the Brighton, Marylebone, and Victoria Theatres.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA218">
     <p>TRAVERS, WILLIAM.—Mr. W. Travers, after some years’ probation in the provinces as an actor,
      made a successful appearance in London, at Sadler’s Wells Theatre, under Mr. Phelps’s
      management. He subsequently joined Messrs. Johnson and Nelson Lee, at the City of London
      Theatre, and remained there for ten years. It was at this theatre he first turned his
      attention to dramatic authorship: his introductory drama, entitled <title>A Poor Girls
      Temptations; or, a Voice from the Streets,</title> was a decided success in 1857, and enjoyed
      a lengthened run. Stimulated to further efforts, <title>Il Trovatore</title> and
      <title>Dinorah </title> followed ; the latter produced at the Marylebone, under the management
      of Mr. J. A. Cave. <title>Cartouche,</title> and the Irish drama of <title>Kathleen
      Mavoumeen,</title> established Mr. Travers position at the East End of London. During the last
      ten years more than a hundred dramas emanating from his pen have been produced in London and
      the Provinces ; and the day should not be far distant when some of his productions reach the
      West End.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA219">
     <p>TROUGHTON, ADOLPHUS CHARLES — is the second son of Richard Touch Troughton, of Chiswick, and
      grandson of the late Richard Troughton, who held the ancient and well- known family seat and
      estates of Lady Place, Berks, which formerly belonged to the Lovelace family. After having
      seen a great deal of military, naval, and cathedral church life in the neighbourhood of
      Rochester and Chatham, where he resided for fourteen years, his first dramatic attempt was
      made, <title>Living too Fast; or, a Twelvemonth's Honeymoon,</title> and it may be mentioned,
      <foreign>pour encourager les autres,</foreign> that this piece for three or four years was in
      succession kicked out of nearly every first-class theatre in London, and treated with the
      utmost contempt by the managers, with the exception of the late Mr. William Farren (at that
      time manager of the Olympic), who wrote a letter in a trembling hand to express his admiration
      of the performance. Mr. Charles Kean, however, took a different view of his capacities as a
      dramatist to the majority of his brother managers, and produced the little comedy at the
      Princess’s, on the 9th of October, 1854. The piece was well received, and after a long run,
      extending over three or four seasons in London, was played all over the provinces. The next to
      take him by the hand was that excellent actress, the late Mrs. Fitzwilliam, who warmly
      espoused his cause at the Haymarket, where <title>Leading Strings </title>was rehearsed, and
      announced up to the very eve of its production, when its career was unfortunately cut short by
      that lady’s sudden death from cholera, in 1854; his comedy being found under her pillow after
      her death. The comedy afterwards found a friend in Mrs. Stirling, and was produced at the
      Olympic, under the Robson and Emden management, on the 19th of October, 1857. The dates of
      production of Mr. Troughton’s dramas are as follows:—<title>Wooing in Jest and Loving in
      Earnest,</title> November 1st, 1858—Strand. <title>Vandyke Brown,</title> March 24th,
      1859—Strand. <title>Shameful Behaviour</title>, November 28th, 1859—Strand. <title>Short and
      Sweet,</title> October 10th, 1861—Strand. <title>Unlimited Confidence,</title> February 1st,
      1864—Strand. <title>The Fly and the Web,</title> February 5th, 1866—Strand.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA220">
     <p>WILLS, W. G.—As the author of several novels which have been favourably received by the
      literary world, Mr. W. G. Wills has become well known to the reading public, but his dramatic
      reputation at present rests upon the success of a four-act drama, called <title>The Man o'
      Airlie,</title> brought out during a summer season at the Princess’s Theatre, July 20th, 1867.
      The leading idea of the piece was derived from a German play, entitled <title>Lorbeerbaum und
      Bettelstab</title> (the laurel tree and beggar-staff), written by Carl Von Holtei, but the
      treatment of the subject differed considerably from that of the foreign author, and the
      literary merits of the play were sufficiently great to justify a high expectation of the
      service which Mr. W. G. Wills would render the stage by continuing to apply his talents in
      this direction.</p>
    </person>
    <person xml:id="LDA221">
     <p>WILSON, John Crawford — born 1826, at Mallow, in the county of Cork, Ireland. First appeared
      before the world in a literary capacity, as occasional contributor to some of the leading
      London journals. Coming to reside in London, he, in 1852, published his first volume, a poem,
      under the title of “The Village Pearl." This was speedily followed by a serial story in
      “Bentley’s Miscellany,” reissued, on completion, by Messrs. Bentley, under the title of
      “Jonathan Oldaker." In 1855 he contributed his “Flights to Fairyland,” poetic legends in the
      style of Ingoldsby, to the “Dublin University Magazine. Also several papers to the earlier
      numbers of the “Welcome Guest," when that journal was under the editorship of the late Mr.
      Robert Brough. His first drama, <title>Gitanilla; or, the Children of the Zincali,</title> was
      produced with great success at the Surrey Theatre, in 1860. <title>The Knuckle Duster,</title>
      a farce, in which the late Mr. James Rogers sustained the principal character, was, in 1863,
      brought out at the Strand Theatre. In 1865 Messrs. Moxon and Co. published a collection of Mr.
      Wilson’s poems, under the title of “Elsie."</p>
    </person></listPerson>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
