<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<group>

 <text>
  <front>
   <bibl/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <head/>
   <p/>
  </body>
 </text>

 <text>
  <front>
   <bibl> “American Payments to English Authors” letter in <title>The Athenaeum.</title> (Nov 8,
    1884): p 592 Iss. 2976/</bibl>
  </front>
  <body>
   <head>American Payments to English Authors</head>
   <p>PERHAPS the following facts may have an interest for English authors whose works are
    occasionally reprinted in America without their leave and without compensation. The other day I
    received a letter from a firm of Boston publishers asking me if I would ascertain the address of
    a certain English author whose books are published anonymously, because, wrote they, ‘we want to
    pay her something.’ Being naturally solicitous that this message of conciliation and justice
    should reach the author as speedily as possible, I enclosed a stamped unaddressed letter to him
    (or her) in a letter to his (or her) London publisher. I waited some little time for a reply,
    and not receiving any acknowledgment one way or the other, I wrote again to the London
    publisher. I said that I had ventured to trouble him with my former letter, <hi>which had
     reference to the payment of some money</hi>, because. at the moment, I knew of no better way of
    reaching the author, and that if my letter had not been forwarded, I might consider the
    propriety of publishing an advertisement in the Atheneum, This elicited a reply, saying, ‘The
    author is at present abroad, and will no doubt send an answer to your note if he considers one
    necessary ; but having <hi>many similar ones </hi>[the italics are mine] <hi>from other people,
     he may not feel called upon to do so.</hi>’ </p>
   <p> This last paragraph is so rich that I ask permission to submit it to your consideration. It
    appears to be a fact that there is at least one English author in existence who can boast
    receiving ‘many’ letters having reference to the payment of American copyright money, and who
    can afford to ignore them. It is hardly of much interest to your readers to know that, though
    acting as ‘literary agent” in England for the Boston firm in question, I am no more answerable
    for what English books they publish than the man in the moon. I am as earnest an advocate of
    international copyright as their honesty in this case leads me to hope they are; and whenever
    the opportunity has served during the past twelve years, I have done my utmost with them and
    others in America to insist on the right of the English author to a fair measure of
    compensation. Perhaps, after all, the London publisher may have misjudged his client. I shall
    rest in hope. </p>
   <signed>CHARLES EYRE PASCOE</signed>


  </body>
 </text>
 <text>
  <front>
   <bibl>"The Theatres" [quotes a letter from CEP] <title>Daily News</title>, (June 7, 1886) Iss.
    12529</bibl>
  </front>
  <p> Mr. Pascoe, author of the “Dramatic List” and other well-known publications, sends us the
   following note regarding a grievance which, judging from the letters we receive from time to
   time, is widely felt by a large and important section of the play-going public: </p>
  <p> Is this a subject you would draw attention to? I feel sure it is one of some interest to many.
   In these times of co-operation and cheap trading, is there no manager of a London theatre wise
   and enterprising enough to conciliate the interests of a very large section of the
   middle-class—the hard-working and thrifty? The most of that class rise early and go to bed early,
   and live in the suburbs. It ordinarily dines at six and gets to bed about 11. Moreover, it can
   afford a few pounds a year, for amusements and holidays. Because Mayfair, which neither toils nor
   spins, turns night into day, and chooses to dine when all sensible folk are thinking of going to
   bed, no inconsiderable section of this middle-class is debarred going to the theatres. The stall
   régime, for which we have to thank Mr Bancroft, is becoming an intolerable nuisance. The managers
   seem to think there is no public outside of Mayfair, and we of liberal tendencies (as to our
   shillings for the play) and of Home Rule influences suburbwise are, forsooth, compelled to accept
   an alien form of government most foreign to our tastes. We have to pay 10s. for a stall when 6s.
   are amply sufficient; to wait till 6.15 for our play when 7.30 is a reasonable hour for its
   commencement; and to be content to get to bed at 1 when 11 is an hour beyond which a wise man
   will not wish to be kicking his heels about outside of it. Who will rise and deliver us from this
   aristocratic thraldom? What has Mayfair to do with Putney that it should be thus dictated to by
   an oligarchy of voluptuous diners at eight, with which, Conservative, alas! as it is, Putney
   should have no affinity, Our ancestors, whose rule it would conserve, dined early and went to bed
   early, and got home from the theatre at 10. <signed>- I am, &amp;c., Charles E. Pascoe.
   </signed></p>
 </text>

 <text>
  <front>
   <bibl>“Is it fact or flourish of phrases?” letter to <title>Daily News</title>, (Oct 15 1896)
    Issue 15772, p.3</bibl>
  </front>
  <body>
   <head>IS IT FACT OR FLOURISH OF PHRASES?</head>
   <p> Sir,—The latest newspapers from Boston devote columns to the reception given in that city to
    Mr. Bryan, Democratic candidate for the Presidency. Among other things he was of course
    entertained to dinner. While he was eating a hasty meal, a gentleman representing the Bimetallic
    Union of Boston delivered himself of what he called “a non-partisan welcome" in which he said:
     <quote> Already the lovers of liberty throughout the world are making the cable hot with
     messages to you as a great emancipator of nations. The agriculturists of all Europe ask you to
     strike the blow, and they will follow your lead in restoring prices with the free coinage of
     silver. Seven hundred members of England's Parliament, with Balfour at the head, honour your
     mission. Grenfell, the multi millionaire chairman of tho bimetallic committee of England, sends
     greeting a column long to the "New York Journal" and says were he in America he would be proud
     to wear the Bryan button: and Bismarck, the creator of the German Empire, who has seen the
     prices of labour cut down one half by deminting silver, asks your to break the fetters of
     Europe, and promises Europe will follow. </quote>
   </p>
   <p> It would be very interesting to some of us on this side to know if this be fact or mere
    flourish of phrases. I have talked with a good many people on the subject of Mr Bryan's
    candidature, and may safely say that, as yet, not one single average middle-class Englishman to
    whom I have spoken understands what Bimetallism is. And now we learn that "700 members of
    England's Parliament" -- thirty, by the way, more than sit in the House of Commons, so, some of
    them must be Peers—honour Mr Bryan's mission (whatever that may mean), which is at least a kind
    of wishing him well in his efforts to turn the financial system of the world topsy-turvy.— Yours
    faithfully, London, CHARLES EYRE PASCOE.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
 <text>
  <front>
   <bibl>Daily News, 30 Sept 1899</bibl>
  </front>
  <body>
   <head>[The Transvaal Crisis -1]</head>
   <p> Sir,—That reference of Sir Edward Clarke's to Majuba Hill should be protested against by
    every fair-minded journal in the Kingdom. It is an outrage on the honest desire to be just and
    fair of every earnest-minded, thoughtful Englishman. I have been travelling about England a
    great deal of late, and have talked with all sorts and conditions of men on this very grave
    subject—only lately, with a well-known and prominent citizen of Leeds, Conservative in politics.
    L have not spoken with one who has not earnestly and thoughtfully recognised the gravity of the
    Transvaal business, nor with one who has so much as once alluded to the subject of “Majuba
    Hill,” or to any suggestion or desire to wipe out the stain of that defeat. It is my belief that
    not one Englishman of any thoughtfulness, or capacity and judgment, in ten desires to proceed
    against the Boers with sword and fire. What every Englishman wishes to do, and hopes the
    Government will do, is to settle once and for all the interminable dispute with Mr. Kruger, and
    to stop a course of conduct on the Boers’ part which every man I have spoken to who has had any
    experience of the Transvaal—and I have talked with friends and relations who have lived
    there—says is simply intolerable, and no longer to be borne by one proud of and honoured in
    bearing the name of Englishman. That's the point, Sir, with the average of us, Conservative or
    Liberal, and no other; and, as for “Majuba Hill," Sir Edward Clarke is utterly misinformed and
    mast be referring to a class of young English “ Boer” who, happily for us, is of no sort of
    weight in expressing the real opinion of honest Englishmen.—<signed>Yours faithfully, CHARLES
     EYRE PASCOE. Streatham, S.W. </signed>
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>



 <text>
  <front>
   <bibl> Daily News, Dec 30 1899, p.9;</bibl>
  </front>
  <body>
   <head/>
   <p>Sir. -- Truly one grows infinitely weary of the preachers from the house-tops. The fire is
    burning from below; and when we look up for instructions practical and to the purpose all that
    we get are words, words, words. It is amazing to me, Sir, that you have the patience just now to
    print some of the letters which occupy your space. It is as if one were to ho to some man of
    ripe experience and judgment to solicit his advice on a matter of great urgency and importance,
    and he met your request for immediate help in the matter in hand with a long-winded
    argumentative sermon on some points in the Church Catechism. What in the name of common sense
    has the present condition of things in Natal, Cape Colony, and the Transvaal to do with the
    "Gospel of Quietism," or for that matter any known gospel at all? The fact is very evident that
    we are at war -- and that it is a very serious war, too. The one point, then, that concerns us
    just now is how best and soonest to win. Every man but a knave or a fool, must see that once the
    Boer ultimatum was delivered we had but one of two courses open to us, either (1) to cry
    "Peccavi!" and bring our troops and transports back to Britain, in which case we should, as a
    matter of course, have lost our South African Colonies or (2) to fight to the bitter end, as we
    propose to do now.</p>
   <p>As to what brought about this war, or who actually provoked it, is of no more interest at this
    juncture. I submit, than, Mr Harold Hare's experiences of the charms of the Gospel of Quietism.
    Nor (not to seem impertinent) is it of the slightest interest to the great majority of
    Englishmen, Scotsmen, and Irish men as to what are the particular views of this man or of that
    on the question of how far we can fulfil today the Divine precepts of the Sermon on the Mount.
    If a man waylays you with a bludgeon and threatens to kill you, it is your duty to the
    commonwealth as a citizen to try to protect yourself and to give the assailant over to the
    charge of the nearest constable. If Mr Silas Hocking, Mr. Stead, and Mr Page-Hopps, and those
    that think and act with them., fancy for a moment that their countrymen are likely to turn their
    backs to the Boers and to cry "Dear Christian friends kill, slay, destroy, rob, do as you will,
    I am your brother," they and their followers had best apply for present admission through the
    rightful authority, to the nearest lunatic asylum of their county. Having the courage of my
    opinions, as Christian, I hope, and as a Liberal, I am sure, I beg to sign my name, respectfully
    CHARLES EYRE PASCOE, Streatham, S.W.</p>
  </body>
 </text>

 <text>
  <front>
   <bibl>Daily News 1 Jan 1900, p.6 </bibl>
  </front>
  <body>
   <head>[Conclusion of a letter from Silas Hocking, in response to the foregoing]</head>
   <p>.... Mr. Charles Eyre Pascoe “hopes" that he is Liberal and a Christian. Well, I hope so, too;
    but why one Liberal should object to another Liberal thinking for himself, or expressing his
    thoughts, I do not understand. Perhaps this is the new Liberalism we have heard so much about
    lately. Mr. Charles Eyre Pascoe’s Christianity is so large and generous that he would like to
    see me locked up in a lunatic asylum. After this gentlemanly method of conducting a controversy
    I do not wonder he says, “I beg to sign my name respectfully." Mr. Charles Eyre Pascoe's
    Christianity is not only large and generous, but delightfully latitudinarian. “‘What in the name
    of common-sense,"’ he asks, “has the present condition of things in Natal, Cape Colony, and the
    Transvaal to do with the gospel of ‘ Quiet ism,’ or, for that matter, with any known gospel at
    all?’’ Exactly; the gospel appears to be of no account to-day. The ethics of the New Testament
    are in the way when Christians are thirsting for blood. Any suggestion of peace makes Mr. Pascoe
    impatient, and he wonders at the patience of the Editor; but people who are so certain they are
    right ought not to be impatient, and a man who hopes he is Liberal and a Christian ought to have
    charity. It is little chance the minority has to-day of uttering its protest, and so the
    majority need not be churlish about the matter. </p>
   <p> One thing, however, seems clear. The tide in England is turning. We have been trapped by
    inept diplomacy, hoodwinked by adventurers, blinded by an unreasoning passion, and led astray by
    those whom we trusted as our guides. And we are slowly awaking to the fact. It is no wonder,
    perhaps, that the bulk of Englishmen are angry and resentfui, and are casting round for a
    scapegoat, but they should not hurl their brickbats at those who have protested from the first
    that the war was unecesary, and therefore a crime. Let them go for the real makers of the
    mischief—Messrs. Chamberlain, Rhodes, and Milner. Those who havc pleaded for peace instead of
    war, for arbitration instead of the sword, need not fear the verdict of time. If, however, to
    preach the gospel of righteousness and brotherhood and goodwill be a crime, I am prepared to
    abide by the consequences.—<signed>I am, yours truly, Highgate, N. SILAS K.
    HOCKING.</signed></p>
  </body>
 </text>

 <text>
  <front>
   <bibl>Daily News, 3 Jan 1900, p.3</bibl>
  </front>
  <body>
   <head/>
   <p> Sir,—It is evident that the Rev. Silas Hocking is not to be pinned down to the plain
    consideration of a plain question, which, if you will allow me, I will put in this way:
    Supposing we are passengers in a ship on fire in a great storm at sea, which is the best to be
    done, to utter a silent, heartfelt prayer to the Almighty for pardon and courage, and turn to
    and help the ship’s company to get the fire under, and the ship under control, or to call a
    meeting in the saloon to discuss the cause of the calamity and the Law of Storms, and the
    question of whether we should bend to every trouble and difficulty that assails us, or yet
    trusting in God, rise up and gird ourselves like men and strive to overcome our trouble and
    difficulty? Mr. Hocking invites us to a conference, where we shall probably get little else but
    speeches and talk, talk and speeches, with possibly invective against the Government. Well, what
    I maintain, in defiance of Mr. Hocking, is, that just at this moment we want much less talk and
    far more quiet thought and well planned action. We shall be pleased to attend Mr. Hocking and
    his conference by and by, when the storm is abated and the fire under. Then, perhaps, wo may be
    found to agree in a variety of matters, political and religious, Meanwhile, I am still living in
    hope that I am a Christian by persuasion, and a good Liberal too; albeit my angry passions will
    arise when I find other Christians and other Liberals inviting us to meetings to hear their
    speeches when we desire to be otherwise occupied in any capacity, however humble, that may be
    helpful to our country at present engaged in a very serious and terrible war. May I add this—I
    did not say I would like to see Mr. Hocking in a lunatic asylum. God forbid. I hope he will
    enjoy mental quiet and every happiness to the last hour of his life, and that ho may help us
    also to get what measure we can of both at this particular moment, by sparing us further
    consideration of his sermons, at all events in the newspapers. I hope to be allowed again to
    subscribe myself, respectfully yours (and his, if he will), CHARLES EYRE PASCOE Streatham, Jan.
    1st </p>
  </body>
 </text>

</group>
